Post-Expedition Interlude, Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Laurelorn Over the years, combing and braiding your hair in the morning has become part of your daily rituals, a meditative focus that works better for you than any number of more formal methods and mantras. You've recently learned that having someone else do it for you is drastically less good at gathering your focus, but as a trade-off is astoundingly better at putting you in a calm and relaxed state of mind. "There's a lot of rumours floating around about the Karak Vlag business," Panoramia says as she runs the brush through your hair. "Oh?" you murmur, doing your best to focus on her words instead of the hypnotic quality of her voice, which still contains a trace of half-asleep huskiness. "One of the most common elements is that they're saying you succeeded where Teclis failed. I know you're very Windsight-oriented, but I didn't realize it was to that extent." "Oh, I've no doubt Teclis could run circles around me in every Arcane discipline, including Windsight," you say with a smile. "But when he visited High Pass, it was in the direct aftermath of an expansion of the Chaos Wastes, and it was a path that had recently been trodden by an Everchosen and his partly-daemonic hordes. I doubt any mortal being could have spotted the trace of Karak Vlag under those circumstances." "Ah. Still, it's a very big deal..." "Oh, absolutely. Just because I don't think I'm the only one who could have done it doesn't mean I won't take the credit for being the one that actually did. They've sent a few letters through the Karaz-a-Karak notables that are trying to coax them out. Once they're fully convinced that all this is all real, there's little they wouldn't do to repay what they see as their saviour." You lift a hand to touch Ranald's Coin through your nightshirt. The letters from Karak Vlag made it quite clear that Ranald's Protector aspect had somehow informed them that you were responsible for their return to reality, and the complete certainty they apparently had in that was frankly disconcerting. Sometimes you need to remind yourself that Ranald is no less a major God than any of the Old World pantheon. "Going to bring them in on this Waystone thing?" she asks. "I'm thinking about it. There's other debts I could call in - from here, of course, but also a couple from back in the Empire, one from business in Sylvania and another from the War Below. And from the Karaz-a-Karak Metalsmiths Guild from the Monitor rescue." There's an extended silence from Panoramia. "I looked up that spell you used on the sunken Monitor in your library. Substance of Shadow? There was an entire chapter on how it can go wrong." You wince. "It's a finicky and temperamental spell, yes. But it was risking one life to save, what was it... three hundred and twelve. I couldn't not." She squeezes your shoulder, and you place your hand atop hers. You sit like that for a long moment before the brushing resumes. "So, Waystones," she says, and you untense as the topic is firmly changed back. "You think you can get anywhere with it?" "I know that wiser and more experienced Wizards have taken their best swing at the topic, but all of them were working within the Colleges. The Dwarves and the Elves each have their own pieces of the puzzle, and I don't think anyone in the Colleges have ever been in a better position to bring both together." "Mmm," she hums in agreement. "There's..." she hesitates. "Well, I..." "Jade secrets?" you guess, to a silence that speaks volumes. "And if there were, you wouldn't be able to confirm or deny their existence?" "And I wouldn't be able to confirm or deny if I was able to confirm or deny," she says with a forced laugh. "I won't put you on the spot. If I try to bring the Jades aboard, it'll be through official channels. I've got a feeling that if I dig deep enough I'll find pieces in all of the precursors to the Colleges." "I know the Shamans know more than they let on," she says thoughtfully. "Hinting that you know more than you let on is the favourite pastime of the Colleges," you say with a smile. --- As you look over the fields of the Karak from your balcony as sunlight creeps over them, you consider the matter further. The Expedition itself is still never far from your thoughts as you continue to process it. There's still a sense of lingering frustration that you never got to the bottom of the Karag Dum mystery, but the rescue of Karak Vlag makes it impossible to consider the Expedition as a whole any type of failure. There's a lot of different lessons that could be taken away from the entire business, but you have to assign a great deal of the credit to diplomatic matters, which is possibly your weakest area. There are countless ways to divide up the Expedition - four intelligent species, eight types of magic users, five religious orders, seven different polities, and that's just off the top of your head - and success relied on the cooperation between these very different groups. And you're at least part of the reason that it all worked. That, more than anything else, is what your mind comes back to as you go over the journey. Mathilde will decide on two major themes to take away from the Expedition as a whole: one diplomatic, and one not. Vote for as many as you like from the list below, and one from each with the most votes will win. The exact mechanical effects will be revealed only for the winners. Strengthened Diplomatic Abilities: [ ] DIPLO: Collegiate How independent the Colleges are from each other depends a great deal on your perspective. There can be a lot of value in bridging those gaps. [ ] DIPLO: Dawri You've lived along Dwarves for long enough that your Wizard robes and Arcane Marks are often the only things preventing you from being mistaken for one. But you could immerse yourself even deeper in Dwarven culture and become able to navigate it like a native. [ ] DIPLO: Draconic Fascination You've only really spent time with two Dragons, but both have been thoroughly fascinating individuals. [ ] DIPLO: Interfaith Dialogue Ranald isn't the most accepted of Gods, but you're growing adept at finding common ground with the other faiths of the Old World. [ ] DIPLO: Knight You bear the title of Knight, and you've worked alongside Knightly Orders multiple times now. [ ] DIPLO: Mentor Though you've never taken an Apprentice of your own, you have spent quite a bit of time taking less-experienced Wizards under your wing. [ ] DIPLO: Polyglot If you had been unable to use Khazalid as a bridging language, there were many encounters that could have gone quite badly. There's a great deal of potential benefits to further expanding your linguistic lexicon. [ ] DIPLO: Trucemaker Sometimes the best battle is one you never fight. Every life not spent fighting lesser evils can be turned against the greater ones. Other Lessons Learned: [ ] LESSON: Cartographer Being able to explore, record, and subsequently navigate unfriendly territory is an incredibly useful and often underrated skill. [ ] LESSON: Dhar Insight You've seen Daemons, the Chaos Wastes, the Windfall. You're reaching as thorough an understanding of the fel energies of Dark Magic as can be attained without actually wielding them. [ ] LESSON: Leader Despite not seeking it, once more you found yourself in military command. Perhaps this tendency is something to be embraced. [ ] LESSON: Light Fingers It's not theft, it's espionage. The enemies of the Empire and the Karaz Ankor have all sorts of interesting and portable items that would do a lot of good in friendly hands, from supplies to devices to paperwork. [ ] LESSON: Logistician Warriors win battles, logistics wins wars. Being able to get what you need to where you need it is halfway to victory. [ ] LESSON: Mystic Some mysteries should be embraced, rather than unravelled. You might not fully understand the Gods this way, but you are much more likely to get along with Them. [ ] LESSON: Poker Face Acting like you always know what's going on has gone from a source of personal amusement to a vital diplomatic first line of defence. [ ] LESSON: Syncretic Ranald will likely always be your primary God, but you are branching out into a healthy and respectful understanding of some of the other Gods of the Old World, both human and Dwarven. [ ] LESSON: Theologian You have a breadth of experience with the Divine that would put many Priests to shame, and are starting to build tentative overarching theories of the Divine that many might consider heretical. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - No, there is no Windsight trait. As Windherder taught us, it gets treated as an autopick even when it's a sidegrade, and Mathilde is already near the peak of what is considered possible. - Similarly, there is no 'chain casting' trait. I'm considering introducing a mechanic where it can be learned individually for each spell, but it will always retain some danger and the most sensible path will almost always be to find another way to do whatever needs doing. - Deed / Boon Expenditure is pencilled in for the next update. - 'four intelligent species, eight types of magic users, five religious orders, seven different polities' - Human / Dwarf / Elf / Dragon, seven Colleges plus Ljiljana, Morgrim / Grimnir / Ulric / Taal / Ancient Widow, Empire / Kislev / Ulrikadrin / Karak Eight Peaks / Karak Kadrin / Zhufbar / Karak Vlag (sort of, via the Rangers of High Pass). - Yes, wrapping up the Expedition while also setting up the next project has been a bit of a mess. While it would be preferable to have it neater, it also feels 'real' to have it be a bit of a mess as Mathilde closes one chapter of her life at the same time as trying to open the next. - Say hello to the new avatar, courtesy of the Eonir of Laurelorn (via Total Warhammer). - For the record, anyone wanting to Trucemake between Elves and Dwarves is four thousand and eighty-five years late. That war ended with the death of Caledor II.

Planning the Waystone Project, Part 4

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] LESSON: Dhar Insight [*] DIPLO: Polyglot When the substance of the Aethyr flows through the poles and into the world, it undergoes a transformation into the Winds of Magic, becoming linked to the fundamental forces of reality rather than the transient whims of the Chaos Gods. Light and Shadow, Life and Death, Fire and Firmament, Logic and Instinct. These Winds were taken and wielded by the Elves of Ulthuan during the Coming of Chaos and used to create the Great Vortex to draw in those Winds and return them to the realm that birthed them. An odd decision at first glance for them to funnel away much of the power they had just learned to wield, but the reason is simple: the Winds have another transformation left in them. When they lie stagnant for too long or are forced to intermix, they become Dhar, Dark Magic, an echo of their original form. This noxious substance inflicts madness and mutation upon mortals and, when enough of it gathers, it allows Gods and Daemons to walk the world freely. When the Vortex was created, the Daemons besieging Ulthuan were banished, but so too were the Gods that once walked amongst the Elves. Even after the imminent apocalypse was averted, Dhar continued to twist history into new and terrible forms. The first Phoenix King's son, Malekith, studied Dhar in secret to gather the power to try to claim his father's crown, and when the war turned against him he used it to tear the cities of Nagarythe from Ulthuan, creating the Black Arks that would be the seeds of his future Kingdom of Naggaroth. In the sands of the Southlands, a Prince of Nehekhara known as Nagash combined the energies of Dhar with the rituals of Nehekhara's priesthood to create Necromancy to try to claim the throne for himself, poisoning the Great River of Life in the process and dooming the once-great desert cities to eternal undeath. When Nagash fell, his Dhar-empowered generals scattered across the continent, each going on to found a Vampire bloodline and some entire Vampiric realms - Strygos, Sylvania, Mousillon, the Vampire Coast. To the north, many of those that live close to the pole fell under the sway of the Chaos Gods, and those with the talent for magic were taught to channel the authority of their patrons to command Dhar into the terrible spells of Chaos Sorcery, and twelve times their Everchosen have attempted to claim the world for the Chaos Gods. And their whispers reach further south, promising all sorts of things to all sorts of people, and those that turn their study to the Chaos Gods can do terrible things. In the time of Sigmar the nascent Empire was endangered by the Great Enchanter Drachenfels, and though he was laid low by Ghal Maraz, slaying the terrible things that still crawl out of Castle Drachenfels takes a toll on Reikland's military to this day. The Beastmen were first born from the radiant Dhar of the green moon Morrsleib, and each year their numbers are bolstered by those who are unable to avoid its gaze and prove susceptible to its influence. Their Shamans wield Dhar in a bestial form theorized to be a corruption of Ghur, and they erect Herdstones wherever they roam to draw in Winds and corrupt them, in what you feel must be a deliberate mockery of the Waystones. The Skaven have an affinity for Dhar in its solidified form known as Wyrdstone, and they scour the world for it to power their many clever and terrible applications of it: the magic of their Grey Seers, of course, but also inducing mutations to create their war-beasts, fuelling their technosorcerous devices, and in a form confirmed to exist by you, bending Ulgu into a magical lore dedicated to assassination. That history shows why it is so vital to understand Dhar to be able to counter it, and also why the Colleges must be so very careful when it comes to those studies. It only takes one person with the wrong knowledge - one Malekith, one Nagash, one Drachenfels - to permanently mar the history of the world and leave a terrible legacy that the passage of millennia cannot erase. For this reason, the very document that allowed for the existence of the Colleges also forbade them to ever study 'any sorcery or witchcraft that utilises the wicked powers of Dark Magic', and dictated that any that did so were 'both Heretic and Traitor' and were to be 'put to sword and fire immediately'. Compared to the rest of the Articles that laid down privileges and protections for the nascent Colleges, Article 7 is worded very sternly indeed. But just like the rest of the Articles, it is also worded very carefully. It forbids the study of magic that uses Dhar, but not the study of Dhar itself. It's still not something that is allowed lightly or often, so it could not be said that the Colleges boast any experts in the matter. College theory dictates that there is no safe level of exposure to Dhar, and College procedures dictate that any study of it must have the express permission of a Magister Patriarch or Matriarch, which is given out very infrequently indeed, and almost never more than once to the same Wizard for fear of accumulated corruption. So how can any Wizard build up a working knowledge of Dhar under those circumstances? Well. More or less inadvertently, you've answered that question. Due to an espionage gambit of your former Master, you campaigned against the Necromancers of Sylvania. Due to the... opinions of Abelhelm's heir, you were looking for a new purpose when Belegar called for aid, and by sheer chance one of your fellow campaigners was an undercover Magister given permission to study Skaven technosorcery, and under that aegis you've studied a number of applications of Wyrdstone. And when you called upon the Light College for aid in the Karag Dum Expedition, they sent a Magister who was entrusted with another very rare permission, this time to study the Windfall and the atmosphere of the Chaos Wastes. Through happenstance and good fortune, you've found yourself in three different, excellent, and above all College-authorized opportunities to study the terrible substance of Dhar when most Wizards would never have one. That's the story you'll tell, if ever you have to tell it. But while all of that is true, a significant underpinning truth is that so many of the insights you've garnered from those opportunities owe a huge debt of gratitude to two very unapproved individuals: Baron Frederick Van Hal and Vashanesh, better known to history as the Necromancer Vanhel and the Vampire and later Count Vlad von Carstein. Authors of the Liber Mortis, the original copy of which was entrusted to your care by Abelhelm van Hal after his death. And if anyone in the Colleges knew that, there is nothing you could say or do that would prevent them doing everything in their power to see you dead. And though the tome does contain enough secrets of Necromancy to more than justify that reaction, it also contained a great many notes on the nature of Dhar. Almost everything you have learned about Dhar from your exposure to it has depended on a foundation in its fundamental nature provided by those two. From your many encounters, you boast about as thorough an understanding of Dhar as anyone could possibly attain without channelling its terrible power for themself, and what's perhaps equally important is that you possess an entirely legitimate explanation for how you attained that understanding. Much more prosaically, the other topic of study of yours that has proven vital has been that of languages. It couldn't be said to have been a passion of yours, or that it was all that important for much of your career. Sure, you learned Lingua Praestantia and a smattering of Old Reikspiel like all Wizards, and you learned Tar-Eltharin like most Grey Wizards, but apart from the mystical applications of Praestantia the only good it could be said to have done you is allowed to you to converse freely with Asarnil. And though the profits of his memoirs were welcome, the full dividends of that were not to be seen for over a decade. Then you joined Belegar's Expedition, and through intermingling with the others and then the fledgling multi-species community of Karak Eight Peaks you picked up Khazalid, the ancient language of the Dwarves. And though that proved useful when it came to working with the Dwarves, and you certainly welcomed the additions to your library the new language allowed you, even then multilingualism didn't really flourish into a key skill. But more recently, it's become more and more important. The first inkling of this was during the final battles of the reclamation. An Emperor Dragon waking up nearby and going on a rampage would spell the end of many settlements, but through Eltharin you were able to reach a truce with the Ice Dragon as it tore through the Skaven that had disturbed it, and over time build something approaching a friendship with the being you now know as Cython. Then in what may be the crowning achievement of your Wizarding career, you managed to finagle a great deal of stolen materials and a compliant prisoner into a grasp of Queekish, the common tongue of the Skaven Under-Empire. Should the Skaven ever find out about that, you'll probably have to take the name of Lady Magister Grey and go into a heavily guarded retirement, but even if they do there are a great deal of opportunities that the Empire and the Karaz Ankor alike will have during future conflicts with the Skaven, now that they're able to interrogate captives and translate captured writings. And if that wasn't enough, linguistics truly cemented its worth with the Karag Dum Expedition. Firstly, the relationship you established with Asarnil allowed you to poach him from Marienburg, which is also great for him not being on Marienburg's side should that whole situation boil over. Then during the Expedition, that the Chaos Dwarves spread their dialect of Khazalid to their trade partners allowed you to talk your way through a number of situations that would have been rather awkward without it, or if you didn't speak it. And an oddity in the way Snorri echoed the defensive phrase concealing Karak Vlag - a phrasing that would not normally be used in Khazalid - confirmed for you that something was up and led to the Karak's recovery. And after the Expedition, when you repeated Borek's words regarding the Karak-Waystones to Belegar, the exact words he chose planted a seed of doubt in Belegar's mind regarding his theory of Karaz-a-Karak committing widespread theft against the Karaks, which would not have been the case if you'd been communicating with Borek in the less precise Reikspiel. To cap it all off, in a highlight of the potential danger of a lack of linguistic knowledge, that you were speaking Khazalid to the Kurgan instead of their own tongue led you to miss what could have been an early warning of Karag Dum's guardian, as you mistook their talk of 'Dum' for a reference to Karag Dum, rather than Cor-Dum, Morghur's name in Khazalid. Now that you're soon to be working with the Eonir, who have their own dialect of Eltharin and, you hope, a library bursting with materials in all sorts of esoteric languages, you've resolved to turn more of your focus to the matter of languages. Not being able to speak a language is a terrible reason to miss out on new understandings, and hopefully in the future you'll be able to converse with allies and interrogate enemies without any linguistic barriers interfering. [Trait gained: Polyglot: You've developed a tongue and an appreciation for languages, from the ephemeral poetry of Eltharin to the solid precision of Khazalid. +2 Diplomacy, languages are quicker to learn through study and absorb through immersion.] [Trait gained: Dhar insight: You've observed Dhar in so many different contexts that you've reached a deep understanding of it without ever wielding it. +10 to studying or countering Dhar-based magics, +20 to wielding Dhar.] [Skill increased: Colleges of Magic, Advanced: You've worked with your fellow Wizard of the Eight Colleges of Altdorf on numerous occasions. +1 Diplomacy] [Skill increased: Kislev (2/2): You've developed a basic understanding of the northern realm of Kislev. +1 Diplomacy] [Skill gained: Kurgan (1/2)] [Skill gained: Strategy - Knights (1/3)] [Skill gained: Strategy - Wizards (1/3)] [Skill gained: Tactics - Wizards (1/3)] [Skill gained: Scouting (2/3)] [Skill gained: Logistics (1/3)] [Skill gained: Kislev Pantheon (1/3)] [Skill increased: Bibliothecography (2/3)] [Skill gained: History (Old World) (2/3)] [Skill gained: Linguistics: You've gone beyond a mere knowledge of languages and are developing an understanding of language itself. +1 Learning] --- While you're reminiscing, there are a few feats in your history that might come in useful for more than feeling good about yourself. You've yet to use your destruction of the Black College of Teufelheim or your translation of Queekish to open doors within the Empire, and the precedents for repaying Great Deeds like those are fairly clear. Knighthood would be an option if you didn't already have it, and you could use it to found a Knightly Order or bring a specific matter before the Emperor or an Elector's Meet. But perhaps most relevant is that a Great Deed could be used to gain permission to open an official Branch of the Colleges of Magic. The most prominent example is probably the Hochland College of Sorcery, but other examples are the Wizards and Alchemists Guild of the Gold College in Middenheim, the not-actually-ancient-by-any-measure Ancient Library of the Light College in Tubingen, and the Esoterica Wing of the Royal Academy of Talabecland partnered with the Jade and Amber Colleges. They can serve many purposes, from libraries to research institutes to educational facilities to bases of operations. One obvious benefit is that a Wizard operating as the head of an official branch of the Colleges of Magic is an individual that gets treated with more care and respect than a lone Wizard operating as no more than themself. Another benefit is it makes the headquarters of your branch officially part of the Colleges of Magic, giving them various esoteric legal protections, a modest payroll, the option to bring in Senior Apprentices and Perpetuals as staff, and making it possible for them to attract investment from interested parties, such as College leadership or local rulers. The other side of your unredeemed acts is that in the Dwarven realm. There seems to have been a shift in how you've been treated lately. At first you thought you might have somehow misstepped and offended the Dwarves in some way, but over time you realized that you're no longer being treated with the condescendingly demonstrative approval given to an Umgi that's proven themselves tolerable. You're being treated the same way the Dwarves treat each other: with gruff and understated respect. That might have some inherent downsides since something laudable and worthy of reward when done by a human would simply be expected of a Dwarf, but the warm feeling you got when you realized it, and still get when you think about it, more than makes up for it. You've got four wellsprings of Dwarven gratitude that can be tapped: Belegar's for your time with Karak Eight Peaks, Karak Vlag for their return from the Aethyr, Karaz-a-Karak for the rescue of their Metalsmiths Guild, and Karak Kadrin for the return of most of their Steam-Wagons and engineers. There's no real structure to what these could be turned to, there's not much that's outside the capabilities of Dwarven labour to achieve or Dwarven wealth to acquire. You've entertained a few ideas in the past, but now's the time to turn ideas into action if you want the results to be of use during the coming years. Branch College Headquarters: -[ ] Karag Nar -[ ] Tor Lithanel -[ ] Altdorf -[ ] Middenheim -[ ] Deinste Deinste is a trade and lumber town built on the meeting point of the borders of Middenland, Nordland, and Westerland, and is the closest Middenland town to Laurelorn. -[ ] Mobile Will require the acquisition of a decent-sized vessel of some sort. -[ ] No set abode -[ ] Other (specify what) Charter: -[ ] Research (optional: specify what) Dedicated to studying a certain field or phenomenon. -[ ] Education (optional: specify what) Dedicated to teaching, whether it be of something specific or in general, and of Apprentices, of Magisters, or even of non-Wizards. -[ ] Library (optional: specify what) Dedicated to the accumulation and preservation of knowledge. -[ ] Outpost (optional: specify what) Dedicated to providing a place for other Wizards to work in or out of. College: -[ ] All -[ ] Grey -[ ] (specify combination) The more specific you are with the purpose for the Branch, the more cooperation it is likely to receive and interest it is likely to garner. Remember that the Hochland College of Sorcery went broad, and ended up being a dumping ground for people too annoying or inconvenient to have knocking around Altdorf. You can have a headquarters in one place while utilizing its authority and staff elsewhere. You can found multiple branch colleges by expending additional Deeds. Names will be decided in a future vote. Example: [*] Karagril College of Dwarven War Yodelling -[*] Headquarters: Karagril -[*] Charter: Research (Yodelling) and Education (Yodelling) -[*] Colleges: Grey, Amber, Bright Other possible Great Deed expenditures Spoiler: Great Deeds Great Deeds are the favour equivalent for the entire Empire. An act that saves an entire province would qualify, as would anything that negates a threat that the Imperial Army would otherwise have had to mobilize against. When the Imperial Army is actively campaigning, turning the tide of a battle that the main force is engaged in would count. Incomplete list of things a Great Deed can buy: Raising a topic at an Elector's Meet for serious discussion and contemplation, and anyone otherwise neutral on the topic would vote for it. Give you the right to address the Meet on a topic they're about to vote towards, and your opinion and any points you raise will be given serious weight. Have an exhibit opened in the Imperial Zoo, named after you, and maintained. If the beasts are already well understood, or you can supply that knowledge, they will also do their best to acquire them. Otherwise you need to supply them. Have a Wolfship built to your specifications and put under your permanent command. Raise your name for promotion to Wizard Lord, and if you fail by only a single criteria (loyalty, ability, reliability, experience) it will be handwaved away. Write a specific law or treaty for the Emperor's consideration, and if he sees no significant problems with it he is likely to enshrine it in law. Found a Knightly Order (permission only, Knights not included). Found a branch of a College of Magic (permission only, buildings not included). A trained and mostly tame Griffin. Knighthood, with a small fief to go with it. If already possessing a noble title, for two Great Deeds, being granted the title of Baron and a large fief including one town. Be granted the right to make copies of all written materials within one library under Imperial (non-Collegiate, non-Cult) authority. Provide your own scribes. Example: [*] Great Deed: Found a Knightly Order of War Yodellers [*] Great Deed: Ask the Emperor to outlaw War Yodelling Dwarven Boons Mathilde has broken the Dwarf Rep system. Her Dwarf Rep is now 'Yes'. Anything that Dwarf Favour was previously spent on can now simply be requested, and as long as it can be seen to be of benefit to the Karaz Ankor in some way, the Dwarves that have come to trust her judgement will pull the strings to make it happen. Limitations will be put in place if you go crazy with it. For things that are strictly to Mathilde's personal benefit or the benefit of foreign polities, Boons should be expended. Any future significant deeds that Dwarves approve of will be rewarded in Boon form. Available Dwarven Boons: Karaz-a-Karak (Moderate) / Metalsmiths Guild (Major): You rescued a significant amount of the Karaz-a-Karak Metalsmiths Guild, including their leader, from a sunken monitor. Karak Eight Peaks (Transcendent): For your part in the Karak's reclamation, simply name it, and King Belegar will see it done. Karak Kadrin (Minor) / Engineers Guild (Moderate): They are grateful for the safe return of many of the Steam-Wagons and most of the Engineers. Karak Vlag (Transcendent): They know irrefutably that you risked your soul to tear theirs from the grasp of Hell. Dwarven Boons are a lot less structured. As a rule of thumb, a Minor boon gets you an expert for a year or a team for a few months, a Moderate one gets you a team and a longer time, a Major one gets you something the size of the Karag Dum Expedition, and a Transcendent one gets you the Okral. Boons affiliated with a specific Guild can be called in from that Guild for something within their capabilities for the larger boon attached to them, instead of the lesser one from the Karak in general. Example: [*] Karak Vlag: Build me a College of Dwarven War Yodelling - Due to importance and potential complexity of this vote, there will be a 24-hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - The trait and skill gains were originally posted here. - If you think there's a skill increase that deserves to be on there but isn't, first, think carefully, because I'm going to run out of patience fast if everyone thinks Mathilde should get (1/3) in Dwarven War Yodelling for having heard a faint echo of a yodel at one point. If you've thought carefully and still think you've got a suggestion with merit, please let me know. Topics already broached: greatswords, pistols, illusions, Chaos Gods. - For posterity, Mathilde's final Dwarf Rep figures were: Dwarf Reputation: 134, Dwarf Favours: 32. - Voting will be open until at least 2am GMT on Sunday 25th.

Planning the Waystone Project, Part 5

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Plan: Cleaned Up College of Collaboration -[*] Branch College --[*] Headquarters: Karag Nar --[*] Charter: Research: Studies involving collaboration between the Colleges of Magic, and between the Colleges and divine miracle-workers, with a particular focus on working with Runesmiths. --[*] Colleges (all) -[*] Karak Eight Peaks: To the degree it safely and sustainably can, let K8P gather, preserve, and disseminate knowledge to all goodly folk. Let the tool of this boon be a library and all the books that might be gathered to it, watched over by those of any race who would swear and be accepted as librarians. -[*] Karak Kadrin Engineers Guild: A gyrocarriage With your idea for a branch College solidified, you've sent a proposal through the proper channels, and in short order you're invited to a meeting with the Magister Patriarch and the Provost to hammer out the details in one of the medium-security meeting rooms. "Tricky," Algard says thoughtfully as he looks over the proposal once more. "Collaboration between the Colleges is straightforward enough, and you've got a fair bit of experience with that. But between the Colleges and clergy... well, I suppose you put your best foot forward, there. The Cults don't like any suggestion that there's any sort of similarity between the Arcane and the Divine, but they won't make too much of a fuss about it if it's built on collaboration with Runesmiths." "It's usually the Cult of Sigmar that would spearhead that sort of thing, and they're doctrinally obliged to get along with the Dwarves," Kurtis agrees. "With them defanged the next most likely to raise a fuss would be the Ulricans, and since the first project of this branch would be with the Eonir, the Ar-Ulric will almost certainly nix any sort of pushback." "Where is Karag Nar, anyway?" Algard asks. "One of the Black Mountains Holds?" "It's one of the titular Eight Peaks," you reply. "It's home to the human citizens of the Hold, and the branch of the Imperial Gunnery School." "Ah, right. Well, the distance will help buffer you well from any problems, and being something of a brother branch to the Gunnery School won't hurt either." "'Intra-Collegiate and Extra-Collegiate Studies'," Kurtis says thoughtfully. "With the example given being collaboration with the Runesmiths... do any of the Dwarven Witch-Hunters have a presence there?" "King Belegar's Chaplain is a member of the Order of Guardians." "Then you should be well insulated from any sort of official criticism." "The phrasing allows for the possibility of working with Damsels and Ice Witches. Any plans in that regard?" Algard asks curiously. "Nothing set in stone, but I did intend to leave the option open. Carcassone and Kislev both showed an interest in the Waystone Project, and it may be possible to bring them on board even though they aren't hosting it." "Both parties are protective of their secrets," Kurtis says, "but then, so are the Runesmiths and the Eonir." "What about your lot, Kurtis?" Algard asks. "The Middenland Hedgewise call themselves 'Cunning Folk'. They're Ranaldites and they have a long-running feud with the Ulricans, so it might be difficult to bring them on board. The Nordlanders are Haléthans and as such are largely concentrated east of the Salz to watch over the Forest of Shadows, so they don't really have any bad blood with the Elves." "Something to keep in mind, once you're established," Algard says with a nod. "By which the Magister Patriarch means that collaboration with them may be of use as a pretence for ascertaining their suitability to join one of the Orders of Magic, as required by Article 13," Kurtis says. "Otherwise collaboration with the Hedgewise would make you a party to a breach of Article 3." "That is of course what I meant," Algard says with a smile. "I understand said ascertaining can take quite some time." "Years. Decades, even." Kurtis agrees. "Got to do the job properly." --- "Right," Belegar says as he takes a seat at the conference table with a sigh. "You've come up with a way for me to repay you for the retaking of my home?" "I have," you say, sliding the paper across the table. You spent far too much time revising the wording of the request to not give it to him in writing. Vala-Azril-Ungol vornit urbar kron, karakar kron, dawri afanaddokar kron. Gandar, barar un zintar grozkron gronit barazit dawri, dawi un nadawi. A great library made for and by all the good people of the world, whatever their species. "A library," he says. "Straightforward. That shouldn't be a problem. The staffing, though... I take it you had humans in mind?" "Any species," you say firmly, "as long as they don't act against the Civilized Realms and are willing to swear the proper oaths." "That could cause trouble down the line," he says thoughtfully, "but I don't see anyone but the Dwarves and humans and Halflings of the Karak being willing to join it any time soon, so it's trouble for whoever wears the crown after me. There's been some talk among the Runescribes of establishing something, but they've been stuck on whether or not to restore the Hall of Reckonings for years now. I'll redirect them into making this happen. As for acquisition... how involved will you want to be in this? Edda would be quite capable of laying the groundwork and the rest could be up to whoever ends up being Loremaster after you, but you'd be the natural choice for running this organization if you're willing." [ ] (LIBRARY) Hands-off Mathilde will have no involvement at all beyond this point, but will retain full rights to peruse the contents of the library. [ ] (LIBRARY) High-level policy Mathilde will be able to make decisions such as location, selecting a Head Librarian, and setting broad policies, but will not have day-to-day control over the library, so it will not consume any meaningful amount of Mathilde's time. [ ] (LIBRARY) Head Librarian Involved in all the day-to-day workings, and able to make staffing decisions, negotiate access to new sources of books, assign priorities for book acquisition, and make sure the day-to-day of the library is going fine. Will count as an organization under Mathilde's control, so will cost a half-action a turn. [ ] (LIBRARY NAME) (write-in) [ ] (BRANCH NAME) (write-in) - There will be a twenty-four hour moratorium for everyone to stretch their creative muscles and come up with name candidates. - Names can be in English or Khazalid or both. - If Mathilde goes full hands-off, the library will still operate in the spirit in which the winning vote was intended. - Don't be concerned about ending up with an odd number of half-actions assigned, there'll be tweaks to the AP system when the quest fully switches over to the Waystone Project that'll make that not a concern.

Turn 34 - 2486.5 - The Closing of a Chapter

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] (LIBRARY) Head Librarian [*] (LIBRARY NAME) The Library of Karak-Eight-Peaks / Kron-Azril-Ungol / The Archive of the Silvery Depths [*] (BRANCH NAME) World's Edge Branch for the Multidisciplinary Advancement of Thaumaturgy "Head Librarian," you say with confidence that you don't fully feel. You've gone back and forth on it a great deal over the past weeks, trying to measure the ephemeral but high value of the amount of time it would take against the uncertain but possibly equally high rewards of having ultimate control over what you're determined to make an important and prestigious institution. Belegar nods. "Then I'll leave it in your hands. First matter would be location - like I said, the Hall of Reckonings was being considered by some of the Runescribes, but that probably wouldn't be a great fit for what you have in mind. Figure out where you want it and let me or Edda know and there'll be picks on stone within the day." The rest of the Council of Karak Eight Peaks begins to arrive, and they all make their way over to you to deliver hugs or hearty claps on the back before taking their seats. Word of your moving on has already spread, and of your next project being an attempt to rebuild one of the greatest works of the Karaz Ankor's golden age has put that departure in the best possible light amongst the Dwarves. You listen with half an ear as the Council give their reports and get their new instructions, your mind already mostly on the jobs ahead of you. --- As you make your way back to Karag Nar, you consider the next few months. You're officially Karak Eight Peaks' Loremaster until the end of the year, and though Belegar made it clear it was optional, your assignment is to investigate the Lhune Depths, the largely unmapped series of caverns deep underneath Karag Lhune from which fresh air sometimes blows from Gods know where. The most straightforward way to do so would be to wander in there and hope for the best, but you could also try to coordinate the Karak's Miners to perform the investigation and bring the results together into one cohesive map like you did in the Chiselwards during the Battle of Karag Lhune, or you could search for old records of the Lhune Depths that might have survived the fall of Karak Eight Peaks. There's also looking to the future. The World's Edge Branch for the Multidisciplinary Advancement of Thaumaturgy currently exists only on paper, but you could start adding to its roster here and now instead of waiting until you get to Laurelorn. Johann and Max are all but certain to agree to joining your next adventure, but the other Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks are all already occupied with various projects and employers and it's a lot less certain whether they'd agree. Wouldn't hurt to try, though. And, of course, there's a large pile of ongoing projects, investigations, and curiosities that the Expedition has only added to. Though your debt to Borek has disappeared into an unusual legal limbo where it would take a team of Loremasters decades to decide what should come of it, the items that gold purchased are still very much real, and there's quite a list of observations and mysteries that need putting to paper. There always seems to be so much more to do than you have time to do it in, but you must admit that's preferable to things being the other way around. Mandatory Actions: Pick one from each category. Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Recruit him into the research branch of WEB-MAT (NEW) [ ] MAX: Recruit him into the library of KAU (NEW) [ ] MAX: Recruit him into the EIC (NEW) [ ] MAX: Recruit him out of pocket (NEW) [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his metalworking studies. [ ] MAX: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Write a paper: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which. Must be taken with a 'dictate' action. Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Recruit him into the research branch of WEB-MAT (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Recruit him into the library of KAU (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Recruit him into the EIC (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Recruit him out of pocket (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Have him continue to teach Adela what he knows of engineering. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit someone into the research branch of WEB-MAT (specify who) (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit someone into the library of KAU (specify who) (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Continue to work with Panoramia with implementing the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. (NEW-ish) [ ] DUCK: Panoramia's about ready to test for Magister, but she's putting it off because she doesn't have a lot of free time to prepare. Work with her to help make the most of every spare minute. [ ] DUCK: Aid Hubert in his search for a Familiar. [ ] DUCK: Each of your three ducklings can fight in melee. Spar with them, and teach them what you can. [ ] DUCK: Study an artefact with one of the Journeymen: specify who and which. The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 175 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Expansion along the Aver EIC Handler: The Hochlander [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. Will remove this section from future turns and regain the half-turn invested in it. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in your fief. [ ] EIC: Suggest Eike spend a few weeks in Karak Eight Peaks, so she can grow familiar with Dwarves and their ways. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Julia to find out if she's interested in being poached or passing on information. [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Improve and expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (optional: specify how) [ ] EIC: Have a blackpowder factory built in Wurtbad. [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. Personal Actions: you have four actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. Current overwork status: [-] [+] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. Current Task: Investigate the Lhune Depths (optional) [ ] Seek any pre-Time of Woes information on the Lhune Depths that may have survived the Karak's fall [ ] Organize and coordinate investigations by Miners and Prospectors and collate the information they gather into a unified map (optional: specify priority) [ ] Personally explore the Lhune Depths (optional: specify priority) Spoiler: Qrech Qrech [ ] Despite him considering it treasonous, push Qrech to share the Moulder dialect of Queekish. [ ] Despite him considering it blasphemous, push Qrech to share High Queekish. Qrech Gambits (can be taken for free alongside a Qrech option): [ ] Convince Qrech that you seek an arrangement with Clan Moulder, and that you will release him as an ambassador for that arrangement once you are satisfied he'll cooperate. [ ] Convince Qrech that the Under-Empire has no way of knowing he's even alive, and that he should prioritize the comfort with which he will live the rest of his life. [ ] Convince Qrech you're ambitious and loyal only to yourself, and you're willing to repay his cooperation in ways that will benefit the Under-Empire. [ ] Other (write in) Self-Improvement: [ ] Challenge Dragomas for the title of Supreme Matriarch (NEW) [ ] Ask an acquaintance to train you in a skill: specify who and what. [ ] Attempt to learn a spell from scrolls (specify which, will be harder than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Hire a trainer to come to Eight Peaks and teach you: specify what. (costs favours College trainers, money for human ones, Dwarf trainers are free) [ ] Travel to the Grey College and attend lessons there. (1 College Favour per class; 100gc can be paid instead for non-magical classes) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Gain enough control of your unruly shadow to still it temporarily. [ ] Gain enough control of your attraction to smoke and gases to have it collect away from your face. [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [ ] Have one of Prince Gotri's pilots teach you to fly a Gyrocarriage (NEW-ish). [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] Dictate papers: select which two, must be taken with Max's 'receive dictation'. [ ] Investigate the possibility of using one Wind to directly manipulate another. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. Aethyric Vitae (14 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item with a Fiendishly Complex or easier spell (specify what and which) [ ] Attempt to enchant an object to translate Windsight into a visual image. [ ] Attempt to deepen your skill with Enchantment (will be more difficult than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to codify Rite of Way so that others can learn it [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff from mundane materials. [ ] Turn a staff from the horn of a Storm Dragon. Karag Nar Penthouse: each turn, you get ONE free choice in this category. Additional selections cost actions. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have a tower built atop Karag Nar: -100gc for 1 room, bonus to room's purpose. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Build a basic tower of single-Wind environments for each of the 'missing' Winds: Light, Amber, Amethyst, and Gold: 300gc for four towers. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have additional rooms excavated underneath your Penthouse: -150gc for 6 rooms. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have firing platforms built around the Penthouse so that it can be defended from flyers or climbers without granting access to it. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add preservation Runes to your library. [ ] PENTHOUSE: No additional construction. Setting up rooms for specific purposes will have to wait until new rooms are constructed or excavated. Only one construction or excavation can take place at a time, but you can do one of each. Building downwards will increase by 1 each time; second set of excavated rooms will be 3 rooms, third will be 4, and so on. Building upwards can be added upon; towers can be added on to or additional towers can be built. The distinction between the two is entirely cosmetic. Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in the Sylvanian campaign (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Marienburg affair (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Black Waters project (specify how) Personal Relations: [ ] Attempt to recruit Egrimm van Horstmann into WEB-MAT (NEW) [ ] Spend time assisting with a fellow councillor's task: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Books and rubbings from an Asur explorer of Lustria and the Southlands Golden Arm Ghyran Nut Kurgan Shrine to Mannsleib Kurgan enchanted weapons Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Daemonic Concealment of Karak Vlag (FRESH) Observations on the Windfall north of the Dark Lands (FRESH) Observations on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes (FRESH) Observations of Karag Dum and its unusual guardian (FRESH) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ulgu (FRESH) Windsoak Mushrooms - Aqshy(FRESH) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghyran (FRESH) Windsoak Mushrooms - Azyr (FRESH) Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (FADING) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition. (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual. (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae. (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. Windsoak Mushrooms (missing: Chamon, Hysh, Shyish, Ghur) The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty Separate Vote: The Library of Kron-Azril-Ungol Establish the site of the KAU: [ ] [KAU] In Karag Nar, just below your Penthouse [ ] [KAU] In Karag Nar, easily accessible from the entrance [ ] [KAU] In Kvinn-Wyr, with an entrance from the Eastern Valley [ ] [KAU] In the Hall of Reckonings, far below the Citadel [ ] [KAU] In the Silver Tower, an ancient structure on the southwestern face of Karagril [ ] [KAU] In Karag Zilfin, just below Cython's territory [ ] [KAU] The Lhune Depths, below Karag Lhune [ ] [KAU] Other (write in) - There will be a thirty hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format, with the library location vote separate. - In the quite likely event of there being anything I've missed, including potential papers from the Expedition, please let me know. - The library does not cost you any actions to run for this turn. The action costs of institutions will be overhauled for next turn. - There will not be Duckling Club actions after this turn. - You have a -10 to all rolls this turn due to overwork performed in the lead-up to the Expedition.

Turn 34 Results - 2486.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Plan Efficiency, EIC, and Swords -[*] MAX: Recruit him into the research branch of WEB-MAT -[*] JOHANN: Recruit him into the research branch of WEB-MAT -[*] DUCK: Continue to work with Panoramia with implementing the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. -[*] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (Cult of Karnos, Talabecland) -[*] Suggest Eike spend a few weeks in Karak Eight Peaks, so she can grow familiar with Dwarves and their ways. -[*] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. -[*] Investigate the possibility of using one Wind to directly manipulate another. -[*] Attempt to recruit Egrimm van Horstmann into WEB-MAT --[*] COIN: Gambler -[*] SERENITY: Write a paper: Daemonic Concealment of Karak Vlag -[*] PENTHOUSE: Build a basic tower of single-Wind environments for each of the 'missing' Winds: Light, Amber, Amethyst, and Gold [*] [KAU] In Kvinn-Wyr, with an entrance from the Eastern Valley "Yes," Maximilian says, almost before you finish explaining the purpose of the World's Edge Branch for the Multidisciplinary Advancement of Thaumaturgy and your intention to recruit the two Gold Wizards. Johann takes a moment longer to consider it. "Any other research branch, I'd have my doubts how well I'd fit into it," he eventually says. "But I've seen how you do research. I think it would be a good fit." You smile, doing your best to show how pleased you are without also showing your relief. "While the branch would be based out of Karag Nar, the first major project would be based in Tor Lithanel. I've secured a gyrocarriage for transport between here and there, but you would be spending a lot of time amongst the Elves of Laurelorn. Would that be a problem?" "Do they speak Reikspiel?" Johann asks. "Some would, since they're trying to build bridges with the Middenlanders. We could sort out a translator or some other arrangement." "Would we have access to a forge?" Max asks. You give it some thought. "I would say so," you eventually conclude. "They respect trees, but they're willing to sacrifice them to necessity. Maybe their forges are fuelled by windthrow or something like that. Worst case scenario, we could import peat-coal and set one up." "Then I won't have any trouble continuing my studies," Max says. "There's sure to be other troubles, but we'll deal with them as they come. Now," you pull the cover off the chalkboard you'd prepared earlier, revealing a very rough sketch of the Old World with the known major Waystone nexuses marked. "Obviously the entire problem we're trying to solve is that we don't understand the Waystone network that well, but let's make sure we're all on the same page with what we do know. Have either of you gone through the Waystone course at the Colleges?" "As an apprentice," Max says uncertainly. "I think I remember some of it." "I was warned not to try to cast Breach the Unknown on any part of it. Apparently the spell tries to encompass the entire network, and you probably won't survive to see Frederheim." "On the most basic level, the Waystone network is a worldwide network of artificial leylines that keeps reality from being drowned by the magical energy constantly flowing in from the poles. Without it, the entire world would be in the same state as the Chaos Wastes. All that energy is funnelled over to the Great Vortex at the centre of Ulthuan, and from there..." you tap the question mark at the heart of your sketch of Ulthuan on the chalkboard, floating off the coast of Bretonnia. "Well, our best guess is it's dumped back into the Warp, but we don't know for sure. We think at least some of the energy goes to keeping the island of Ulthuan afloat, and there's a lot of theories about what else they might tap into it for." "They'd be stupid not to make the most of it," Johann says, nodding. "Dwarven writing on the subject calls them duplicitous for it, saying they like to paint themselves as noble saviours of the world even though they're benefiting from having access to so much magical energy. But Dwarves aren't exactly unbiased on the matter." You twirl a piece of chalk in your fingers distractedly as you consider the map. "A big part of the mystery is that the network isn't just an Elven creation. The heart of it was supposedly an adaptation of an already-existing network built by precursors to the Elves, which we know basically nothing of. They started building entirely Elven Waystones throughout the world, but that didn't last long until they entered into their Golden Age partnership with the Dwarves and started incorporating Runecraft into the Waystones, and as far as I've been able to uncover, the details of those Runes are no longer known to modern Runesmiths." You sigh. "Dwarven philosophy says that it's better for knowledge to be lost entirely than taught to the unworthy, so they only ever record the least of their secrets. So when they had to turn all their attention to military matters just to survive the Times of Woes, a lot of knowledge was lost simply because there was no time to pass it on even to the deserving. But to acknowledge that would be to acknowledge a major flaw at the very heart of their culture. Modern Dwarves have to choose between seeing their Ancestors as flawed or themselves as undeserving, and most pick the latter." The silence stretches as you brood on that. "So," Johann eventually says, "Runes are why we don't understand Waystones?" "Right, Waystones. Well, Runes are a big part of it. The Elves being unwilling to tell us whatever they still know is another - most of what I've just said is pieced together from offhand comments Teclis made to the first Magisters. But a third problem is that there's a lot more to the network than Ulthuan's Waystones, even when you account for the differences between purely Elven and Elven-Dwarven hybrid designs. From the runes found on them, they're believed by most to have been made by early human tribes - Belthani in the west, Scythians in the east." "They're extinct, aren't they?" Johann asks. "When I was reading up on the Kurgans, the books said that they wiped out the Scythians." "The Kurgan say they're the inheritors of the Scythians, but it's unclear if that's from descent or conquest. The Kislevites claim that the Gospodars were descendants of the Scythians, but that might just be to bolster their land claims. I've seen theories that the Roppsmenn were Scythian remnants, and others that there are tribes even further east that might be. As for the Belthani, they were variously displaced and absorbed by the Pre-Imperial Tribes when they entered the Reik basin. Some say the beliefs of the Taalites and Rhyans descend from them, or the Damsels do, others say there are still secret cults keeping Belthani beliefs alive, and some say the founders of the Jade or Amber Orders were drawn from them. Some even say there's some secret island off the coast of Bretonnia where the Belthani still thrive, but that's never seemed plausible to me. So if that information is still out there, I'm going to have to try to winkle it out of someone who won't even openly claim they have it." "Where do the Wood Elves come into this?" Johann asks. "Eonir," you correct. "They were originally a colony of Ulthuan, and they've indicated they have at least some of the information Ulthuan has, and for reasons I can't get into, I believe them. They've also said that they're willing to share it, which is why we'll be partnering with them. They have a variety of plant they cultivate that acts as a tributary to the Waystone network, though I'm not sure if that was an original part of the network, or if it postdates or even predates it." Max looks up from the notes he's been taking. "So by my count, you've got four nations, three tribes, four Cults, and two Orders that could all have pieces of the puzzle, and most of them aren't inclined to share, and some of them might not even still exist." "At least." You hadn't mentioned the Hedgewise, after all. "Well," he says, "at least it won't be boring." --- A question in your correspondences with Lord Magister Kurtis Krammovitch: how important is the Waystone Project? Well, you would say very important. It could allow for the expansion of the Dwarven network. It could end conflict between Karaz-a-Karak and Karak Eight Peaks. It could drive back the malign energies of Sylvania, of Mousillon, of Troll Country, of the Blighted Marsh. It could reclaim the Badlands, heal the Dark Lands, revive Nehekhara, push back the Chaos Wastes. It could save the world. Could, could, could. Your response to him focuses instead on would. It would build a new connection with the notoriously isolationist Eonir. It would be meeting Elves as equal partners in a research project. It would accelerate the normalization of relations with Laurelorn. It would give the Empire greater insight and influence into the source of tensions between Nordland and Middenland. It would give the Empire another line of communication with Ulthuan, and counterbalance their financial interest in Marienburg with their desire to rebuild relations with their former colonies. This approach bears fruit in the form of a letter full of banalities that translate into a time and a place, and as the sun barely begins to peek over the walls of Altdorf you make your way through the mists of Tempelgarten. In the center of a bubble of mist keeping a respectful distance you see the person you are here to meet: Lady Magister Mira, former Magister Matriarch of the Light Order, at least a foot taller than you and clad from neck to toe - well, neckline to toe - in white. Whatever internal mechanisms keep Alric in power have also resulted in power being ceded to her on multiple occasions, albeit temporarily, and if there's anyone that can loosen Alric's grip on Egrimm, it's her. "Lady Magister," she murmurs as you approach, the thrum of her voice pushing back the fog another foot. "Lady Magister," you reply as you take a seat on the bench next to her. "Thank you for meeting me." "Thank you for the seed of a solution to the Drakwald issue. Dear Dragomas has been trying to make overtures to them for quite some time." She flicks a finger and a marble-sized ball of light shoots out, causing a quack of complaint from a perhaps overly-inquisitive duck. "You think our Egrimm could help?" "We worked together well on the Expedition, against enemies and mysteries alike. This project is going to call for as much cooperation between the Orders as we can muster." "And if even the Lights are putting their trust in this little Shadowmancer, so can you," she says with a smile. "Quite ambitious of you. But many a researcher among the Light Wizards has spent fruitless years obsessed with the Waystones, filling books with questions without ever stumbling across an answer. What makes you think you can outdo them?" "I don't, and I'm not trying to," you retort. "Egrimm and I studied the Windfall because Dwarven artifice let us reach it. Every paper I have written owes much to doing so behind Dwarven walls and while referencing Dwarven tomes. When Waaagh Birdmuncha died, it was not just me, it was as much Runelord Kragg and High Priest Gunnars. If I am going to see further, it will be by standing on the shoulders of Dwarves." "Which is something the Golds have been trying to achieve for some time," she observes. "Have they achieved it, through you?" "I have two Magisters of The Golden Order who will be contributing to the project. And now I am offering the same to one of yours." "Clever answer," she says after a moment's thought. "Sometimes we say that any idiot can be a Light Wizard in the sun, their true test comes in the depths of night. If the inverse can be said of your kind, you could be said to be doing very well indeed." "Thank you," you say, trying to sound sincere. "Have you ever visited our grounds?" "Yes, when I met with the Magister Patriarch." "You may have observed that it was not a capstone standing alone, high in the sky, but an enormous structure built of many pieces. A fact that the person you met could stand to be reminded of." She muses a moment longer, watching the first rays of sunlight stretch over the water. "Come the new year, pay a visit to Wizards and Alchemists Guild in Middenheim. You may find waiting there a new and luminescent recruit for your burgeoning project." "Thank you," you say simply. The smile she gives in reply seems to owe nothing to friendliness. "No thanks necessary. The pleasure will be mine." --- As many know, Necromancy is a form of magic wherein the caster manipulates Shyish which in turn manipulates Dhar, and in doing so is able to tap into the power of Dhar without the caster coming into direct contact with it. Where a human directly wielding Dhar will be driven insane in short order, a Necromancer can go many years without going mad, and even then that madness comes from the environmental Dhar that Necromancers tend to surround themselves with, rather than as a direct result of their spellcasting. A question presents itself: if Necromancers can use one form of magic to manipulate another, can other combinations be achieved? The answer: Probably. Wild Magic, the magic of Beastmen, is often suspected to be a corruption of Ghur in a similar manner. Your answer: Definitely. You saw for yourself a Clan Eshin magic-user wielding a combination of Dhar and Ulgu. Another, safer question: can a combination be achieved that doesn't involve Dhar? The answer: Possibly, but any misstep might cause Dhar or a miscast, so it would be terribly dangerous. At least, it would be for someone who doesn't already have at least a theoretical grasp on the techniques of a Dhar based magic, which no Magister should ever have. So it would be folly to even try. Your answer: A significant, thoughtful silence. One that's been lurking in the back of your mind for quite some time. To make the attempt, you're absolutely sure, would not be a breach of the Articles. It risks the accidental creation of Dhar, but the same could be said of any manipulation of magic. If it does not use Dhar and is not intended to result in it, then it's legal. A success, if reported to others, might raise certain questions that you'd want to be very careful to create plausible answers to, but that's no reason not to make the attempt in the first place. So with a stack of reference materials and Wolf on the lookout for unexpected visitors, you read up on an alien Wind and ensconce yourself within the protections of your White Tower. You've settled on Ghyran for your first attempt, in part because of pleasant associations, in part because of your hopes the Wind of Life would be the most benign and familiar of the possibilities, in part because if all goes terribly wrong you could blame it on the Seed embedded in your palm. With utter focus you grasp Ulgu with your soul, and instead of shaping it into a familiar form to be projected out onto the world, you try to push it outwards to wrap around a strand of Ghyran. It is, you quickly discover, rather like trying to catch a live eel in a cat's cradle, if the cat's cradle was also made of eels. As every Apprentice knows, the Winds repel each other. If that were not the case then there would be no Winds at all, as they would all merge and decay into Dhar shortly after emerging into the world. You had hoped that you could move skilfully enough to encircle and thus control a strand anyway, but when after hours of concentration you finally manage to entrap a strand of Ghyran so it can't slip free from the web you have built around it, its thrashing attempts bring it directly into contact with the Ulgu and a bloom of Dhar forms and begins to spread, slowly but interminably. You expel the Ulgu and activate the protections of the Room of Calamity, and the curdling Winds are drawn out of the room and flushed into the air. There's no danger in that, you remind yourself. You looked into it when you first built the room. At this height it will be blown away, and if it blows west or east or south it will be one more drop in the oceans of the Badlands or the Dark Lands or Nehekhara, and if it blows north it will be drawn into the Waystone network and be dealt with by the ancient artifice of the Elves. When you learned that the Karak itself is eight enormous Waystones it simplified it even further. Within the hour it will have been captured by one of them and will be on its way to Karaz-a-Karak, where some ancient Runic masterpiece will somehow break it into usable and benign energy. You repeat the experiment until you're sure there's no happy medium where you can constrict the Ghyran tightly enough for it to be under your control, but loosely enough that it doesn't come into contact with the Ulgu. But it does not react reliably, the way a solid or liquid would always act the same way when presented with the same circumstances. It reacts like a maddened animal, reacting to being cornered with escalating aggression until it either escapes or tears itself apart. Again and again Dhar blooms and is then flushed away, and many days end with a throbbing headache from seeing the beauty of Winds being corrupted into the malevolent substance of destruction. You abandon your torment of Ghyran in the hopes that it acts like a living being because it is the Wind of Life, and move on to Chamon, hoping that the Wind of metal and logic will act more, well, logically. And it does act differently, but only in the way that it drives itself wild in your grip before another bloom of Dhar confirms a failed experiment: this is more like a roiling boil than a thrashing creature, but the result is the same. With five more Winds you reach the same conclusion, the only variable being that some Winds require a tighter or looser grip before they are no longer able to slip free. The conclusion is inevitable: the Winds just don't want to be near each other, and if you make them, then they react with escalating chaos until they touch and form Dhar. Which should be the end of it, but... well, there's no crime in mere speculation, is there? Say you did force them, and a minute amount of Dhar did form, as it has many, many times in the preceding experiments. It would, in time, corrupt both Winds involved. But during that time, the corruptive power of Dhar would counteract the repellent power of the Winds. During that time, if someone acted quickly enough, they could reach through Ulgu to to more directly manipulate the subject Wind. They could shape that energy into a spell, and unleash that spell with enough force to sever the connection, leaving the Dhar with the caster and the spell free to act. That tiny amount of Dhar could then be shaken off by the caster before it corrupts the entire strand of Ulgu, leaving only a trace amount of environmental Dhar and minimal danger to the caster. It's plausible. Very plausible. The only problem is that unlike your experimentation so far, it would undeniably be a 'sorcery or witchcraft that utilises the wicked powers of Dark Magic'. From there the Articles go straight to Abominable Act, Heretic and Traitor, put to sword and fire immediately. You've never outright breached the Articles before, at least not by your understanding of them. But the only way to pursue this further would be to change that. With that conclusion, and with its unspoken question hanging in the air, you encode your notes, lock them securely away, and burn the originals. --- Your letter to Wilhelmina broaching the idea of Eike paying a visit to Karak Eight Peaks seems to have been very convincing indeed, because their response comes carried in the hands of Eike herself, who Wolf spots halfway up the stairs of Karag Nar and gives a ride the rest of the way, leaving her minder from the local EIC branch far behind. The tone of the letter, which you carefully read your way through as Wolf shows the wide-eyed Eike through your trophy room, seems to indicate that this is not due to some falling out between Eike and Wilhelmina as you initially suspected, but simply because of how important the Dwarves already are and are going to become even more to the EIC's continued success. In Wilhelmina's eyes Eike is apparently starting to meet the ambitious expectations she had of her, and is ready to start truly blossoming, hopefully in the field of Dwarven relations. Well, okay then. How do you even treat an eleven-year-old, anyway? The only lesson you can really take from your own childhood is to not threaten Eike with a fiery death. You grew up in two very different worlds, both very different to hers. But eventually you remember one thing: how much you hated it when the Apprentices older than you - pretty much all of them - treated you like the child that, admittedly, you still were. So perhaps the way to proceed is to treat her, at least to her face, like the adult that Wilhelmina expects her to be. "Well then," you say as you enter the trophy room, where Eike is staring transfixed by Alkharad's empty eye sockets. "There'll come a day when you'll be running the EIC, so it's important for you to know how to get along with the Dwarves - which is something a lot of people never really figure out." "Yes, Dame Weber," she says obediently. "If you're going to be my partner, you can call me Mathilde. That's Wolf," you say with a nod at him, "he's my familiar, so he'll be helping look after you while you're here, and if there's anything you need to tell me, you can tell him and I'll hear it." She looks from you to him and back again. "Okay," she says. "So, let's introduce you to some very important people," you say, still trying to work out exactly which people those should be. Vote for what people or institutions Mathilde will introduce Eike to during her time at Karak Eight Peaks. This will be on top of her learning about Dwarves in general, and may or may not shape the person she becomes in the years to come. You can vote for any amount, and the three with the most votes will win. [ ] Belegar Ironhammer [ ] Kazrik and the Dwarves of Karak Azul [ ] Dreng, Clan Huzkul, and the Cult of Grimnir [ ] Edda and the Cult of Valaya [ ] Gotri, the K8P Air Corps, and the Cult of Morgrim [ ] Gunnars and the Cult of Gazul [ ] Johann and the Cult of Grungni [ ] Max and the Cult of Smednir [ ] Gretel and Braganza's Besiegers [ ] Kragg the Grim [ ] Thorek Ironbrow [ ] Panoramia, Hluodwica, and the Halflings [ ] Francesco, Soizic, and the Undumgi [ ] Adela, Oswald, and the Gunnery School [ ] Hubert, Sir Ruprecht, and Ulrikadrin [ ] Cython [ ] The We - There will be a one hour moratorium. - For the record, there were no dicerolls involved with the 'tongs' section. This is the quest-canonical metaphysical answer to the question that was asked.

Turn 34 Results - 2486.5 - Part 2 - Eike's Visit

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Belegar Ironhammer [*] Kazrik and the Dwarves of Karak Azul [*] Panoramia, Hluodwica, and the Halflings Well, if your intention is to introduce Eike to some important people, why go to half measures? King Belegar won't have nearly as much time to spare as just about anyone else, but he's an incredibly important figure, an embodiment of Dwarven greatness, and someone you've personally grown quite fond of over the years. This does mean travelling all the way down Karag Nar and then halfway up Karag Lhune, so you introduce Eike to one of your little shortcuts: Shadowsteed. She's at first enthused and then disquieted by the horse-shaped mystical construct, and you learn from her that the rigid bearing of a Shadowsteed awaiting a rider would be indicative in a flesh and blood horse that they're tense or nervous and should be approached cautiously. You talk her through her nervousness and after she mounts the horse - side-saddle rather than properly astride since she's wearing a dress, but that won't matter on a Shadowsteed - you take her back down Karag Nar. She quickly recovers her enthusiasm as she accelerates to a canter down the stairs, and as Karag Nar is well accustomed to your own mounted comings and goings up and down the central staircase you simply smile and allow her to enjoy the trip. Once out into the Eastern Valley she accelerates even further, the Shadowsteed taking her at a speed beyond the capabilities of any mundane horse. You could still run rings around her if you were of a mind, but you lag behind and let her enjoy it, though you take care to remain within shouting distance. A canter up the much shorter external stairs of Karag Lhune later, you allow Eike to dismount before dismissing the horses with a gesture - the gesture is superfluous, but it puts people slightly more at ease around magic if they think they can see some sort of cause and effect. You take a moment in a Dwarven bar adjoining the entrance hall for Eike to regain her breath and composure over a mug of small beer, and after conjuring a reflective surface for Eike to make sure her hair was still in place, you bring her into the Hall of the Moon to wait your turn amongst the petitioners, mostly Elders from the local Clans or representatives of foreign powers, and you exchange nods with some of the faces you recognize. While you wait you draw Eike's attention to the ceiling, where the escutcheon of every contributor to the original Expedition have been carved. She quickly spots the crest of Stirland, which was credited for the contributions of many of the former Crossbowmen who left the Army of Stirland during Roswita's modernization efforts, and then spots Anton's, in gratitude for his contribution of materiel. You point out Sylvania's crest for her, as few people in modern times would recognize the dragon crest of the long-extinct Von Draks, and the cluster of crests belonging to the Winter Wolves, the Knights of Taal's Fury, and the Knights of the Vengeful Sun. "You've been taught that Dwarves never forget a Grudge?" you ask, and she nods. "Nor do they forget a service done for them." She seems to be thinking on that as the two of you wait, only fidgeting slightly and staring thoughtfully up at the ceiling. "Loremaster Weber," Belegar says in Reikspiel as you finally approach the throne and bow. "What brings you before me this day?" "I have the honour of introducing Eike Hochschild, heiress to Wilhelmina Hochschild, the Governor and Founder of the EIC." Eike freezes for a moment, her eyes wide, but regains her composure after a nudge from you. "An honour to meet you, Your Majesty," she says formally, bobbing a curtsy. Belegar nods. "Much of what arrives at our gates passed through EIC hands, and King Byrrnoth has spoken well of Mistress Hochschild. How old are you, Miss Hochschild?" "Eleven, Your Majesty." "And you're Journeying already?" he asks. She hesitates. "Yes, Your Majesty," she repeats, confused but trying not to show it. "Strollenokren?" you ask Belegar, and he nods. "He means in the sense of being a Journeywoman, Eike. She's still a Gnutrommikit, but travelling is part of that for traders." "Ah, of course." He glances from you to the line. "I'll be happy to speak some more to the plaitling after lunch." "Thank you," you say with a bow, which he returns with a nod, and after she curtsies a farewell you guide Eike out of the Hall. --- After a lunch spent explaining Dwarven life stages to Eike, you take Eike into Belegar's meeting room, where he's busily covering the table with maps of tunnel systems. "How goes the Elf business?" he asks in Khazalid without looking up. "I've brought in Johann and Maximilian, and have set wheels in motion to recruit Egrimm van Horstmann, the Light Wizard on the Expedition who despatched the Higher Daemon in the Battle of High Pass." "The one that had that Elf's Dragon in its claws?" You nod. "Do you think that will win points from these Elves?" "It couldn't hurt, but I'm more focused on bringing in as many perspectives as possible. The Light Wizards have access to a lot of old secrets." He nods. "Makes sense. Have you decided on a location for the Archive?" "Kvinn-Wyr, with an entrance from the Eastern Valley." "Good, apart from the reservoir there would have been nothing calling it home for years to come. I don't like leaving corners of the Karak empty, because they never stay empty." He turns his gaze to Eike. "So. Your business partner's daughter?" "Granddaughter. Her sons were unsuitable, but Eike seems a good seed." "Gold and muck come from the same shaft." He stands and walks over to Eike, who is just about the same height as him. "So," he says in Reikspiel, "you'll be the one keeping the goods flowing from here to the Empire in the future?" "Yes, Your Majesty," she says, nodding rapidly for emphasis. "Good. Good. Many human traders don't understand how things are done, though the EIC seems better than most. You make an agreement with Dwarves, you do your honest best to stick to every letter of it, and you won't have any trouble that can't be sorted out. Have you heard the legend of the Tuppence Grudge?" Eike's eyes dart to you, and you nod. "Yes, Your Majesty," she admits. It's an old and often retold legend about a fort commissioned from the Dwarves, and after they were shorted in payment by two pennies they went to war to tear it down. "The part the legend leaves out is how many Elders and Loremasters did their best to explain to the manlings what would happen, and how many times they were ignored. Humans may bluff and bluster, but Longbeards don't. Listen when they speak and you won't go far wrong." He looks over to you. "When will she be taking over?" he asks in Khazalid. "Wilhelmina's sixty next year, so probably within the decade." He shakes his head. "A Dwarf of sixty wouldn't yet be ready to be called a Master. Never could figure out if you go about things too quick, or if we go about things too slow." "Looking at my sword, I'd say you do things just right. But looking at the empty Karags..." you shrug. "Still, the Karak has some of both. Best of both worlds, right?" He considers that, and turns back to Eike. "The Karaz Ankor and the Empire have been allies for nearly two and a half thousand years. It's my belief that if they weren't, both would have fallen long ago. Remember that." "Yes, Your Majesty," she says again. He pats her on the shoulder. "Ancestors guide you." --- Eike seems somewhat overwhelmed, so you leave her with Wolf to recover as you see to some other business. The next day she's back in form and ready to be introduced to even more royalty, and you put her back on ethereal horseback to lead her across the Caldera. "Do you know why your grandmother and I think it's important to get along with the Dwarves?" "Oma says the best stuff is Dwarf-made," she says. "A lot of the time, yes. They made the Runefangs, they made Ghal Maraz. But that's not the only reason. What do you know of Karak Azul?" "They're south from here. They buy a lot, but all the shipping from here goes through them." "Why is that?" She frowns. "Protectionism?" "No. Well, not in the way you mean. It's literal, not economic. Do you know their history?" She frowns, concentrating. "They were founded by expatriate Clans after the Time of Woes." "That's Izor." "Oh. Um. I, um, can't remember?" "That's okay. Most people don't know much about them. They were cut off from the world after Karak Eight Peaks fell." She considers that. "But that was forever ago," she objects. "About three thousand years, yes. They held out alone all that time, surrounded by greenskins and Beastmen. That's why they guard their tunnels so closely." You give her a moment to digest that. "Look, dealing with Dwarves can be a pain a lot of the time. They can be proud and stubborn and condescending. But it's worth it. When times are tough, there's no better ally to have on your side." Karag Rhyn is less accustomed to humans on magical horses riding through their corridors than Karag Nar, so the two of you dismount at the entrance and make your way inside on foot. It is the home to most of the Karak's Dwarven Clans, and amongst the Clan Halls is one set aside for visitors from Karak Azul. You've introduced Eike to about as intimidating a personage as she's likely to meet unless she stumbles across Kragg, so now you want to balance that out with one of the most personable Dwarves you know. "Got time to meet someone new, Kazrik?" you ask loudly, knocking on the door to his office. "Always," he says as he emerges, wiping ink-covered hands on his chainmail. "For you, doubly so. Who's this Garazit?" "This is Eike Hochschild, heir to my good friend and partner in the EIC, Wilhelmina. Eike, this is Kazrik, Crown Prince of Karak Azul and Diplomat of Karak Eight Peaks." "An honour to meet you, Your Highness," she says. "Highness is for the Crown Prince of the Empire," you correct. "For a Dwarven one..." You frown and look to Kazrik. "What would the proper honorific for a Prince be?" Khazalid doesn't have them, so you've never really used them. "Utkalanit always worked for me," Kazrik says with a smile. "An honour to meet you, Utkalanit", Eike says, and then frowns as the two of you laugh. "And mine to meet a wayward sibling," Kazrik jokes to the deeply confused Eike. "I don't think anyone would mind one more sister in the family, even if your plaits are a little short." "Since she'll be running the EIC one day, we decided it was important for her to get to know Dwarves," you say. "As someone who's only recently gotten to know humans, I can attest how difficult that can be." He scratches at his beard thoughtfully. "Leave her with me and I'll take her around, I've got some family business to deal with with the local Clans, and there's enough Azul Dwarves here at the moment that we've got the Hall's kitchens operational, so there's going to be dinner here later. Some of them haven't been up north yet, so Eike should be popular." "Thanks, Kazrik, I appreciate it," you say. "Not at all, I'd have to get to know her after she takes over anyway. You've saved me a trip north." --- After a few days in the company of the Karak Azul Dwarves, Eike comes back with her hair properly plaited, an elegant axe on her hip, and the aura of soft jingling that you guess to be a chainmail slip. She also has a long list of questions about Dwarves that she was too polite to ask of Kazrik, many of which boil down to 'why are they always so ready for a fight?' The answer you have to give her is that it's because they've been fighting for almost their entire history. The Empire can push back the forest with saw and fire and carve out pockets of peace for towns and cities to be built and children to grow up in peace, but the Karaz Ankor can't push back the mountains. By the time you take her across the Caldera, up through the Citadel, and into the Eastern Valley, her questions have died down. "While you're here, I want you to meet the Halflings," you say. She is growing up a Stirlander after all, and you want to make sure she doesn't internalize the prejudices against the Mootlanders many Stirlanders hold. "As well as a Wizard who works with them who's very special to me." "The tall golden one?" she guesses. "No, she's a Jade Wizard." She thinks about that. "She's a friend of Rhya?" You spend a moment thinking she's commenting on the internal religious conflict of the Jade Order before you remember the euphemism for someone who prefers the company of the same gender. "Yes, I suppose we both are," you say. "What's she doing?" You look ahead, to where a flare of Ghyran makes you as able to find Panoramia as a compass is to find north. "She's working with the fields. Different Wizards can do different things, and Jade Wizards are good at helping living things grow." "Can she still fight with magic?" You smile. "When she has to. She's busy right now, so when we get there, wait until I tell you so you don't interrupt her." Panoramia's business in the fields are always a lot more lengthy and involved than your own interactions with Ulgu, but you suppose if you wanted to permanently make a place amenable to mists or confusion it would take you... well, you actually wouldn't even know where to start, but if you did you'd guess it would take you at least as long. She's currently standing upright with her staff held in front of her and her eyes closed, and you know from previous observations that the staff would have sprouted roots that would be digging deep into the soil. You'd once assumed that dirt was dirt, and if there was something wrong it was simply a matter of correcting ratios of whatever ingredients go into making dirt, but from what Panoramia has told you you're now aware that proper soil is home to a literal microcosm of insects and fungi that need to be cultivated before a single seed is planted. Time passes in silence as you watch the dancing of energies, and with the part of your mind that's not entranced you note that Eike is showing admirable patience while watching what must to her be just a woman standing immobile in an empty field. "Is she finished?" Eike asks as the magic begins to die down. "Nearly," you say, then frown. "What made you ask just now?" "I don't know. She just seems finished." You turn your full attention to Eike, and consider a number of questions before rejecting all of them. Without doing anything to draw her attention, you summon what Ulgu you can while standing in the middle of a sunlit field, focusing to prevent the usual visible signs of extended channelling, and you hold back a sigh as Eike begins to give you sidelong looks and fidgeting nervously. "Is something wrong?" you ask her in as normal a voice as you can. "No, Dame Weber," she replies quickly. You let the Ulgu leak out of you, sinking into the soil and darting towards nearby shadows, and she relaxes once more. "You're sure?" "Yes, it's just for a moment- it's nothing, Dame Weber." "You felt something?" She nods. "It's okay. Describe it." "I don't know." You open your mouth to ask again, but she continues. "I mean, I felt like what it feels like when you're supposed to know something but you don't." Magesight. It's more common than most people think, but for most people who have it it's just hunches and instinct. Someone with just a touch of it might be able to recognize that Panoramia was doing something, but not the moment she began to wind down. They might be able to recognize a Wizard next to them performing magic, but not just them holding onto their Wind. For her to react so strongly and so quickly... This is probably going to do a lot of damage to Wilhelmina's well-laid plans. 13. All Magisters are required to seek out magic users as may exist within the bounds of Sigmar's Holy Empire to ascertain their suitability to join one of the Orders of Magic, or else report them to the Holy Orders of the Templars of Sigmar, or else destroy them if they prove to be of immediate and grave menace to Sigmar's People. But by the letter of the law, you're not forced into action while you're this far south of the Empire's borders. "Panoramia," you call out as you lead Eike across the field. "Hey, you," she says with a smile as she turns. "Who's this?" "This is Eike, I think I've told you about her." "The EIC girl?" You nod. "An honour to meet you, My Lady," Eike says. Not technically correct, but no Journeywoman is going to be offended at being addressed as a Magister, so you suppose it was the right form of address to choose. "Just Panoramia will be fine," she says, giving Eike a friendly smile. "I was hoping you could introduce her to the Halflings. You know, while she's down from Stirland," you say with slight emphasis. "Ah. Yes, I can do that," she says, nodding. "Will you be coming?" "I was going to, but..." you take a moment to consider your response. Lingua Praestantia can be used as a language, but it wasn't made for it and it's always a bit clunky. "I just discovered she has strong Magesight. I have to think about how I'm going to handle that." Panoramia nods. "Magic stuff," she explains to Eike, who nods. "Lunch would be a good start. Halflings consider a proper lunch to be a form of worship." Eike brightens a little. "So does Shallya," she says. "Well, there's a few differences between a Shallyan meal and an Esmereldan one, but there's enough agreement there to work with," Panoramia says, leading Eike in the direction of a nearby cluster of buildings. You exhale, and start mentally rearranging your calendar. You need to have a difficult conversation with Wilhelmina, and sooner rather than later. But the problem will ask a question of Wilhelmina, and many questions have their answer decided by how they are presented. Eike won't be the first heir to come down with an inconvenient case of magic, and more nobles than many would guess once paid a discreet visit to Altdorf to be fitted with magic-dampening jewellery and trinkets so they could continue on the path their parents had decided for them. But the problem is that many of those nobles are unable to resist the allure of magic, and enough of them end up self-teaching from black market grimoires that there's a term for them - Magicker. A deliberate crime against proper grammar to highlight how incorrectly they're going about things. It usually ends badly, whether that be on a pyre or in a nasty miscast or in the clutches of the myriad forbidden Cults that Magickers are easy prey for. Or you could try to guide Eike down a specific path. A lot of emphasis is placed on how it's up to a prospective Wizard to choose what Order they join, but most young people are malleable enough that they can fit into just about any Order, and many Wizards that retrieve a prospective Wizard will take the opportunity to tip the scales for their own. You yourself didn't so much choose the Grey Order as you chose not to be separated from the Magister that had retrieved you from Kelham. Nudging Eike down the path of the Grey Order might, from a certain point of view, be best for the Order and the EIC. The Vow of Poverty would not necessarily prevent Eike from inheriting, but it will mean that she will be required to make the EIC 'of direct and practical use to her cause'. You take a moment to smile at the thought - perhaps instead of becoming Wilhelmina's heir, she would be Wilhelmine's. Or... perhaps your own. You'd given thought in the past to taking on an Apprentice, even though you never went through with it. But if a Grey Wizard is going to be trained to be the future handler of the EIC, you would be the natural fit to do the training. An interesting thought, but not one you have to wrestle with just now - she'd need to have the basics taught to her before she took on a Master, and that's a process of several years. Or perhaps she'd fit better into one of the other Orders. Only entering into the Amethyst Order would prevent her from inheriting, as their initiates are required to part ways with all worldly possessions upon joining, explicitly including future inheritances. Admittedly she might make a poor administrator after being taught the ways of Aqshy or Ghur, but Eike as a Gold Wizard could make for a potent Governor, or the Jade Order might inculcate a proper desire for long-term growth. Or you suppose she could join the Clergy. Teclis was recorded as stating that Divine Magic and Arcane Magic is one and the same, so perhaps she can turn that gift towards more socially acceptable ends. But on the other hand, not everyone agrees with Teclis on that matter, and the Cults have very firmly resisted all attempts by the Colleges at getting at any solid answers. Or, finally, you could do nothing. Maybe Eike just has unusually strong Magesight without the rest of the abilities that make one a Wizard, it's rare but not impossible. Or maybe she could just never develop the ability to channel the Winds through her soul. Maybe she never has to know that she may have been blessed, or cursed, with the gift of magic. Maybe this will allow her a 'normal' life. Or maybe it will end in disaster, as it so often will if someone begins dabbling in magic without instruction. When Mathilde meets with Wilhemina to tell her that Eike is very likely to have the gift and curse of magic, she can present the facts in a neutral way, or she can do so in a way that suggests a particular course of action. This is likely, but not guaranteed to shape the course of action Wilhelmina decides upon. What fate, if any, will Mathilde suggest for Eike? [ ] Neutral [ ] Take no action [ ] Magic-Dampening [ ] Wizard - [ ] No specific Order - [ ] Let Eike decide - [ ] The Order of Light - [ ] The Celestial College - [ ] The Golden Order - [ ] The Order of Life - [ ] The Amber Brotherhood - [ ] The Bright Order - [ ] The Grey Order - [ ] The Amethyst Order [ ] Clergy - There will be a twelve hour moratorium. - I'll decide whether Mathilde suggests just one thing, or multiple things, or one thing primarily and other things as less preferable alternatives, based on how the voting turns out. So simply vote for whichever option or options you think are best. - You can vote for sub-options of Wizard without voting for Wizard itself, if you would like to do so. This will make Wizard no less likely to win, but will mean your vote for the Order will count if Wizard does win. - So. Eike's a Wizard. Sounds contrived, right? What are the odds? In this case, they're exactly one in a hundred, as one eagle-eyed reader spotted a fortnight ago. Maybe Ranald is real. - This was going to be a much shorter part of the turn before *waves hands in general direction of dice*. The rest of the turn will continue after this is resolved. - Relevant information from the WoQM threadmark: Apprenticeship Most would-be Wizards have their magical awakening at 15-20, and it's rare for it to happen outside 10-25. Junior Apprenticeship is developing control over the ability to touch the Winds. For some people this means learning how to reach out and touch it, for others it's learning how to stop. They cannot leave the mono-Wind environment of the Colleges without risking Dhar poisoning. They usually get a Master when they reach regular Apprentice, which is when they start learning how to actually do things with magic instead of learning how not to be killed by magic. Most spend this inside the College, though it can be spent at any College-controlled location, and they still rely on mono-Wind environments for practice and learning. Senior Apprentices have enough control and ability that they can be allowed to leave College property of their own accord. Practically every Senior Apprentice will have a Master, as it's the level when they can pull their weight and properly assist their Master. Some of them join their Master on their missions or get sent on simple assignments, some of them go adventuring on their own, most just use it to explore Altdorf.

Turn 34 Results - 2486.5 - Part 3 - Eike's Fate

Spoiler: Voting results Vote tally [*] Wizard - [*] The Grey Order - [*] Let Eike decide Eike's time with the Halflings goes well, and on several occasions you watch through Wolf's eyes as she sheds the fretful student guise to play with children her own age and half her height. You get the feeling she doesn't often get the opportunity to simply be the child she still is, and if anything that's going to become even more the case in the future. The law gives all Magisters the power to unilaterally take into custody and escort to Altdorf anyone with the ability to use magic, but the Orders very much prefer to be less disruptive and seek the technically unneeded permission of the recruit or their guardians, both for the sake of their public relations and for not traumatizing would-be initiates with an abduction. When the guardian of that initiate is one's business partner, a tactful approach becomes even more important. So you prepare and hone a few key arguments and when it comes time for Eike to leave the Karak, you tell her that you've got business in the Empire, so she might as well fly back with you by Gyrocarriage. She's quite excited at the prospect, and though you can't deny the view can be amazing, passenger compartments that were originally bomb racks aren't the most comfortable way to travel. You advise her to dress warm and bring something to plug her ears with. --- A series of hops between Karaks later, you arrive in Stirland, touching down in a clearing of the gardens outside the EIC offices. It's an effective way to announce your arrival, and by the time you reach her office, Wilhelmina is already waiting for you, and as you enter glances to either side of you. "What is it? Is Eike okay?" "She's fine, I told her to go bug the kitchens for lunch so we can talk. Here's the reports from the Karag Nar branch, one was marked time-sensitive." You hand over a slightly rumpled pile of papers, which she skims through with a distracted frown. "I've been trying to convince the Dwarves to let us rent the use of the Gyrocopters for information that needs to travel quickly, but they're dubious about it. Military assets not for civilian use, especially human civilians. Knowing this piece of news before anyone else on this side of the Black Mountains will make us a nice bit of money." She looks up. "Anyway, what is it that brings you here?" "I believe Eike has the potential to use magic." Wilhelmina puts the papers down and turns her full attention to you. "Why do you think that?" "She was able to identify and distinguish concentrations of magical energy. Having Magesight doesn't always indicate the potential to be a magic-user, but Magesight that sharp at her age almost certainly does." She exhales. "I finally have an heir worth a damn, and... what are the odds?" You nod in commiseration. "No, I'm seriously asking. Tell me what the odds are. I thought it was supposed to be one in a thousand of one in a thousand, or something like that." "I've heard the same, but it's nowhere near that. Maybe it's artistic license. If that was the case, the Empire would have maybe thirty Wizards, and that's including recruiting from Tilea and Estalia-" "How many are there?" she interrupts. "About four hundred fully-qualified Magisters or higher. If you include everyone in the Colleges - Apprentices, Journeyman, Perpetuals, Sealed, Minor Talents, everyone - maybe five thousand total. But as for odds... well, maybe one percent of people have some degree of usable Magesight. For most people, they never even know it. Maybe they get hunches, maybe they just know things. Some people can always tell when a storm is coming, some people are good at 'reading' people, some people have a 'knack' for dice or cards." You nod to her. "What made you a good trader? Why are you ruling a trade empire, when so many end up dead in a ditch or penniless or just scrape by their whole lives?" "I guess..." Her frown deepens. "Well, a lot of things, but I see what you're getting at. I always said, if I shake a man's hand and look him in the eye, I can get the measure of him. And my husband... he'd get a bad feeling sometimes, and we'd go a different route or take a different cargo and sometimes we'd hear later that..." She shakes her head. "Are you saying that's magic?" "I'm saying, maybe you and he could sense magic. Not consciously, but if you could sense the Ulgu drawn to someone trying to misdirect, or your husband could sense the Shyish drawn to a path lurked by bandits or Beastmen, that could manifest as a 'measure of a person' or a 'bad feeling'. If you both had it, maybe you passed it down." You consider what you've heard of her sons. "And maybe it skipped a generation. "So, we estimate one in a hundred people have Magesight. About one in ten of those will have some ability to actually use magic - so, one person in a thousand. That's any ability at all. A lot of people will never actually use it, sometimes the ability lies dormant their entire lives, sometimes they have one bad experience and consciously or subconsciously slam the door on it. A lot of people react by turning to the priesthood. Those left over - about a third of those one in a thousand - end up at the Colleges. "From there, we shave away even more. There's Minor Talents - people who can only do one thing or a narrow range of things with magic. Clairvoyants, telekinetics, weather-seers, whatever. There's people who don't want their magic, if we can't convince them to even try it we give them jewellery and trinkets to dampen their magical ability. There's people who can't control their magic at all, and they get the trinkets too. Both are just called Sealed. Some of them stay on at the Colleges as assistants or administrative staff, some return to their previous lives. There's Perpetuals, Perpetual Apprentices, people who have the ability to manipulate magic into different forms but can't channel enough power to do more than basic cantrips. Once all those are winnowed out, maybe another one in ten or less reach the rank of Magister." "One in thirty thousand." You nod. "And my Eike is one of those." "I think she has the potential to be. Some people do just have strong Magesight, but they usually get it by honing it through decades of tough living. Eike's eleven and she's able to identify and distinguish Winds, without even knowing that's what she's doing. It's more likely that she's a regular Wizard-to-be than her having Magesight that strong and no other magical ability." Wilhelmina is silent for a while. "What if the odds were different?" she asks quietly. You look at her a while, and nod. "What if I reconsidered the matter and reached a different conclusion about her ability to use magic, you mean?" She nods. "As an entirely theoretical exercise, in that case I would no longer be bound by the Articles to recruit, report, or destroy her. She would continue on in life with the beguiling light of the Winds dancing just within reach. And if that reconsideration was incorrect, it's very likely that one day she would reach out to those Winds, and from there there's a thousand different ways it could go horribly wrong." You shake your head. "Some that avoid the Colleges seek education outside them, but there aren't many benign teachers left outside the Colleges these days. That leaves grimoires full of traps for the unwary, and Sorcerers and forbidden Cults that would be all too happy to get their hands on a malleable young thing like her, and worst of all, Daemons of every stripe that would fight each other for the chance to whisper temptation into her ear. It's the same reason we don't like putting people in dampeners unless the person is completely against using magic in any circumstances, either because they're completely opposed to it or because they've been traumatized by it." She considers that. "So unless you do... reach a different conclusion, you're bound by your laws to bring her in or report her." You consider the wording of the Articles. "Technically she's not covered by that Article until she actually uses magic, so I could leave the matter be until that changes. But the first time someone uses magic can so easily go badly, and it would be much better for her if she is able to take her first steps in a safe and controlled environment. And besides that, sometimes the magic a person first uses can shape their future with it. Up north I worked with a Wizard who first developed magic when she was attacked by Beastmen, and defended herself with the fires of her charcoal pile. Because of that she ended up with the Bright College, where she might otherwise have been a better fit for another." "Wouldn't you just take her in to your one, since you discovered her?" "No, they're supposed to go to the Order that they're most suited to. But someone of her age who hasn't actually touched any of the Winds is a lot more malleable than most, and she could probably do well in any Order. I was a year younger than her when I was taken in, and the main reason I ended up in the Greys is the Wizard who brought me in was a Grey and I'd grown attached to him. So it's really a decision to be made, rather than something inherent." "To be made by who?" You'd been turning that over in your mind a fair bit in the past few days. Half of you wants Eike to end up in the Grey College, both so you can take her under your wing and so the EIC remains firmly under Grey Order control. But the other half wants Eike to be able to make the decision herself. "The decision would be hers, and it's one I do think she should be allowed to make for herself. But... it is a huge decision, one that will shape the rest of her life. It might be justifiable to encourage her to make the right choice." "That being the same choice you made?" You nod unabashedly. "I have contacts in the other Orders so I could help her to some extent wherever she ends up, but I could do orders of magnitude more for her in the Grey Order than anywhere else." She considers that, and nods. "Otherwise I might say the Alchemists or the Seers, but you're right, patronage would make all the difference. And if she is a Grey Wizard... well, it's going to disrupt her education, but if she can do the things you can do..." She looks at you. "She'd still be able to have children of her own, wouldn't she?" "Only the Lights and Amethysts are required to be celibate." "How long would her training take?" "The first stage of her training would take three to five years, and would require her to stay within the confines of her College. After that it would be possible for her teachings to be continued elsewhere - the EIC would easily have the resources to organize facilities and tutors." "Three to five... probably closer to three than five, she's sharp. So she'd be fourteen or so... that... shouldn't disrupt things too much..." She closes her eyes for a while, her brow furrowed in thought. "Okay. I'll have a talk to her, let her know. Will you take her to Altdorf?" "If that's what you want." You'd already checked the range, the Gyrocarriage can make it to Altdorf and then reach Karak Ziflin in the Grey Mountains to refuel. "She's already packed, and I can have the rest of her things sent downriver easily enough. Are Apprentices allowed non-Wizard visitors?" You have to think about that one. "I think so." She looks at you, and you're pretty sure you know the questions she's not asking, but then she simply nods. "We'll find out." She rises, taking a deep breath, and takes a moment to collect her thoughts before walking out of the room. --- An hour later, after you'd gotten tired of waiting and gone off to follow Eike's example in bugging the kitchens for lunch, Eike finds you leafing through various reports scattered throughout the building. "Can I talk to you?" she asks, her voice small. "Of course. Let's chat outside." You return the report to the extremely nervous clerk you had pilfered it from and lead her out into the gardens, where the only company is the Gyrocarriage, its pilot engaged in his own search for sustenance. You'd recommended Wurtbad's wines to him, but Dwarves don't seem to trust wine. "I'm going to be a Wizard?" she asks you as you take a seat on an ornamental bench. "I think you can be, yes." "Do I have to be?" "If you are, it's very hard not to be." You nod towards the Gyrocarriage. "It would be like trying not to hear anything while we were flying in that." "Oh." She's quiet for a while. "Oma says it's my choice which, but that I should choose yours." "Do you know much about the Colleges?" "Only yours. There's eight, right?" "Right." You think for a moment, and then smile. You'd thought there were no practical uses for your experiments in trying to indirectly manipulate Winds, but you might have been wrong. "Do you feel the sun on your face?" She looks up, squinting. "Yes." "Do you feel the part of it that isn't just the warmth? The same way you felt what Panoramia was doing out in the fields?" She closes her eyes and concentrates. "It feels... like a complicated thing that's been made simple." "That's a very good way to put it. That's Hysh, the White Wind of the Order of Light." You walk her through the other Winds, herding in sufficient amounts for her to sense from the ambient energies that the world is forever awash with. The Golden Wind of Chamon reminds her of the sums and tables she's spent years grappling with, the Blue Wind of Azyr a sense of anticipation, the Red Wind of Aqshy a tense escalation ready to burst, the Amber Wind of Ghur makes her shift uneasily and imbues a sense of claustrophobia, which you believe to be a result of her sensing in the middle of a city. The Jade Wind of Ghyran reminds her of Panoramia, which you suppose makes sense, since that was probably the first time she encountered it in large amounts. The Amethyst Wind of Shyish has her go quiet, and you allow it to pass without prodding her for her impression of it. Then you summon Ulgu once more, and she sits there for some time, staring into space. "Does it always feel like that?" she asks. You could answer with strict honesty, and say that you have no way of knowing how her relationship with a specific Wind would evolve. Every Wizard's relationship with a Wind is deeply personal, and even beyond that, your own Windsight is visual and hers is either emotive or intuitive. But there's another answer that comes to your lips, one that's arguably equally honest. "It used to when I was young, but to me now, it feels more like something I know, but nobody else does. Like a fog that I can see through, but nobody else can." She considers that for a while, then thanks you and gives you a small sidelong hug before going back inside. The next morning she has made her decision, and the Gyrocarriage lifts off to take the two of you to the Grey College, which is to be Eike's home for the next few years and, you hope, for the rest of her life. - Remainder of Turn 34 to come. - Canonical note: The numbers Mathilde gave to Wilhelmina are my own back-of-the-envelope maths. Canonical population numbers for the Empire are absurdly small with some provinces having as few as ten thousand citizens, so I've given them the 15 million of the mid-1600's Holy Roman Empire and doubled that for magical recruitment purposes to account for Tilea, Estalia, the Border Princes, and smuggled male magic-users from Bretonnia and Kislev. Something I've seen said in the fandom a few times is that 'one in a thousand can see magic, one in a thousand of those can use magic', and I've got no idea where that comes from and suspect it's a misremembering of something from 40k about psykers. 2e Realms of Sorcery outright says 'the most learned agree that perhaps one child in a thousand has the potential to become a spellcaster.' - The mainstream theory is that there's three magical senses - 'Intuition' or 'Aethyric Attunement' that all humans are believed to have to some degree, 'Witchsight' that a minority have that manifests as an entire sense, and 'Channelling' which is what makes someone a full-blown magic-user. Mathilde simplified things for Wilhelmina's benefit, and for obvious reason does not like the 'Witchsight' terminology. - Each College has an official name which can be found in the Collection of Important Information threadmark under 'The Winds of Magic, and the organizations authorized to study them', but like many Wizards, Mathilde uses 'the X College' or 'the X Order' interchangeably for all of them most of the time.

Turn 34 Results - 2486.5 - Part 4

Spoiler: Unfinished business [*] DUCK: Continue to work with Panoramia with implementing the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. [*] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (Cult of Karnos, Talabecland) [*] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [*] SERENITY: Write a paper: Daemonic Concealment of Karak Vlag [*] PENTHOUSE: Build a basic tower of single-Wind environments for each of the 'missing' Winds: Light, Amber, Amethyst, and Gold [*] [KAU] In Kvinn-Wyr, with an entrance from the Eastern Valley With four varieties of Windsoak Mushrooms already mastered and construction underway on four new (albeit undersized) towers to supply the Winds for the missing varieties, you and Panoramia return to the Green Tower to finish the job. Your mind is rather occupied, however: with the construction of a Light Magic tower underway, you realize you've painted yourself into a corner with regards to tower names, as you named your magically-neutral tower the White Tower without regards for the naming of a future Hysh Tower. Panoramia is no help at all, as she seems to consider the problem greatly entertaining, and then her assertion that you look 'cute' when you're mentally wrestling with the issue makes you even more distracted from the task at hand. Somehow you manage to muddle through these troubles and raise two thriving crops. Normally you'd have trouble applying that word to fungi, most of which look varying degrees of sickly to your untrained eye, but in this case you have the other two crops to give a strong contrast: the Shyish and Chamon crops. It's an issue anyone with basic familiarity with the Winds can spot: the Lore of Metal and the Lore of Death are both rather antithetical to natural growth, but removing the Winds from the equation would rather defeat the entire purpose of growing these mushrooms in the first place. "Can we wait until it's fully grown and then soak it?" you ask Panoramia. She shakes her head. "The visible mushroom is more like a fruit than a plant. Once it's fully grown, it releases spores and withers, at which point it stops absorbing Winds." "So it needs to be exposed to the Winds while it's growing, but exposure to those two Winds prevents growth." "And I can't use magic to encourage it because the mushrooms would absorb some of the Ghyran, which would create Dhar." [Attempting workarounds: Learning, 23+29+15(Windherder)-10(Overwork)=57.] The two of you give it your best shot, but you're unable to find a way to make it work. There's a minimum amount of Winds that need to be present for the mushrooms to absorb them in useful quantities, and there's also a maximum amount of those Winds that the mushrooms can tolerate, and that minimum is greater than that maximum. Panoramia broaches the possibility of breeding more Shyish- and Chamon-resistant mushrooms, but that's a long-term project with no guarantee of success - mycology is a field that has received much less human study than botany, both in the Old World in general and by the Jade Order specifically. For now, you turn to the two successful varieties and turn them over to the Halflings for them to work their own form of magic on. A few rounds of often-delicious experimentation later you're left with mixed results: the sun-dried Hysh mushroom jerky is handily portable and can be seasoned to taste, but your observations with volunteers reveals that no matter what the Halflings try, there are no results better than those produced with consumption of the raw Ghur mushrooms. Which you suppose makes sense, but it does mean that there's no portable, palatable, and long-lasting form of the mushroom for the Amber Wizards, which you find rather unsatisfactory. The two of you wrap up the experimentation and carefully store away spore prints with your notes, pondering whether to consider the current set of results good enough or to pursue a complete set of eight viable mushroom-producing techniques. [New papers available: Windsoak Mushrooms - Hysh, Ghur.] --- Next you turn your attention to the matter of Karak Vlag's abduction and return, and it promises to be a tricky paper to write. The ways and means of the Chaos Gods are always a topic one must use care in discussing, especially those constrained by the Articles, but on top of that it involves the Karaz Ankor Waystone Network, a topic you have no intentions of broaching to the academic community at large. You quickly reach the conclusion that it would not hurt the quality of the paper to leave that part out entirely, and work on wording until you reach a phrasing that misdirects without actually being counterfactual. After all, it's technically correct to refer to the enormous stream of energy flowing from Karag Dum as a 'local leyline', and it could be seen as an accurate depiction of the matter to say that it was 'commandeered'. People reading a redirection of the Waystone energies into that phrasing will not significantly affect the utility of the paper. With that problem circumscribed, you're left with the much more significant one that is the simple truth that you don't actually know what the Daemons did. You suspect nobody could know, not without enough knowledge of the Aethyr to break the sanity of any mortal mind. But that doesn't really matter. It might make for a lesser paper, but even the reduced paper is likely to be extremely well-received. The world of academia does put on airs of rationality, but every person in it is still a person and as such is vulnerable to the allure of novelty. You consider it unlikely that any currently-living person will ever face the same circumstances that Karak Vlag faced, lying as it does at a unique confluence of an Everchosen-induced swelling of the Chaos Wastes and the availability of a massive stream of magical power, but it will still be read by a great many people. And who knows, perhaps at some point in the distant future lightning will strike a second time, and someone might dust off a copy of your paper. Maybe the next victims of this particular torment will not have to wait almost two centuries for rescue. [Writing: Learning, 74+29+10(Fresh)-10(Overwork)=103.] It's been quite some time since you actually wrote a paper by yourself, but the subject matter requires you at least put together a carefully expurgated first draft before you bring Maximilian in. This time you may not have to, as right from the outset you manage to strike a balance between scholarly observation, factual recording, and thrilling recounting - including in the ensuing battle with the Daemons, the inclusion of which is absolutely necessary as the detailed description of the Higher Daemon involved might allow it to be identified at a later date. The paper is sure to lose some of its impact as the involvement of Daemons and the remaining mentions of Waystones will require a degree of classification, but overall you're extremely pleased with your effort. [The Return of Karak Vlag, 2486. Subject: Unique, +3. Insight: Revolutionary, +2. Delivery: Thrilling, +2. Popular, +1. Classified, -2. Total: 6.] --- You've read and collected a number of books on the topic of swordsmanship over the years, and though those books came exclusively from the Old World, some of them mention stories, rumours and legends of swordsmen of other lands. One group often mentioned is the knights of far-off Nippon, who are said to hone every facet of swordplay into an art in its own right. One of those is said to be the turning of the drawing of a sword into a single killing blow to end a fight just as it begins. The Barak Varr booksellers are tragically short of swordsmanship manuals from the far side of the world, so you're forced to start practically from scratch. Most Old World swordsmanship styles have one thing to say about starting a fight with your weapon sheathed, and that is to not start a fight with your weapon sheathed. Your previous work with dumping momentum provides a decent starting point, as you've already practiced moving empty hands into a position to bring a sword down for the next swing and adapted to the sudden appearance of a large piece of momentumless metal in your hands. But though that's perfectly serviceable, it does not nearly satisfy you. Branulhune's ability to appear in your hands at a thought could theoretically make you able to begin and end a fight in a single motion, but that becomes less likely if just before that single motion you have to maneuver yourself into a swordfighting stance. You need to chart the most efficient and, ideally, innocent-looking paths from various neutral stances into a swing, giving the target as little opportunity to notice and time to respond as possible. [Developing the quick-draw: Martial, 97+23-10(Overwork)=110.] Progress comes quickly after a realization: you are not inventing, you are combining. Local martial cultures may have little to say about looking innocent as long as possible, but this is a topic that is of great interest to other, less respected groups, most of which traditionally use much smaller weapons. In your own way you are already quite skilled at assassination, and some of that knowledge can be directly integrated and other parts give you ideas where to look for useful information. The Grey College has its own books on the topic, of course, but the Grey College is far from the only people with interest in getting a knife where it isn't wanted. The problem is that those people tend not to be the type to hold lessons or write books. But you do have an in with those that work in the shadows. [Rolling...] Spreading word to a specific person is quite hard in the Ranaldian community, but spreading word to the right person can be very easy. Word travels north at the speed of rumour and someone, somewhere, cocks a head and listens. The reply brings you north at the speed of Dwarven artifice, and under cover of night you slip into the town of Regrakhof. Once it was a tiny satellite town of Drakenhof, barely large enough to justify the palisade that keeps the milder terrors of Sylvania at bay, but after long-term garrisoning by Stirland's Fourth Division standing guard over the road north towards Sylvania's final vampiric holdouts and the influx of refugees from Drakenhof it's become relatively bustling. In the core of the original palisade, now surrounded by much sturdier fortification, you find the tavern you were directed to, and when entering it you experience the disconcerting sensation of becoming the center of attention even though nobody inside openly looks in your direction. An arm waves from across the room, and even though everyone was already looking away, attention turns away from you too. "Codrin Petrescu," you say as you slip into a chair that was roughly-hewn once, but has been worn smooth by decades of constant use. "It's been a while. Cute name." "It was a necessity," says the careful and softly-spoken man who once commanded the Stirlandian forces of the Karak Eight Peaks Expedition. He's dressed in a nondescript cloak but a faint creak as he moves gives away the leathers underneath, as does the touch of Ghur still lingering in them. "So who are you, really?" He smiles from under his hood. "Better if I didn't say." You smile back. "I ask for politeness' sake. I know what you are, if not who." "Oh?" "Back during the Expedition, you mentioned Siegfriedhof." The smile slips slightly. "You remember that?" "I keep notes. Since that was the foundation of your authority back during the Expedition I knew that much had to be true. You couldn't have pulled off a large-scale deception without serious respect from the Sylvanians, which rules out unaffiliated - if you were a lone hero type of that magnitude, someone else would have heard of you. So a respected organization." "There are many respected organizations." "Sure, but not that many with connections to Siegfriedhof. You don't fight like a Knight, so not a Black Guard or a Raven Knight. You wouldn't have heard the word I put out if you were a Sigmarite, so you're not one of Helhunten's. You wouldn't have needed or heeded the word if you were a Dreamwalker. You're used to large-unit tactics, so not Andanti. You're Sylvanian, so not the Tsarevich Pavel Society. That just leaves the Shrouds. And you're meeting me here instead of at a Garden, so Fellowship, not Order." He's quiet for a while. "You've gotten sharp," he says. "My robes aren't grey because I skimp on laundry." "Point taken." "So why was the Fellowship involved in a Dwarven war? Did the Guardians call you in?" He shrugs. "When your Count rolled into Sylvania, there was a lot of opportunities for people who had been waiting and watching for them. After taking those opportunities, a lot of people needed to be elsewhere in a hurry. And some of us aren't the types to while away a few years in a Tilean abbey." You nod, satisfied. "Okay," you say. "Okay?" he repeats, eyebrows raised. "Okay." You wouldn't normally take someone at their word this easily, but the faint hint of Morr about him counts for a lot. He gives you a searching look, then drains his beer. "Okay. I'll teach you what you want to know. The techniques have been honed for Vampires, but there's not many beings out there that aren't at least inconvenienced by a stab to the heart." As promised, the next few days are a masterclass in ways to deliver sudden violence as quickly and unexpectedly as possible. Techniques honed against Vampiric reflexes have had every ounce of flair and inefficiency stripped away by necessity and attrition. You learn techniques for delivering stabs and slashes from neutral positions, and though you may never need them, you also pick up ones for stabbing from bowing, prostration, lying asleep, and to someone clutching you from behind, each of which tells an unspoken story of cocky Vampires meeting unexpected ends. Sure, there are Vampires that seem to linger forever, but those are just the ones that get famous - for each one of them, there's a thousand that think their new powers make them invincible, and many of them quickly learn that there are those that prey on the predators. "Why is the Fellowship helping me?" you ask Codrin as he wraps up his teachings to you. Sure, you were satisfied his motives were pure, but that didn't mean you weren't still curious about them. He looks at you, then looks around him. "If Abelhelm wasn't enough, Roswita would have been. If two Elector Counts died to Vampires back-to-back, the third would have pulled out, and things would have returned to the way they once were. Instead we're still pruning bloodlines that have grown in Sylvanian soil for centuries." "But not uprooting?" He gives a bleak smile. "Not in our lifetimes." [Branarhune aspect developed and mastered: quick-draw. Remaining aspects: guard bypass, hand switching.] --- "So," you say to the Hochlander. "Tell me about the Cult of Karnos." "Here?" he asks doubtfully, walking alongside you. You wave your hand at the empty halls. "Kvinn-Wyr. The only beings inside this mountain are Dwarven architects, and they're from Karak Azul. This is as secure as it gets." You understand his caution, though. Spying on non-proscribed Cults is the kind of thing that can get touchy. He nods. "Okay. Karnos is said to be the God of Beasts, worshipped by hunters and propitiated by peasants on the edge of woodlands. Sort of like Lupos in the 'respect the savagery of nature', sort of like Shrowl in the focus on hunting. They're pretty insular, but hunters generally are. Not many records of them that I could find, but again, hunters. The Cult of Taal would probably have records, but they consider it internal business. A contact found a few mentions in Witch Hunter archives, they were investigated as a suspected blood cult - that's sort of shorthand for 'we don't know if it's Khaine or Khorne or Ahalt or Vampires, but they're too into blood so it's probably one of them' - but they didn't find anything untoward. "Getting someone in wasn't easy, they tend to be the sorts that take decades to generations to warm up to newcomers, but one of the EIC's Talabeclander employees managed to get in. As far as they could see, it was all very normal - well, niche wilderness Cult normal. A few deadly serious prayers to say while hunting and as thanks over the body of a kill, and the rest is pretty relaxed - drinking, feasting, couples disappearing into the bushes together. Nothing out of the ordinary for that sort of people." "A minorly esoteric social club, then?" you ask, frowning. "Mostly. But the thing is, the reason the Witch Hunters investigated them in the first place was some of the Runes they leave around their shrines. Looked a bit like a scythe to them. I managed to get rubbings of their runes, and while I can see where the Witch Hunters were coming from..." he hands you a notepad. [Godly matters: Piety, 99+26+5(Polyglot)-10(Overwork)=120.] "Yes, that definitely looks like a scythe," you say, frowning at it. "And even blood dripping off it, if that's what you're looking for. But that's Eltharin, really badly-drawn Eltharin. It could be Verdan, or Volroth..." you turn it over. "Or Drathro, if they have it backwards." You flip through the pages. "And that could be Kurn-ath... so if we assume that first one was Verdan..." you flip through the rest. "That's it? No Cadai? That five-pointed crowny-looking one?" "That's all the ones they were using." "Verdan, Kurn-ath, but not Cadai..." Two of the three parts of the sigil of Kurnous, Elven God of the Hunt. You look up, and stop walking. "Oh, here it is. This was a muster hall, apparently." You look through it, frowning, trying to look through centuries of neglect to the potential underneath. "Does it seem damp in here to you?" He nods. "There is a bit of it in the air." "Not here, then." You turn and keep walking. "So is it... humility, in that they're not threatening Taal for supremacy? Stealth, because they're operating in Taal's backyard? Or is it just random accumulated esoterica?" "It seems to be fairly solid. The Witch Hunter records were from sixty years ago, and they had the same Rune I found carved into a tree, line for line." "How old were the Cultists?" "Not many grey hairs. Drinking in the forest all night is a young man's sport." "So fairly steady handing down of traditions. Maybe the corruption is at the source." You frown, and turn your attention to another corner of your memory. "Talabheim is the heart of Taal worship..." "It's in the name," the Hochlander says with a smile. "The Taalite holy city, founded by the Cult..." But they weren't the first. You found old maps of Elven settlements while researching the Eonir, and what is now Talabheim was once Athel Maraya. What makes competition for Taal pop up in His backyard? When it wasn't always His backyard. Elven Gods flourishing at the same time that the Eonir are turning their attention to human affairs? Human religious affairs? Could that just be a coincidence? Or perhaps you're looking at this wrong. As Cython said: do two Kings share a Kingdom? What if the crown is absent because Taal set it aside? There are always those that opt for the obscure simply because it is obscure. Would a God hedge His bets by doffing His crown and acting as His own competition? That might be a smart way to squeeze out genuine competition... "Any foreigners? Middenlanders, perhaps?" "None, of any stripe. Insular sorts, like I said." You frown. A piece of the puzzle, maybe, but just a piece. "Alright. Good work. Any news from the rest of the EIC?" "We've finally got a presence in Barak Varr." "Dwarves don't like leasing to non-Dwarves," you note. "Apart from that, just further consolidation. More and more attention is turning towards the Black Waters project and there's plenty of other trade concerns sniffing around southern Stirland, looking for a way in. The Sylvanian sieges continue, and there's rumours that Sylvania might be parcelled out once the job is done. Stirland is happy that the boot is on the other foot, but there's hints it might not be happy for long if it keeps paying to keep the entire army mobilized." You nod. Nothing unexpected, and no news is good news, especially when one is about to embark on an ambitious research project. With half an ear you listen to the rest of the EIC news while you make your way to the next prospective site for the Library. Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The four with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) [+] EIC Reports (does not cost a choice) - already covered Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Belegar, to discuss who will be Loremaster after you. [ ] Panoramia, to properly finishing catching up with her. [ ] Gretel, who's apparently spending her newly-earned wealth to make herself at home. [ ] The Karak Azul Architects, to get to know their ideas for the potential layouts of the Library in detail. Foreign Relations [ ] Altdorf, to witness the octenniel duels for the position of Supreme Patriarch. [ ] Stirland, to see for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. [ ] Middenland, to see how the Ulricans are going with their new Eonir coreligionists. [ ] Karak Vlag, to see if they've been talked out from behind their fortifications yet. Friends Abroad [ ] Roswita, to get a sense for who will control Sylvania after you turned down the position. [ ] Julia, to see what she has gotten up to as Stirland's most experienced spy master. [ ] Eike, as she begins her tutelage at the Grey College. Following Up [ ] The Amber College, to check in on the salamanders. [ ] The Gold College, to see what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. - There will be a three hour moratorium, to allow for suggestions for additions to the above. If you have any, please share them. - Mathilde will have choices about the library's layout whether her nerding out over it is chosen here or not.

Turn 34 Social - 2486.5 - Part 1 - The 24th Supreme Patriarch

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Eike, as she begins her tutelage at the Grey College. [*] Altdorf, to witness the octenniel duels for the position of Supreme Patriarch. [*] Panoramia, to properly finishing catching up with her. [*] Karak Vlag, to see if they've been talked out from behind their fortifications yet. [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) For twenty-four years, Ghur has blown strongly in the streets of Altdorf. An entire generation has grown up always knowing a city where even the lowliest must be treated with cautious respect, as all those without a home to shelter in, from street urchins to feral dogs, are those that have become most attuned with the Wind of the wild. The oft-indistinguishable guilds and gangs of the waterfronts have swelled with people no longer willing to be subjugated, with the Hooks and the Fish spilling into outright war against each other, turning parts of the docklands into a battlefield. The parks and the Zoo swell with visitors even as the amount of injuries sustained in them climbs, and the city's population holds steady as the constant influx of newcomers to the city is balanced by those leaving, chasing a yearning they've discovered within themselves for the untamed wilderness. You were twelve when Dragomas supplanted Alric as Supreme Patriarch, and as a Junior Apprentice you could not leave the grounds of the Grey College, and even if you could your magical senses at the time were vastly insufficient to meaningfully understand what was happening. When Dragomas retained his title for a second term, you had just begun your work in Stirland; when he did so again, you were busy preparing to join Belegar's Expedition. But now you have not just the time to pay attention, but also the right as Lady Magister to stand in the Obsidian Hall and witness the challenges firsthand - and, though you are not currently so inclined, to make a challenge yourself. Today the streets are mostly empty of Altdorf's citizens as the city's long memory knows that back in 2415, the duels between the Wizards were replaced with all-out magical war, begun when one of then-Supreme Patriarch Alric's underlings by the name of High Luminary Horx imprisoned Alric in crystal and unleashed a Storm of Magic onto the city. The citizens aren't the only ones who remember. The Holy Order of the Templars of Sigmar always have a strong presence in Altdorf for the duels, and many Wizards suspect they do so in hopes of getting another chance at revoking the charter of the Colleges of Magic. Magisters Vigilant and Battle Wizards of every Order likewise stand ready to strike down any would-be Horx before they deliver that chance to the Witch Hunters. The Battle Wizards in particular are almost fanatically loyal to Dragomas, and will brook no tarnishing of the reputation of the man who has so dramatically improved their living conditions over the years. The twenty-fourth Supreme Patriarch will be decided today, and that again shows the influence of Supreme Patriarch Alric. Volans served two terms, but at the time was considered the second Supreme Patriarch after Teclis, rather than second and third. But though Alric was stripped of the leadership of the Colleges in the aftermath of the Night of a Thousand Arcane Duels, he retained leadership of the Light Order, and then in 2438 he defeated Felip Iyrtu of the Amethysts and once more became the Supreme Patriarch. But record-keeping decided it was untidy to have the 12th Supreme Patriarch be head of the Colleges once more after the 13th, 14th, and 15th had reigned, and the numbering system was tweaked to count individual terms rather than unique Patriarchs, making Alric the 14th and 18th. And then, after being defeated by Paranoth the Wanderer and then reclaiming it again, the 20th. Dragomas has been the 21st, 22nd, and 23rd Supreme Patriarchs, making him tied with Alric for most terms and the only Supreme Patriarch to serve three consecutive terms. When leadership is decided by a one-on-one duel, turning into a hitherto unknown and evidently very powerful species of Dragon is quite difficult to argue with, and many in the Colleges believe that Dragomas will be the 24th Supreme Patriarch. Today, you'll find out for sure. The Obsidian Hall is a large octagonal structure made of thick, smooth, and magically inert obsidian. It was built by Teclis and the founding heads of the Colleges of Magic for the sole purpose of deciding the leadership of the Colleges, and in its center lies a raised circular altar - well, most of the literature on the subject says altar, but you would argue that its secular nature makes 'plinth' or 'socle' more correct - over which the Staff of Volans will float. Each wall holds an alcove behind protective enchantments for the Lord and Lady Magisters to witness the duels, and you enter the structure from the Grey Order's side of the octagon. "Lady Magister Weber," says Reiner Starke with a short bow as you enter, the only one already present. "Porter Starke," you reply. "How many are we expecting?" "Four for sure. Grey's going to try to be here, Kupfer hasn't said one way or the other, and Melkoth may or may not be here in time." You nod in understanding. You don't last long with the name Grey if you're not cautious about your travel arrangements, Kupfer is retired in all but name, and Melkoth has what might charitably be called a unique relationship with the passage of time. "Have you witnessed one of these before?" "Not firsthand." "How many challengers do you think we'll see?" He shrugs. "Paranoth has the puissance but not the inclination. Feldmann has the people skills but isn't much of a duellist. Reicthard isn't a risk-taker. Elspeth..." he hesitates. "Is terrifying," Algard says from behind you, causing the two of you to jump, "but I don't think she's entrenched enough to make a play for more, even if she was willing. And she might not be willing - she stepped up as Magister Matriarch largely because there wasn't anyone else suitable after Hexensohn's..." he pauses for a fraction of a second, eyes darting over to you, "unfortunate fate. And as for me, I'm happy with Dragomas' leadership." "That leaves Maria Stossel and Alric," you note. "Trying to predict what Maria's going to do just makes her less predictable," Algard grouches, and Starke nods in agreement. Discussion is cut off by raised voices outside the door, as what must be Altdorf's least sensible remise driver tries to argue a higher fee out of his passengers and has the error of his ways quite firmly and thoroughly explained to him. A moment later Wilhelmine von Bucht and Kupfer enter arm in arm, and you note that Wilhelmine seems to be supporting some of Kupfer's weight. "Not late, are we?" Wilhelmine asks airily. "The Jades are always late, we're fine," Kupfer says. "We were just discussing who might be the challengers today," Algard says, peering out of the Alcove. Across the room you can just make out figures in the opposite Alcoves by the light of their open doors - what must be the Lights, Golds, and Ambers since the layout is based on the Wheel of Magic - but it's too dim for regular eyes to make out much and with this much obsidian pressing in your Magesight is all but blind. "There'll be a few ambitious and newly-promoted Lords and Ladies that will have a go," says Lady Magister Grey, who you were sure wasn't there a moment ago. "There always are. Dragomas is a gentle sort, relatively speaking, so they should be fine." "When did you get here?" Starke asks of her. "Yesterday," she replies with a sniff. Speculation continues as the minutes tick past and the entrances of some of the other Colleges slide closed, and Melkoth and Kurtis Krammovitch arrive just in time to confirm that, once more, the Jades are the last to trickle in - the duel taking place in winter makes it difficult for those of them attuned to the seasons. As the last door closes the chamber is almost, but not quite, plunged into darkness, the only remaining illumination being those of the Light and Bright Orders that live up to the names in a more literal manner than most. "Brothers and sisters," booms the voice of the Supreme Patriarch, as the Staff of Volans glows with an amber light that reveals the shirtless Dragomas in the middle of the room. "Here we are once more. You all know me. You all know what I stand for. If you think you can do a better job, come forward and prove the strength of that belief." He slams the Staff of Volans into the center of the room, and it lifts itself into the air. "Dragomas stands for the Amber Brotherhood." There's another slam and a flash of pure-white light, and a voice that echoes unnaturally rises. "Alric stands for the Order of Light." A third slam, a golden light. "Feldmann stands for the Golden Order." Green. "Paranoth stands for the Order of Life." Blue. "Maria Stossel stands for the Celestial College." Grey, from right beside you. "Algard stands for the Grey Order." Purple. "Elspeth von Draken stands for the Amethyst Order." Red. "Norbert Reicthard stands for the Bright Order." There's a shimmer in the air, and then the seven flashes of lights are drawn into the middle of the room and into the altar, and your Magesight flinches back as a magical barrier flashes into life in front of the alcove, and an even illumination from nowhere in particular brightens the room. Silence reigns for a moment, and you can see those of the other Orders looking back and forth from their alcoves, wondering who will be Dragomas' first challenger. "Alric of the Light Order challenges Dragomas of the Amber Brotherhood," an echoing voice announces, and directly across from you the barrier opens for the challenger to step through. Dragomas turns and regards Alric, but if he has any comments he keeps them to himself, instead giving a nod to the man and walking in your direction until he is standing opposite Alric's position. The two stand motionless for a long moment, and you note the contrast between them: Dragomas shirtless, muscled, and deeply tanned, Alric pale and thin in pure-white robes and softly glowing. Then the Staff of Volans pulses with magic, releasing precisely equal amounts of Ghur and Hysh into the room. [Rolling...] "Stand DOWN," Dragomas thunders, his voice reverberating through the room, and Alric seems to physically recoil from it. Dragomas strides forward confidently, and by the time Alric has collected himself and has started to react, Dragomas' hand is already wrapping around the Staff of Volans, pulling it from the air and unleashing another flood of Ghur. Dragomas stands in place, staring Alric down. "I yield," Alric says a moment later. You exhale, sharing glances with your fellows on either side. "Not the best showing," Starke notes. "Not the sort of thing that inspires confidence in leadership," Wilhelmine agrees. "Might be trouble in the Light Order," you say, remembering your conversation with Mira. If she needs an opening to try to move against Alric, she probably just found it. As Alric retreats back behind the Light Order's barrier, Dragomas turns in place, surveying the alcoves for the next challenger. "Arburg of the Order of Life challenges Dragomas of the Amber Brotherhood," comes a rich but stilted voice, and a woman steps forward from your right. "Kurtis?" Algard prompts. "Former Battle Wizard, promoted a few years ago. Fought alongside the forces of Ostland and Nordland against Beastmen, and with the Second Fleet against Norscans." [Rolling...] With a flash of Ghur and Ghyran the next duel begins, and Arburg quickly folds Ghyran into a spell that causes the obsidian to crack as roots punch through, forming a living battle-altar below her. It's a tricky piece of magic and done commendably, but while she was doing that, Dragomas had performed his signature spell, his skin hardening and stretching until he almost fills his half of the chamber. His now-draconic gaze meets Arburg's, and for a silent moment all is still. Then Ghyran stirs once more, and in seconds Dragomas has flitted across the chamber, ignoring the Staff entirely in favour of pouncing atop Arburg, his claws tightening around skin that is already in the process of hardening into stone. Once more they freeze in place, a silent conversation seeming to fill the air between them before Arburg nods and says, "I yield." "Very neat spellwork," Melkoth notes. "Strong showing for a recent graduate," Algard agrees. Two more duels come and go. One involves a Gold Wizard that pulls in a truly massive amount of Chamon and tries to fold it into a spell that causes grumbling from the other Greys before it's rather contemptuously slapped aside by Dragomas, who glares at him with such venom that he quails. Then a Celestial Wizard stands against Dragomas and draws in Azyr until she crackles with energies, but instead of transforming Dragomas plucks an Amber Spear from empty air and throws it at the challenger with such force that she is pinned to the magical barrier behind her. After a brief interlude while the spear is banished and the damage healed by the Jade Wizards, Dragomas once more stands in the center of the room, looking for a new challenger. [Rolling...] But none step forward. "Let all witness that Dragomas of the Amber Brotherhood has earned the title of Supreme Patriarch," Dragomas announces. "So witnessed," comes the chorus from the leaders of the other seven Orders, and a pulse of Ghur rises from the Staff of Volans and floods outwards, disrupting the magical barriers, pushing open the doors, and flooding into the streets beyond. For eight more years the Amber Brotherhood will lead the Colleges of Magic, Dragomas will advise the Emperor, and Ghur will blow stronger than any other Wind in Altdorf.

Turn 34 Social - 2486.5 - Part 2

Spoiler: Unfinished business [*] Eike, as she begins her tutelage at the Grey College. [*] Panoramia, to properly finishing catching up with her. [*] Karak Vlag, to see if they've been talked out from behind their fortifications yet. [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) The Grey College's dormitories are segregated by age and gender, and the one that Eike would have been assigned to is one that you are quite familiar with, having spent half of your own Apprenticeship in it. Being Lady Magister might get you within the grounds of the College, but that doesn't mean you can simply wander in as you please. Even Algard would not be able to enter outside of emergencies without the permission of whoever he was visiting. It seems Eike has already granted you permanent permission to visit as you see fit, as the caretaker on watch at the crossroads that leads to each of the residential quarters simply nods to you as you pass. Eike's is the smallest of the six dormitories and rarely home to more than a dozen young girls, but that doesn't mean it's cramped, nor does it mean there's not privacy to be had. There's a seemingly bottomless warehouse of old and battered but well-made furniture and privacy screens for each Apprentice to customize the portion of the room available to them, and the less social Apprentices can and do take advantage of this to build themselves a solid wall around their bed. You were one of them once, before you found your footing in the atmosphere of easy camaraderie that a shared Wind allows for. Eike seems to be more inherently extroverted than you were at her age, as she's simply screened off her writing desk against one wall and the rest of her space is open to the rest of the room, and she's currently sitting cross-legged on her bed as she frowns at a slim and battered book. You smile nostalgically at the sight, and more as you run your eyes over her other furniture. She's either a quick study or quick to earn the trust of Apprentices that have been here longer, as there's the telltale signs of very careful breaches of the rules of the dorm rooms. You remember that the custodians were always very careful to emphasize without seeming to emphasize that the rules of the dorm rooms were not the Rules of the College. Little-r rules like those against pets or keeping books past their due date or the trade in harmless contraband were punishable by chores and searched for by carefully predictable spot-checks, while the big-r Rules contained in the Articles were absolutely sacrosanct. A mind unable to navigate what can be perceived as an ambiguity is one unsuited for Ulgu, and those that broke down at or raged against the perceived unfairness of it were transferred to other, more suitable Orders. Eike's area shows the sign of one that has found or been taught adaptations: bedsheets wider than the ones she would have been assigned to protect the area under her bed from prying eyes, the footlocker wedged under the bed so it could not be easily opened and searched, the books on her shelves arranged with spines level to create hidden areas behind them. As an Apprentice you kept bowls of food and water under your bed for a cat you'd adopted called Morr, and as you grew older, you became involved in the trade in officially-forbidden-but-not-forbidden-forbidden novels that required similar protection. It must be a difficult needle to thread, you reflect: to develop the necessary mindset of deception and misdirection while also making sure that those developing them would still cleave to the Articles. "Mathilde!" Eike exclaims as she finally notices you, and from the corner of your eye you notice the heads popping up and around furniture to take note of the visitor. "Hello Eike," you say as she comes over for a hug. "How are you settling in?" She sighs. "It's all very complicated." You nod. "It starts making a lot more sense when you get used to it." Literal internalization: the soul adapting to the presence of Ulgu. You don't say that out loud, though. People get jumpy about how mutable their souls can be. She leads you over to her area, and you pull the chair from her writing desk out to sit on as she sorts through her books, and as best you can you try to explain some of the concepts she points out as eluding her. You're far from the best teacher for this, as you haven't gone over material this basic in about twenty-five years, but that's not the point. The point is making sure she knows that she still has people that will help her, even as she's uprooted from the life she knew and dropped into a completely alien environment. After a while the questions go quiet and Eike seems to be thinking. "Oma says being a Wizard will make me better at running the EIC when I'm older." You look up, and you smile to yourself at how none of the other girls need to quickly look away, because they're already acting like they aren't eavesdropping. "If that's what you want to do," you say. "What do you mean?" "It takes a long time to become a Wizard. You'll be a different person by the time you finish your Apprenticeship. It will be up to that person whether they want to run the EIC, or whether they want to do a traditional Journey, or even whether they want to be a Battle Wizard instead." "But the EIC's important," she objects. "Important enough that the person running should want to be running it, that way they'll give it their all. Me and your Oma can work something out for it if we need to." She goes quiet as she considers that. "Now," you say as you stand. "Have you found the good nooks in the library yet?" "Both of them," she says proudly. "Only fourteen left to find, then," you say, and smile at her look of shock. "Come with me, I'll give you some hints for the next few." --- Even for someone that has grown used to the trips across the Old World, the gyrocarriage trip to Karak Vlag is a long and tiring one. You spend a lot of your time reading anyway, but doing so in cramped conditions with the drone of engines and the chill of altitude for company is surprisingly draining and it doesn't take long for you to yearn to be doing anything else. But it's a burden you have to put up with, as your sense of responsibiltiy and your ego are aligning with each other to point you in their direction. You want to know more about the Dwarves that survived almost two centuries locked away in the warp and besieged by Daemons, and how well they're finding their place in the world once more. The approach to Karak Vlag from Peak Pass is currently watched over by Clan Redbeard and any uninvited visitors would normally be met with a barrage of questions and then a more literal barrage if their answers were not satisfactory, but arriving by air bypasses the worst of it and the Ranger watching the recently-hewn landing pad simply nods you through after you identify yourself. You wonder if Snorri's told the rest of his Clan that you might visit at some point, or if they simply have faith that the Dwarves of Karak Vlag are capable of dealing with a single intruder if it proves necessary. It takes much less time to reach the forewardmost defences of Karak Vlag, and though everything in front of them is still as ruined as you remember, at least the path through them is illuminated now. The illumination itself is of interest, and you take some time to examine one - it looks like a normal lantern at first, but instead of a wick inside there's a small stone sphere bearing a single Rune and emitting a steady glow. After some thought you suppose that makes sense, if they survived almost two centuries cut off from the rest of the world, they would have had to limit the use of finite resources like lamp oil as much as possible. Runes only require the effort of a Runesmith to make, and a simple Rune to make light is the sort of thing that could be made for practice by an Apprentice. The path of light ends abruptly at the still-formidable fortifications that mark the point where the Dwarves have reclaimed the Karak thus far, leaving yourself harshly illuminated and the defences and defenders plunged into darkness. It's a form of defence that tells you quite a bit. Daemonic invaders would care little for light conditions, as just like you can, they'd be able to see through the darkness with their own equivalent of Magesight. Most other invaders that might come from above would not have this advantage, whether they be Orcs, Hobgoblins, Kurgan, or Chaos Dwarves. So this bodes well for how much they've accepted that they truly have been returned to reality. No point taking chances, so instead of striding out into the light yourself, you allow an Illusion to go out in your place, just in case the locals are just as free with crossbow quarrels as you remember. "I am Mathilde Weber, Dalmhornzhufokrul," you announce to the darkness once more. "Aye, that you are," comes a voice in reply. "And more than that, we hear." You nod. "Currently the Loremaster of Karak Eight Peaks." For a few more months, at least. "Azrildrekked. Waaaghdrengi. Karag Zangunaz Vengryni. All well and good, but we've had some harsh lessons about things that seem too good to be true. You just stay right there, we've sent for someone to weigh the truth of your words." You keep yourself occupied by making sure the Illusion convincingly displays slight boredom as you wait, and before too long a Dwarf emerges into the island of light in the middle of the room, carrying a pair of stone stools. "I am Brokkr Ivaldisson of the Second Generation, Azulokri and Rhunkit," he announces, looking your Illusion up and down. "I have the honour of being the current Loremaster of Karak Vlag." At first glance, he appears fairly typical for a Dwarf of advanced years who is almost but not quite yet a Longbeard, but the more you look, the more discrepancies you spot. The only metal on his person seems to be the axe on his hip, and the rest of his clothing is fabric and leather - and reptilian leather at that, instead of the more typical goat. His hair and beard are unornamented and hang loose instead of being kept under control by rings and plaits, but seems no less carefully tended for it. He's thinner and wirier than the Dwarves you're used to. And he's also looking at your Illusion with growing thoughtfulness. You dismiss it and step forward yourself, and he nods as he turns to your true self. "No outsiders may be allowed past the second line of defence until a majority of each generation of the Regency Council agree to opening our doors to visitors once again," he says. "We shall have to talk here. Can I offer you a drink?" "Yes, thank you." He disappears into the darkness, and returns with a pair of flagons - stone, and filled with water, which might have caused you to splutter as you discovered it if you weren't sipping so cautiously. He takes a seat on one of the stools, and you sit across from him. "What brings you to Karak Vlag?" he asks. "Curiosity, mostly." He nods in understanding, one Loremaster to another. "Satisfying that curiosity is the least we could do. What is it you wish to know?" "For starters, what is the significance of Second Generation?" "The nearest ancestor of mine to have lived before the Escarpment was a grandparent. There are significant cultural differences between the generations, and as such an equal amount of each is represented on the Regency Council." He smiles wryly. "Which I suppose we shall have to rename. Many of the Royal Clan had been with a Throng that was outside the Karak when it was stolen. There had been hopes they had found refuge with the Karaz Ankor and could resume the throne, but it seems those hopes were in vain." "You've been without a monarch all this time?" "The King was on the front lines against the initial assault, immediately after the Escarpment. He fell in battle. His heir disappeared a week later. We put together a Council of Elders to make decisions until things were peaceful enough to investigate what happened to him and work out the succession, but the Royal Clan went extinct within the first decade." He smiles sadly. "Many Clans did not last a single generation in the new reality we found ourselves in." You frown. "I'd heard that two thirds of the Karak had survived." "Our population is two thirds of what it was when we were stolen," he corrects, "but it was once lower, and has been climbing steadily for over a century. Once the Daemons changed tactics from their frontal assault to a more insidious probing, we had time to take stock of our circumstances. We had but a single enemy, and Her goal was either inscrutable or mercurial. All would kill or die to thwart Her, but none could agree on how that could be accomplished. Some thought Her goal was to capture as many Dwarves alive as possible, and argued that the Karak should die. Some thought Her goal was to keep us imprisoned to leave Kislev vulnerable from the east, and argued that the Karak should live." He chuckles in what seems like genuine amusement. "Ironically, the two factions found symbiosis. Those that wished to die free needed some to stay living so that they would not be vulnerable to capture before they perished, and those that wished to live needed those willing to die to protect the Karak from predation." "Do you know which faction was correct?" you ask. "Both," he says firmly. "We have encountered the harvest that the Prince has taken from us. If She could have secured an entire Hold of those, such a weapon She would have against our southern cousins! Compared to that fate, death would be so very preferable, so the doomseekers were not wrong. It must have been an impossible decision to make all those years ago, without hindsight to vindicate the hopeful. But in living we have rebuked Her thrice - once for escaping Her claws, once for taking pleasure in each others' arms without being ruled by it, and once for returning to the world to protect it once again." He gives the smile of one who has seen the completion of several generations of work. "Some of us always knew the day would come. There is a river running through the lowest levels of the Karak, and even after we were stolen away it flowed clear and clean, bringing water and silt and even fish in. Our Rhunkit-" "Sorry, you mentioned that before. What is a Rhunkit?" "No Runesmith survived long past the Escarpment," he says frankly. "They knew too well where we were, and those that didn't fall in battle petrified themselves in their attempts to free us from it. But some of their Apprentices lived on, those that knew a little of the working of Runes but had not yet learned enough to despair. They taught all those that could trace even the narrowest of lines to Thungni what little they could, and now about a third of the Karak bear the title of Rhunkit, those that are able to interact with existing Runes and craft a very few simple ones. The Cult of Thungni, I hear, is quite outraged, but every one of those Apprentices had already embraced every punishment. Their names are forgotten, their properties forfeited, and once they had nothing left to teach, their lives were spent against the Daemons. So the Cult of Thungni can either march to war against the entire Karak or be silent. We will not apologize for surviving, and we have stood firm against far worse than they." "Ah," you say carefully. He did say that the culture of the Karak had changed over the generations, and you're starting to get an idea of what he means. Those that knew the Karaz Ankor may have once despaired at the judgement that awaited them when they returned to it, but it seems their children and grandchildren are less willing to embrace self-abasement at the measures they had to take. "As I was saying, the Rhunkit determined that the unchanging river meant that we still had some connection to the mountains we once knew. The entrance to our Karak led to the realm of Daemons, and so did any new tunnels we made, but that river still clung on - and so did the stone around it. So we mined along it for generations, carving out new chambers as we fell back from the old ones, finding cave complexes filled with fresh soil to farm in and small animals to raise for food and leather. Perhaps one day we would have dug our way to the surface along that underground river, or perhaps we merely vexed the sorcerations that imprisoned us by forcing it to cast a wider and wider net." You consider that. "I think that would be the case," you say. "The enchantment that held the Karak was absorbing an enormous amount of magical energy to sustain itself, and when I cut it off, it seemed to fail more abruptly than the Daemons expected. They had been gathering forces from three of the Chaos Gods, either for a last-ditch assault on you or to try to restore the energy flow, but they fell to infighting when they were caught by surprise by a sudden translation to reality." He grins savagely. "How wonderful, to have spoked Her wheel so effectively. I hope the next Everchosen arises within my lifetime so I can see it done at least once more." You smile at that, and clink your flagon against his in a toast to the thought. "Have you reopened communication with Kislev?" "Oh aye, we've had a veritable landslide of nobles and dignitaries very cautiously asking about the contents of this vault or the other. Been tricky to properly confirm that each is the proper descendant of the manlings that left this, that, and the other in our protection all those years ago, but they seem quite astonished that we went to the trouble and returned every jot of it. That seems to have confirmed for them that we're not meaningfully different than the Dwarves their ancestors knew, which makes our return easier. We've had more than enough of enforced autarky, we want everything the world has to offer - meat and fruit and vegetables and fabrics and ores and precious stones. Oh, and alcohol. The Elders do go on about it, though they've never been able to properly explain why." "It's an acquired taste." "I've got plenty of tastes without having to acquire more," he says with a shrug. "Oh, as one Loremaster to another, could you answer a question of culture of this Empire of yours?" "Of course." "Would it be inappropriate to invite a visitor from the Empire to share an intimate night with my wife and brother-husband?" You blink at him. "Most would consider it so," you eventually say, taking refuge in answering the question at face value. "It is an invitation that should only be made to someone you were already quite familiar with, and in private." "I see," he says unabashedly. "Thank you for the information." "Thank you for satisfying my curiosity." "It is nothing, compared to what we owe you." You come away from Karak Vlag thoughtful. It's changed quite a bit, as you suppose would be inevitable after almost two centuries of complete isolation in such trying circumstances. They're something of a makeshift republic, they've splintered from the Runesmithing traditions of the Cult of Thungni, their culture seems, erm, markedly different from the Dwarves you're familiar with. They've had to rebuild their entire society around necessity. No brewers if there's barely enough grain to feed everyone. No smelters and very few miners if you can only mine in a single direction, and that upriver. No traders, no hunters, no rangers. Just farmers, and fighters, and those reworking and maintaining their dwindling and irreplaceable metals as best they can over several generations. And yet they survived. No, more than that, they thrived. Their nadir was over a century ago, Brokkr said, and their population has been climbing since. Well, you suppose that makes sense, on both sides of the equation. The Daemons had reason to allow that as a renewable source of their new variety of shock troop, and as a self-maintaining toy for them to turn their attention to when they fancied. And on the Dwarven side, well, you're familiar with Dwarven fatalists, those that dwell on the decline of their race. But Karak Vlag's fatalists died in the first decade, leaving only those that embraced life as an act of defiance. You consider that for a moment, then draw a comparison to Karak Azul, isolated for millennia and constantly surrounded by greenskins but still strong despite it. Perhaps Dwarves with an immediate enemy to spite are ones more mentally healthy than those with no immediate threats, who have sufficient safety and freedom to despair at how much greater they used to be. For a moment you feel that same tinge of despair, as you wonder if the Karaz Ankor will learn from this and immediately feel that they probably won't. But Karak Vlag has a lesson for you too. Those that embrace despair will die, and leave only those that still know hope to inherit. The arch-conservatives of Karaz-a-Karak may continue to wither, but they are not the be-all and end-all of the Karaz Ankor. The Young Holds continue to grow, Zhufbar continues to invent, Barak Varr continues to trade, and Karak Kadrin continues to deepen its relationship with Ostermark. And Karak Eight Peaks lives once more. You find yourself smiling as you climb aboard the Gyrocarriage once more.

Turn 34 Social - 2486.5 - Part 3

Spoiler: Unfinished business [*] Panoramia, to properly finishing catching up with her. [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Panoramia once boasted to you of how indolent her winters were, but with her spending more and more time at your abode, you've gotten to see it for yourself and you're starting to think she was less than honest. Sure, she's not exactly energetic in the colder months, but wherever she's lazing seems to accrete untidy piles of notes and reference materials, and though she often looks like she's napping you can tell by her breathing that she's still awake, just deep in concentration. Her winters are nowhere near as frittered away as she implied, even if she's not trudging around in the dirt during them. It does make her very easy company when you're engaged in your own research. Many days pass in comfortable silence broken only by the rustling of pages, scratching of quills, and crackling of the fire. "What was Karak Vlag eating all that time?" she asks suddenly one day, and you look up from your own reading to see her frowning curiously out at you through the gap between her book and the blanket she's currently draped in. "Stonebread and mushrooms, I gather. Dwarves don't like to grow crops underground, but they can if they must." "Why don't they like it? It seems like it would be right up their alley." "The Farmers and Herders Guild used to have strains of crops that could grow underground, but most of the Guild and their crops were wiped out in the Time of Woes. So nowadays growing underground requires either a series of mirrors and a new entrance to defend to bring in sunlight, or a Runesmith spending time on illuminating Runes, which is something that isn't directly defending the Karak. Growing and herding on the mountainsides can be kept entirely in-guild for the Karaks that still have Clans dedicated to it, or done by Brewers and Rangers for those that don't. Or they can trade. A big part of the Silver Age was the alliance with Sigmar proving that humans were reliable enough to depend upon to supply foods." She frowns. "We are?" "Well, when they're buying it with Dwarven gold and goods, we are." "What about the one down south? Kazrik's hold?" "Karak Azul? They're the exception. They took in most of the survivors from here and Karak Drazh and Karak Izril and they didn't have anyone nearby to trade with, so they've got Clans dedicated to both the old ways and the new, which is enough to be self-sufficient." "Will the other Holds be learning from them, now that they have access to them?" You shake your head. "Probably not." "Why not? They're Dwarves. I thought being self-sufficient is their thing." You shake your head again. "Most Dwarves would rather master a highly-respected craft than be forced by necessity to learn a less-respected one. And farming is one of those. Even those from Clans dedicated to farming prefer to grow for the Brewers and only make bread from imported grains - brewing is one of Valaya's spheres, after all, so that's seen as 'better'." Her frown deepens. "They don't respect farmers? I've never gotten that impression from them." "They don't respect Dwarven farmers. There's no Ancestor God of Farming, so if you are farming, you're doing something their Ancestor Gods didn't consider important. Humans have Rhya and the Halflings have Esmerelda-" "No, she's for cooking and feeding. Agriculture is Josias." "Right, so humans and Halflings are following the example put down by what the Dwarves see as our own Ancestor Gods. Just as the Elves were with Isha, back when the Dwarves were trading with them - which was right from the start, Grimnir and Caledor Dragontamer set the foundations for that alliance during the Coming of Chaos. Then after the War of the Beard, they start trading with humans instead - Nehekhara and early Tilea and Mourkhain and, eventually, the Empire. So subsistence farming became associated with their dark age, and they prefer to trade for food and farm for brewing feedstock. They see that as the ideal, and consider turning Dwarf-grown grain into food instead of beer wasteful." She considers that for a while. "Didn't you say Karak Azul seemed like the healthiest of the Old Holds?" "That sounds like something I'd say." "So they're happier than the other Old Holds, which are doing 'better' by Dwarf standards but are still miserable, and you said Karak Vlag seemed in good spirits despite their circumstances." You nod. "My theory is that it's an immediacy thing. If there's an enemy right in front of them that they're thwarting, they focus on that instead of the wider circumstances." "What if it's a diet thing? You remember the slime I was studying? From the Skaven?" You nod. "The animals that eat it seem to be in perfect health physically, but they become jittery and more prone to fighting, especially over food. What if the Dwarves have a similar problem with their diet?" You frown at that. "Well, the Karak Vlag Dwarves - well, the one of them I saw, anyway - was much thinner than most Dwarves I've seen. And Karak Azul Dwarves tend to be leaner as well. If the diet they see as a sign of success is failing them in some way..." You shake your head. "No, that doesn't make sense. The Young Holds have the same diet, and they don't have the same malaise." "Perhaps not exactly the same," Panoramia says thoughtfully, looking about herself, and then shifting in place until an arm makes its way out of the blankets to pick up a quill. "Looking for a new project?" you ask curiously. "The Eastern Valley will still need me to be on hand for some time, but it's getting to the point where it's reactive, rather than proactive. Even if we start turning the Caldera into pasture as well, that will be much simpler than making actual cropland. There's been some interest in the Order of challenging the humoral theory as a way to undermine the Elementalists, so if there's some sort of case study to be had amongst the Dwarves, it could be seen very positively." You give her a considering look. "Thinking of rebuilding bridges?" She sighs. "Maybe. I've been thinking of finally trying for graduation - my feelings on the whole Earth Mother situation hasn't changed but I'd be okay with swearing oaths to the abstract concept of the natural cycle of life embodied in the Jade Wind that just happens to have the label of 'Earth Mother', which is apparently seen as acceptable." "If you're willing, I think you absolutely should. You're already treated as a Magister in every meaningful way here, so you deserve the official recognition." She smiles at you, and you smile back. --- "Behold!" you say, pulling the sheet off the finished painting with a flourish. The other Wizards lean in to examine it. "Why am I sleeveless?" Johann asks, looking at the lovingly detailed biceps on display. Well, not quite looking, but still seeing. You had the artist use a different metal as a base for each pigment. You shrug. "Artistic license, I assume." "Probably the same reason I was given so many muscles," Maximilian says, looking at his own representation. You shake your head amusedly. "Max, you're a blacksmith. A blacksmith studying under a Dwarf. If anything, he understated it." "Is that a Pistolier cuirass?" Hubert asks. "Why would I be wearing that?" "Am I really that tall? And looming?" Gretel asks. "At least he got the marks of rank correct," Adela notes. "Non-Wizards usually don't." You smile and sit back as the Wizards each nitpick their own depictions. The artist might have taken a few liberties, but you feel like he managed to capture the essence of the Wizards quite well. "Well," you say after giving them enough time to get it out of their systems, "my main concern was losing some of us to the Expedition, but this will still serve as a welcome memento of our time together. As I'm stepping down as Loremaster of Karak Eight Peaks, I will no longer be responsible for Wizard-wrangling, and I would expect that my replacement would be rather more hands-off with us all. So this may be the last time we're all officially gathered in one place." "Why are you stepping down?" Hubert asks with a frown. "Because I can do more good elsewhere. There's an opportunity for a joint research project with Laurelorn, and whatever the actual results of the research end up being, normalizing relationships with Laurelorn could defuse a lot of tension back home. I won't be disappearing from Karak Eight Peaks entirely, though - my home and my friends and several of my ongoing projects are still here. Johann and Max will be joining me in Laurelorn, and I know Panoramia is continuing on with the Halflings, but I'd like to know where our Journeymanlings see themselves in the years to come." "With the Winter Wolves," Hubert says immediately. "If King Belegar decides he no longer requires my services as an envoy, then I'll join their ranks proper." "Are you giving any thought to promotion?" you ask gently. "No," is his only response. You nod. "Very well. Gretel?" "The Besiegers will be active around here for the foreseeable future," she says. "There's always work protecting caravans, and Barak Varr has us on retainer for some ideas they have in the Border Princes. And I've heard rumours of Nehekharan tombs in the area, if I do manage to track them down then a study of them would be of great interest to the Order." "You be careful with them. They tend to be touchy about their treasures." She nods. "Of course." "Adela?" "The Order is always interested in building good relationships with components of the Empire's military, so they're giving me a stipend to continue my work with the Gunnery School here." "I can see why having a resident Bright Wizard might be useful for an organization dedicated to the creative application of explosions." You look around the circle of Wizards. "I'm glad you'll all be sticking around. My door will always be open to any of you." --- "I have investigated further the stone-folk you live amongst," Cython says conversationally, delicately lowering a tome onto a nearby pile. "Oh?" you ask, looking up from your own pile. You do a lot of reading and you're always looking for ways to do so while also accomplishing something else, and building a rapport with the Karak's largest and most dangerous neighbour is as good a cause as any. That is why you had a room built into your penthouse that was conveniently accessible and large enough to be comfortable for it, and regularly transfer sections of your library on the topics it expresses an interest over to that room. "They remind me in some ways of my tamed, Windless cousins, hidden away underground and pining for their long-gone glory days as they are slowly eroded by the nature of the world. But they do not deny themselves the embrace of the Winds out of overweening pride, but because their essence completely precludes doing so. And even then they have done as much as they possibly can to harness the Winds with their Runes. I find myself admiring their endurance and artifice, and wondering if I would be capable of such if the Winds were denied to me, or if I would merely slumber away the millennia underground until oblivion claimed me." Cython shakes its head. "I had wondered why someone who had attuned themselves so adequately to a Wind would choose to spend their years in the service of such creatures. I shall do so no longer." You smile up at it. "I'm glad you've reconsidered them. They can be very reliable neighbours." "That also explains why they did not fit the model of the Elves. They rebelled against their Gods, and fashioned those that led the rebellion into their new pantheon. Investigating those beings directly might lead to useful insight on the nature of the Divine, but I doubt they would welcome such direct study, and in any case they present an entirely different riddle to the one that occupies me." "What leads you to the conclusion that they rebelled against their gods, rather than not having any in the first place?" It cocks its head. "An interesting point," it says after a while. "It could be that... no, there are the splinter faction in the east. Unless... where did they find their God?" "They don't exactly proselytise about Him, but what little we know is that they encountered Hashut at Uzkulak, when they were trying to shelter from the Coming of Chaos in insufficiently-deep tunnels." "So did He go to them, or did they go to Him? Either way..." It hums a low, reverberating tone. "I will have to investigate further, but my impression has been that the Dwarves are rather religiously monolithic. Only one major schism in a long history, and the schismatics have been equally tightly bound to their new patron. That suggests that some property of the Dwarves prevents them from being either attracted or attractive to most, but not all, Gods. Even those that had the attention of the Lord of Excess took a remarkable amount of effort to subdue. You theorized that their imitation of their holy warriors was to make a mockery of them, but I wonder if that was required to make any progress at all with them. Either as trickery, or as imitation." "You've read my papers?" It nods. "I greatly enjoyed the one about the inability of the Shartak to adapt to Azyr." "So maybe... what, Dwarves are just as incompatible with the Divine as they are with the Arcane? Which makes them more difficult to convert?" "More difficult, or less beneficial, or both. But that raises a question in itself." "What makes Hashut different?" "Precisely. The Ancestor Gods are easy - they started as Dwarves, and ascended. Or perhaps descended. Did Hashut? Or is there some other mechanism at play?" It hums again, lowering its head to run an eye over the titles of the stacked books. "Are there any other species with their own unshared pantheons?" "Well, yes. The Halflings." It turns its eye to give you a searching look. "Like humans, but shorter. You must have seen them, they're inhabiting the Eastern Valley, among the farmlands." "I had simply assumed you used your young to tend the fields. They are a distinct species?" You nod. "Where did they come from?" "We don't know, they've been living among us for as far back as written history goes. They came west with the tribes that eventually formed the Empire." "And their Gods? Do they conform to the usual archetypes?" "I'm not all that familiar with them, I'll have to borrow some research materials for you. But I do know that their main Goddess, Esmerelda, is the Goddess of Food and Hearth, which seems more similar to Valaya than Rhya or Isha - especially since they have a separate, masculine God of Farming, Josias." "Are they notably resistant to magic?" You frown in thought. "Perhaps. They produce Wizards only very rarely, and I remember hearing rumours as a child that they're resistant to mutation, though it was framed as being because they're already mutants." You think further. "There's Ogres, too. I've only read about them, but they supposedly only rarely serve Chaos, and most of them instead worship some sort of God of Eating called the Great Maw. I've got some books on their society, mostly from when the Dwarves were expanding into the mountains they inhabit." "There is a greater variety of species here than in the west," it notes. "Simple geography, perhaps? Less formidable natural barriers to stop the spread of species. Dwarves are from the south and Ogres from the east, after all." "Perhaps," it says thoughtfully. --- Library Purchases Budget: 600gc for this turn. Anything not spent will not accumulate. [ ] [LIBRARY] No purchase. [ ] [LIBRARY] Write-in. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a twelve hour moratorium, because it's been a while since the last update and a while since the last purchase vote. - Though Mathilde is leaving the role of Loremaster, the Great Library will play a similar role in future turns, so this shouldn't be seen as a 'last chance' to acquire books on someone else's dime. You get twice as much because there was no purchase round for Turn 33. - Mathilde will be able to borrow enough books on and from Halflings through Panoramia to satisfy Cython's curiosity, and will do so automatically.

Turn 35 - 2487 - Laurelorn

Spoiler: Voting results Vote tally BOOKS: [*] The Eonir of Laurelorn: Esoteric Dwarven (150 gc), Beastmen: Extensive Imperial, Extensive and Antiquarian Dwarven (300 gc), Waystones and Henges: Esoteric Imperial (150 gc and 4 CF) DWARF: [*] No purchase. COLLEGE: [*] No purchase. PURCHASE: [*] No purchase. Your earlier foray into Laurelorn had begun at Salzenmund and had taken you to the destroyed Nordland village of Oldenlitz. You're certain that was not simply a matter of the most convenient meeting place for the Vicereine, but instead a specific impression that she wished to convey. You suspect today's route to be no different, as you're directed to a specific milestone in the Schadensumpf that, according to the records you checked in Middenheim while you were passing through, is the nearest point on the road to the site of the battle where Middenland fought alongside Laurelorn against the Beastmen. You've decided to take it as a hopeful sign, as the Elves could just as easily have directed you towards the nearby village of Vorbegwerk which has been abandoned by the Graf's decree and is quickly being reclaimed by the swamp that once sustained it. That would have set a very different tone for this meeting. As you ride your Shadowsteed west along the Great Northern Road, you wonder if there might be another layer to the message. The Great Northern Road is no man-made road, as the Empire would have built a road around the swamp instead of right down the middle of it. This road is part of the Old Dwarf Road, built by the Dwarves to link Karaz-a-Karak to Marienburg, then the Elven port of Sith Rionnasc, when the two were allied, and passing through Talabheim - then Athel Maraya - and by Laurelorn on the way. So the spot you are to meet a representative of Laurelorn to be guided into their realm could be interpreted as a place where Elves and man, and Elves and Dwarves, have worked together in the past. Or it could just be a convenient place that you could be expected to be able to find from human direction. The problem with a mind honed to find hidden meanings is that it's still able to find them when there are none to be found. In any case, the Schadensumpf is a wetland like any other, which is to say, it's very different from every other wetland to a suitably trained eye. You know just enough to suspect it to be more of a fen or a mire, and are very glad to be a Wizard as your Shadowsteed keeps your boots out of the mud and your Aethyric Armour confounds the swarm of midges, mosquitoes, and blackflies that attempt to feed upon you as you pass. This must have been a miserable place for the Army of Middenland to march through, and then doubly so when the Graf directed them northwards to engage the Warherd that Laurelorn had hounded south. But march they did, and won a strange new ally for their home in the process. You pull up to the proper milestone and run your eyes over the swamp, and see nothing but murky water and vegetation in all directions. Just as you were wondering if you might be early or late, "galri hadri," comes a voice from nowhere, and a leanly-muscled Elf steps out of a clump of shrubs that you could have sworn were too low to conceal anyone. He wears a tunic of what looks like wooden scales, and despite his bare limbs none of the resident insects seem to notice him. "You would be the Weaver-Wizard?" Well, it's not the worst mangling of your name an Elf has committed. "Lady Magister Mathilde Weber, of the Grey Order and on behalf of Karak Eight Peaks." "Vicarius Galenstra of House Fanpatar, Prince of the Rain. Welcome to my realm." He speaks Eltharin in a thick accent - or perhaps more accurately, he speaks a different dialect of it than the one you were taught. "It is my duty to escort you as far as the Rainbow Falls." "Your duty," you echo curiously. "Is it a duty you welcome?" He seems to consider that. "I have had more than my fill of humans coming to slaughter my birds and dredge my waters in search of peat and iron," he finally says, "but I have recently learned there are other kinds of human. So I will give you a chance to demonstrate your nature." He runs his eyes over you, and he cannot conceal his surprise as his gaze meets your Shadowsteed. After a moment he tears his gaze away and goes still as he focuses, and over a few seconds he draws in and shapes Ulgu into a textbook-perfect example of Shadowsteed, bearing none of the tweaks, shortcuts, adaptations or personalizations that every human Wizard develops. He mounts his conjured horse with practiced ease. "Do not veer far from my side unless you're confident in your ability to swim." You fall in beside him, and as you do you are surprised to see that upon his back, as well as the expected bow and quiver is a firearm, and what looks to be a well-made one at that. "Is that a handgun?" you ask, having to use the Reikspiel word as if Eltharin has an equivalent, you don't know it. He looks at you in confusion, and you nod to his back. "Ah, this," he says, drawing it. "Handgun. A gift from your Graf, and so very entertaining. So much more energy imparted than a normal arrow, and for so much cheaper than the special arrows! Noisy, yes, and so slow to prepare a second shot, but that just means the first must be made to count." He sights down it at a clump of reeds. "Some might decry its lack of accuracy, but if you can't get close enough to take a shot, you don't deserve to." "Not all examples are quite as limited," you say, waiting for him to look towards you for you to slowly draw a revolver, making sure to keep it pointing in the opposite direction to him. "Is that a, what was it, a von Meinkopt? I've heard of those, but they're supposedly even less accurate and reliable than the handguns." "No, though it works on a similar principle. This is a Dwarven-made revolver, with eight chambers that can be loaded in advance, and it has a mechanism to rotate them in line with the barrel. They also have guns that are more accurate than most human-made ones." He shakes his head. "Dwarves. It still sounds strange to be talking of them in the here and now, instead of as figures from ancient history. But you're not the first human to speak highly of their craft. If all goes well, perhaps we might begin to import some of their works." You let him finish admiring the revolver before you reholster it, and he turns his attention back to the road - or the lack of one, anyway. The path leads you from hummock to mound to knoll and in between takes you through completely opaque waters that give no indication of their depth. "This is about the outskirts of the battleground," he says. "We'll skirt around it, as many of the fallen beasts could not be properly disposed of, and may not rest easily. An easy problem to solve if they haul themselves up and start wandering, not so much if they grab you from below." "Just the beasts?" you ask curiously. "I suppose humans, too. One of your Morai-Heg priests said a prayer over the site. But none of ours remain here, except those that wished to become one with the swamp when they passed. Every one of our people that ventures beyond their home carries a wayshard to find their way, and so they can be found if they fall." "What is a wayshard?" you ask, trying not to sound too interested. "Like a lodestone for Waystones, and just as useful for navigating," he says distractedly, looking at the horizon. "There," he says. "That hillock, with the spear jutting out?" You follow his gaze and nod. "That is where Vicarius Lindialoc fell. He was the Warden of Frost, and the last Prince of Frost. As his uncle and son fell in that same battle, House Elwyn went extinct. If it weren't for that, you wouldn't be here at all." "House Elwyn had that much influence?" you prompt. "They once ruled Kor Immarmor, and have ruled the Ward of Frost since it was destroyed by the Dwarves. They were some of the loudest voices against contact with outsiders, and had two votes on the High Council - one for Vicarius, one for being a Major House. For centuries the vote had been fifteen to ten against, or sixteen to nine when the Stormwitch was Triumvir. And his family were influential amongst those that especially venerate Asuryan, so were able to keep the Champion Triumvirs swayed. But now, with House Elwyn extinct, your Graf proving himself to me, House Ellemakil being swayed by the Queen, and a Forestborn Warden of Frost in favour of contact, the politics have shifted. Thirteen to eleven for when the Warden of the Sun is Triumvir, twelve to twelve the rest of the time, and the Vicarius Triumvir is one of the Vicarii in favour of contact and the Champion no longer has House Elwyn's whispers in their ear, so the Triumvirate rules in favour of contact." You understood maybe half of that, but nod while committing the rest to memory for later examination. For the rest of the ride through the swamp you let the conversation linger on hunting and firearms, a set of topics of great interest to Prince Galenstra and which may reinforce his new outlook in favour of outsiders. --- Eventually the mire gives way to swamp proper which gives way to the aptly-named Misty Hills, and visibility plunges to almost nothing, though your guide still takes the opportunity to point in the direction that apparently the Pass of Stone lies in, the ruined tower that serves as the closest thing to a capital the Ward of Rain has. Eventually you emerge from that mist and find yourself at the edge of a wide, tree-ringed lake. "The Tarn of Tears," Prince Galenstra says. "The source of what you call the Schaukel, and also of much of Laurelorn's magic." "A source of magic? How?" You focus on the water, and eventually you can make out a deep throb of magical energy far below, and a steady plume spiralling upwards to swirl through the waters of the lake and be drawn north to the outflow. Everything you've been taught says that all magic has its origin in the Aethyr. "We don't know," he admits. "We believe there's some kind of portal at the bottom, but it has a guardian spirit that doesn't like us investigating." He guides you around the lake to the outflow, and the crashing of flowing water in the distance starts to make itself known. "The Rainbow Falls are ahead," he says, raising his voice, "and they are loud enough to deafen those that spend too much time there. That is where the magic of the Tarn's waters are unleashed into the air, and that, I'm told, is what makes Laurelorn the place that it is. That is where I will pass you on to your next escort, the Queen's Champion, Kadoh. He is..." He hesitates. "Skilled in many things," he eventually says. Before much longer the noise becomes far too much to talk, and the path emerges at the top of a cliff. The view before you is an endless canopy of lush green treetops broken only by the silvery line of the Schaukel running through it, but to your right is an even more breathtaking one as the waters of the Tarn of Tears spill over the the edge into the Rainbow Falls. You'd expected one long, elegant fall with the Winds drifting out of it, but instead of a sheer drop the cliff underneath the Falls is a long, broken slope with hundreds of rocky pools and thousands of individual falls. Throughout it all countless spars of jutting black rock emerge from the spray, each of them aglow with a different Wind, and every few seconds one of them discharges into the air in a scintillating spray of magical energy. Standing next to it and staring out at the trees is what you take to be the Champion, the largest, most muscular Elf you've ever seen, wearing a purple tunic and golden bracers and greaves. A short and unsuccessful attempt at a conversation later, where Prince Galenstra tried to communicate through mime and Kadoh tried to shout over the waterfall, you break the impasse by continuing down the path until the Champion catches on and joins you. At first you slowed your Shadowsteed to a walk, but then you had to urge it back up to a trot as the swift jog Kadoh used to catch up to you continues on after he reaches your side. "You are the Mage?" Kadoh eventually asks in a deep voice once the sound of the Falls has receded, not sounding at all out of breath despite his pace. "Yes, of Ulgu." He looks sideways at you without slowing. "You're large for a Mage," he says eventually. "Is that a human thing?" You almost say yes, before you remember he's comparing you to Elves, not to Dwarves, so he probably means your physique instead of your height. "I am also a warrior." He looks at you again. "Of the fists?" he asks curiously. "Of the sword." He's looking at you again, and to pre-empt his question you summon Branulhune into your hand. "Oh, you're a Loremaster," he says, nodding to himself. You open your mouth to correct him, then consider trying to explain that while you are a Loremaster in the Dwarven sense, you're not quite in the Sapherian sense, while not sure if the meaning of the term has changed in Laurelorn's long isolation, and eventually decide against it. "Yes, I suppose I am," you instead say as you dismiss Branulhune again. "I didn't know humans had Loremasters. There was a human Chamon Mage at the battle in the Ward of Rain, just had a staff. Good with the metal, though." He gestures demonstrably and a few slivers of silver shoot out of his outstretched hand, peppering the path ahead. "Most of our metal-Mages are smiths, not fighters." "There are two metal-Mages I work with that will be joining me here, and both are also fighters. One archer, one with fists." "A fist metal-Mage?" He considers that for a while. "That must be interesting. I would like to meet them." "I'll introduce you," you say, and he nods. As the leagues pass you build an impression of the apparently indefatigable Kadoh as the discussion wanders over varying forms of magic and combat, all of which he seems to be at least passingly familiar with, and always veers away from politics. If this is typical for the Queen's Champion, you're starting to see how even someone so theoretically powerful could become a piece, rather than a player, of the political game. "How did you become Champion?" you eventually ask as your curiosity mounts. "The normal way," he responds, seeming confused. "What is the normal way?" "The festival of games in honour of Asuryan, every four years. Feats of vigour and skill and strength. I win them." That reinforces your impression. The sort of skillset that leads one to winning a festival tournament is not the same that leads to one being a political mastermind. Is that deliberate, to create malleable Triumvirs? Or just a side-effect of a symbol of devotion to Asuryan? "And who is the Triumvirate?" "Me, the Queen, and this year the Warden of the Sun, Lady Delynna." You put that together with what Prince Galenstra said. So, the High Council is the legislative body, and it has twenty-four members: twenty-one Major Houses, plus the three Wardens - the Vicarii, some of whom are also Princes for reasons you're not yet sure of - that aren't part of the Triumvirate that year. The Triumvirate is the Queen, the Champion, and one of the Vicarii, and of them the Queen is the only permanent member. And it sounds like the Triumvirate acts as tiebreaker for the High Council. "It must be a lot of work." "Anything worth doing always is," he replies. --- You're not much of a woodswoman, so it takes a while for you to notice how the forest changes as you approach the center of Laurelorn, as the wild undergrowth gives way to short, soft grass, the bark of the trees around you becomes healthier and smoother, and the animals grow bolder and stare curiously at you as you pass instead of fleeing. Even then it takes you a while to look up, and if you were sitting on a conventional horse you might have fallen off it at the sight of criss-crossing rope-bridges high above. Without noticing you've crossed into the area surrounding Tor Lithanel, the home of the Faniour 'Forestborn' citizens - those descended from refugees that sought shelter in Laurelorn during the War of the Beard, and as such forbidden by ancient decree from living within the walls of the city of Tor Lithanel. You catch glimpses of its residents high above, some crossing the bridges as they go about their business and some walking or sitting on naked branches, as at home in the treetops as you would be in the streets of Altdorf. The forest eventually comes to an abrupt halt and gives way to a wide open meadow of short grass surrounding the banks of the Schaukel, and on the other side stands the walls of Tor Lithanel, pure-white marble stretching far above even the tallest trees with slender, graceful buttresses and arches adding texture to what would otherwise be a forbidding blank expanse of stone. An open drawbridge stretches across the Schaukel towards you, and you have to nudge your Shadowsteed to catch back up to Kadoh as it had responded to your unspoken desire to take in the sight by slowing. And as you pass through the shockingly long tunnel from one end of the wall's base to the other, your breath is taken away once more as you emerge into Tor Lithanel itself. All around you are buildings of pure-white marble that would fade to monotony if it weren't for artistic arrangements of living vines dotted with fruits and berries, and in what must be deliberate mimicry of the vines are inlaid veins of silver and gold with 'fruits' of large and shimmering jewels. But instead of the towering structures you expected every building ends after a uniform two stories, and the reason for that is quickly apparent, as every street is split in two by a line of trees basking in the sunlight, each heavy with fruits and nuts of every variety you've ever seen and many you don't recognize. You follow Kadoh through the streets in something of a daze, taking in the sights. The streets are much less crowded than those of human cities, though more than Dwarven Karaks, and instead of the leather, leaves and barks of those outside the walls, those inside are dressed in silks and jewels, and many gawk at you just as hard as you're tempted to gawk back at them. Above you the sky is broken by three towers, the only things that break the otherwise even skyline: one of silver, one of obsidian, and one of marble. Every building seems dotted with doorways or openings for small shops or what seem to be taverns, and it seems like you're never out of line of sight from somewhere to get food or drink, even if the trees weren't offering an endless bounty. At last Kadoh leads you off the street and towards a double door inset in an archway, and your wonder takes a hit as you notice the silver script inset in them: House Elwyn. The home, you presume, of the now-extinct House that once sought to block any accommodation with humanity. Kadoh pushes open the doors, which seem to glide open with the faintest touch, and inside you see a vast expanse of emptiness: an entrance hall that has been stripped clean, with even the fixtures removed from the walls, the only remaining illumination being a fire burning in a massive fireplace that, judging by the single log of barely-singed wood at the heart of the massive conflagration and the shimmering of Aqshy within it, will be burning for quite some time. Standing by it is a slender but towering figure, wearing a breastplate of what must be ithilmar and a crown to match, inlaid with designs of leaves and vines and dotted with sparkling jewels. Her hair is shoulder-length shimmering gold that contrasts pleasingly with the silver of the armour it rests upon, and as she turns towards you, you note that she has a slender face with eyes of faint blue. "Dear Kadoh," she says in a soft, musical voice, unleashing the faintest hint of a smile towards her Champion. "My Queen," he says, bowing deeply. "And the clever disciple of my very clever cousin," she says, turning her gaze to you. "I have heard good things from several quarters, some of them not prone to agreement with the others. That you fought and bled for two very old families and laid rest to very old shames. And those that listen to the Waystones say that when you reclaimed the last of the peaks for the line of Angrund, they awoke and rejoined a network that had only shrunk since the time when Laurelorn was the Eleventh Kingdom of Ulthuan." This is the moment you had been bracing yourself for. For all that cooperation and harmony was spoken of, this relationship was going to be a game of bluff and deception, with ancient secrets for chips and closely-guarded techniques for cards. Each side would be determined to glimpse as many cards and take as many chips as they could while giving away as little as possible. You had managed to win a seat at this table for the Empire, and there was one thing you needed to avoid admitting at all costs: that you have no chips and no cards. You're sure that somewhere, Ranald is grinning. "I have had the honour of burnishing the legacies of the Van Hals and the Angrunds," you say, "and it would likewise be my honour to do the same for the line of Aenarion, and in doing so repay, in some small part, the founder of the Colleges of Magic." She approaches slowly, her gaze lowering as she closes the distance. She must have at least a foot and a half on you, maybe more. "Eight Orders," she says thoughtfully, her gaze flicking to the ground behind you. "Ulthuan speaks so easily of the corruptibility of humanity, but my cousin saw through that to the truth of the matter: you were not meant to stand unbowed by the Winds like the Dwarves, nor were you meant to bend to them and then straighten unchanged like the Elves. You were meant to embrace one Wind, and in doing so take flight." She reaches out towards you and a wisp of spray from Rainbow Falls answers the gesture, abandoning the pull of Ulgu to entwine around her finger. "Ulgu. Legend has it that it was the first Wind that Hoeth mastered, as His confusion at the Winds drew it to Him. A good omen." She smiles briefly, a flash of genuine amusement that disappears in a heartbeat. "I have had a scribe collate the information you will need to set down roots. We will be watching with great interest." With that she leaves, Kadoh trailing in her wake like an adoring puppy. It's not hard to find the promised notes, as they sit upon the mantelpiece in an otherwise empty room. You sit cross-legged in front of the fireplace and begin to read. Near the top is a helpfully-labelled map of Tor Lithanel, including nearby shops for things like food and furniture and, you note with a suddenly dry mouth, books. It explains that with the extinction of House Elwyn, this 'Major House' - apparently referring to the actual structure - has reverted to the crown's control, though the vote it held does not. Also noted are the major powers of Laurelorn that would be most relevant to your project, with carefully polite and long-winded descriptions that you mentally distil into the salient details and winnow into the most promising possible partners. Major House Thyriolan: Originally from Saphery, and one of the two Major Houses influential in the Temple of Hoeth. They were and presumably still are against involvement with human affairs, but do agree that the waning Waystone network is a major concern for Laurelorn. Major House Ecthelion: Originally from Saphery, and one of the two Major Houses influential in the Temple of Hoeth. They're less stringently against involvement with the Empire than House Thyriolan, but unlike House Thyriolan they do look down upon humanity. Major House Tindomiel: Originally from Saphery, and one of the two Major Houses influential in the Temple of... Hekarti? Isn't she a Druchii Goddess? Well, they did vote in favour of interaction with the Empire so they might be a better option for a magically-inclined Major House to bring into the project than the two Hoethian ones. Major House Fanpatar: The House of Prince Galenstra, a formerly Yvressian House that dominates the worship of Ladrielle. Less scholarly than the previous houses, perhaps, but the Prince did seem open to the idea, practically-minded, and curious about human and Dwarven inventions. Major House Ellemakil: A formerly Avelornian House, and one that has recently come to dominate the fledgling Temple of Ulric. Presumably they are the House most enthusiastic about cooperating with humans. Major House Malforric: With the extinction of House Elwyn, House Malforric now dominates the worship of Asuryan. They are also the Warden of the Sun. This makes them second only to the Queen in power, which would make them very useful to get on your side. However, they are possibly the most isolationist Major House in the entire city. The Ward of Storm: The lands of western Laurelorn, touching Middenland on one end and the ocean on the other. Until the extinction of House Elwyn, it was the only Ward ruled by Forestborn instead of a Major House. The current Warden is Kaia, known as the 'Stormwitch', who advocates peaceful relations with the Empire... and also with the Druchii and the Norscans. Huh. The Ward of Frost: The lands of eastern Laurelorn, which until recently contained most of the lands encroached on by Nordland. In the aftermath of the death of House Elwyn, the Ward has passed into the control of a council of Forestborn and, hmm, 'forest beings', with the Warden position rotating to whoever is available at the time. This is the bloc that Vicereine Cadaeth is a part of. The Grey Lords: Oddly, none of the materials mention the legendary Grey Lords, the researchers and exiles that interceded during the War of the Beard to vanish a Dwarven Throng that destroyed Kor Immarmor and threatened to do the same to Tor Lithanel. You should probably start asking questions about that at some point. --- You have five actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. For every two AP spent across all members of WEB-MAT, including recruiting new members, you can spend one 'free' additional AP with any member of WEB-MAT. Current overwork status: [ ] [-] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. WEB-MAT: Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Write a paper: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which. Must be taken with a 'dictate' action. [ ] MAX: Go through every library of the Colleges you can access for any scrap of information about Waystones. (NEW) WEB-MAT: Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Have Johann spend time getting to know Kadoh, who has expressed an interest in meeting the 'fist metal-Mage'. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, Light Wizard (NEW) [ ] EGRIMM: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] EGRIMM: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] EGRIMM: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Recruitment [ ] WEB-MAT: Attempt to recruit someone to WEB-MAT (specify who) The Waystone Project, Recruitment [ ] Attempt to bring an Order into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a non-Order magical tradition into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a human Cult into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Start asking questions about the Grey Lords The Waystone Project, Research [ ] Personally scrutinize a Waystone as thoroughly as you possibly can [ ] Lay the foundations: work with the current members of WEB-MAT and the Waystone Project to build a single unified framework for understanding the Waystones In theory, the more members there currently are, the more complete this framework will be. Will unlock further investigations. Can be repeated if desired, but will not unlock anything new after the first time, it will just make a new framework incorporating any new recruits. Lovely Laurelorn [ ] Furnish the living spaces of the Waystone Project HQ (specify how much: 100gc for adequate, 200gc for comfortable, 300gc+ for nice (no cap on how much can be spent, because Elves)) [ ] Furnish the research spaces of the Waystone Project HQ (specify how much: 100gc for adequate, 500gc for College-grade, 2000gc for Laurelorn-grade) [ ] Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel [ ] Immerse yourself in the culture of the 'Cityborn' Toriour inhabitants of Tor Lithanel [ ] Immerse yourself in the culture of the 'Forestborn' Faniour inhabitants of the woods surrounding Tor Lithanel [ ] Explore one of the Wards of Laurelorn (specify which: Storm, Rain, Frost) Self-Improvement: [ ] Ask an acquaintance to train you in a skill: specify who and what. [ ] Hire a trainer to come to Eight Peaks and teach you: specify what. (costs favours College trainers, money for human ones, Dwarf trainers are free) [ ] Travel to the Grey College and attend lessons there. (1 College Favour per class; 100gc can be paid instead for non-magical classes) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Attempt to gain control of one of your Arcane Marks (specify which) [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [ ] Have one of Prince Gotri's pilots teach you to fly a Gyrocarriage. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] Dictate papers: select which two, must be taken with Max's 'receive dictation'. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. Aethyric Vitae (15 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item with a Fiendishly Complex or easier spell (specify what and which) [ ] Attempt to enchant an object to translate Windsight into a visual image. [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to codify Rite of Way so that others can learn it [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff from mundane materials (specify for whom) [ ] Turn a staff from the horn of a Storm Dragon (specify for whom) Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in the Sylvanian campaign (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Marienburg affair (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Black Waters project (specify how) Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting or ingratiating yourself with someone else: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 175 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Expansion along the Aver EIC Handler: The Hochlander The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in your fief. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Julia to find out if she's interested in being poached or passing on information. [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Improve and expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (optional: specify how) [ ] EIC: Have a blackpowder factory built in Wurtbad. [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Books and rubbings from an Asur explorer of Lustria and the Southlands Golden Arm Ghyran Nut Kurgan Shrine to Mannsleib Kurgan enchanted weapons Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghur (FRESH) Windsoak Mushrooms - Hysh (FRESH) Observations on the Windfall north of the Dark Lands (FADING) Observations on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes (FADING) Observations of Karag Dum and its unusual guardian (FADING) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ulgu (FADING) Windsoak Mushrooms - Aqshy(FADING) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghyran (FADING) Windsoak Mushrooms - Azyr (FADING) Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (FADING) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition. (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual. (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae. (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. Windsoak Mushrooms (missing: Chamon, Shyish) The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a twenty-four hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - As you might notice, the action section has been redone. If there's anything I've missed or that is ambiguous, please let me know. - Thank you for your patience in waiting for this chapter. I didn't suspect going into it how much behind-the-scenes work it would take just to get Mathilde into the city. - A lot of the names, people, and references being thrown around will be as unknown to the reader as they are to Mathilde, even to the reader that knows the setting. This is expected and intended. Laurelorn has very little canon material, and I've had to fill in a lot of the gaps. - Some of the names might not be unknown to people familiar with the Silmarillion. I just looted Quenya for Elfy-sounding names without lining up the personality of the Houses with their Silmarillion counterparts, you won't get any metagaming advantage by being suspicious about House Noldor or whatever.

Turn 35 Results - 2487 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results Vote tally [*] Plan WEB-MAT & Culture -[*] JOHANN: Have Johann spend time getting to know Kadoh, who has expressed an interest in meeting the 'fist metal-Mage'. -[*] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: Golden Arm -[*] MAX: Go through every library of the Colleges you can access for any scrap of information about Waystones. -[*] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (Karak Azul) --[*] COIN: The Gambler -[*] Furnish the living spaces of the Waystone Project HQ (600gc) -[*] Immerse yourself in the culture of the 'Cityborn' Toriour inhabitants of Tor Lithanel -[*] Immerse yourself in the culture of the 'Forestborn' Faniour inhabitants of the woods surrounding Tor Lithanel -[*] EIC: Have a blackpowder factory built in Wurtbad. -[*] SERENITY: Observations of Karag Dum and its unusual guardian You'd met Lady Magister Stanisława Skłodowicz, the High Wizard of Middenheim, once before, but that was a brief meeting while you passed through her domain for a meeting with the Ar-Ulric. As Middenheim is the obvious waystation for personnel and materials that the nascent project may require, and the Wizards and Alchemists Guild the obvious middle-man for handling it, you organize a lengthier meeting with her to take place before the arrival of your first three fellows. "Mmm," she says distractedly, her eyes never straying far from a softly simmering alembic. "Well, I won't pretend I'll be put out by all this. Ulrican hosts can be prickly, and you working with their new friends is going to make that easier. Just Wizards, is it?" "At first, but I'm hoping to bring in non-Wizard contributors. Dwarves, and possibly Priests." "I'll have someone sort something out elsewhere, then. This is primarily a laboratory, and they might not be used to things like the occasional explosion. But Wizards would be used to that sort of thing. Anyone I'd know?" "From your Order, Magisters Johann and Maximilian de Gaynesford." "Gehenna's boy?" You nod. "A bit of a pity project, or so we thought, but he turned out well. Don't think I know the other one. Recent graduate?" "Yes, and he's been working with me in Eight Peaks right from the start, back when he was a Journeyman." She nods, but offers no further comment. "The third is Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, of the Light Order." She looks directly at you for the first time in the conversation. "The Light Order is taking an interest?" "Just Egrimm," you correct. She gives you a long, searching look. As focused as she is on her own research, one doesn't become a Lady Magister or the High Wizard of Middenheim by being ignorant of politics. But in the end she doesn't ask any of the questions she might have. "Just Egrimm, then," she says. "Very well. I'll have someone prepare rooms for their arrival, and I'll have word sent when they arrive. The Graf has birds that can carry messages to their city." --- A few days later you meet the trio of incoming Wizards at Middenheim. "Magisters," you say in greeting as they enter the meeting room you'd borrowed for the purpose from the Guild. "Lady Magister," Johann says, carrying the crate you'd asked him to bring from Karak Eight Peaks. "Where do you want this?" "Just on the table will be fine," you say with a wave, resisting the desire to smile at Egrimm's searching look. He'd been waiting impatiently in the Guild's lobby ever since he arrived in Middenheim, so for him to be told he had a meeting inside it by one of the Guild's Perpetuals without ever seeing you enter must have given him a start. "Good trip?" "Long, loud, and cold," Maximilian says. "Same as always, then. Still better than walking. How about you, Egrimm?" "A boat to Grimminhagen, and a coach the rest of the way. Pleasant enough. But I'm still not sure why I'm here." "Mira didn't mention?" "If that woman says jump, I don't ask questions, I jump. Especially considering..." He looks sideways at Johann and Maximilian. "Well. Considering." "Very well. We're here to work with the Eonir." He frowns. "The Orders are getting involved in the Nordland mess?" "Not directly. A joint research project into the Waystones, as they've been led to believe that Karak Eight Peaks has insight into them that they lack. And as the former Loremaster of Karak Eight Peaks, I was the natural fulcrum for a cooperative effort. And to bring the Empire to the table formally I've formed a branch college - the World's Edge Branch for the Multidisciplinary Advancement of Thaumaturgy." "Led to believe," Egrimm echoes. "Yes, that's the rub. In truth, we don't. Everything that I know about Waystones came from Teclis, and everything Karak Eight Peaks knew died with their Runesmiths Guild in 513 BIC. So our priority is to look busy and productive while we do everything in our power to change that. As such, Max?" "Yes?" "You won't be joining us in Tor Lithanel just yet. With my authority, go through every College library that will have you for any scrap of information. I doubt anyone left their Big Book of Ancient Secrets in the public section by mistake, but there's sure to be pieces scattered around the place, and you're the man to gather them together." "That's going to be a lot of libraries," he says, a smile spreading across his face. "I won't begrudge you taking advantage of the opportunity while you're at it, but don't forget why you're there. Hopefully there'll be enough to serve as a stopgap until we can find something solid for the Empire's contribution. For the Dwarves-" "What if there is nothing for the Empire's contribution?" Egrimm interrupts. You shake your head firmly. "Our ancestors have been living amongst the Waystones since the first one was erected here. I refuse to believe that in six thousand years, the collective minds of a continent have failed to produce any usable data. Nothing mass-produced on that scale is that inscrutable. The problem isn't whether it exists, it's who's keeping it to themselves." You gesture at the room around you. "This Guild is a thousand years old." You gesture at yourself. "The Hedgefolk advised Sigmar when He was building the Empire." You look to Egrimm. "Your Order built a pyramid in Altdorf, and nobody believes it was just for the aesthetic. We are inheritors of magical traditions that predate Teclis' White Tower. That information is out there, and I'll find who has it and drag them to the table, one way or another." You take a breath. "Speaking of dragging, that's my lot for the coming months - I'm going to try to ensnare Karak Azul's Runesmiths. I've worked with them before, and hopefully they'd have less ancestral baggage about Elves since the closest Elven outpost to them would have been Sartosa." "Sartosa was an Elven outpost?" Johann asks. "I've been digging into their history and, believe me, you won't go far wrong if you assume literally every island was at some point. You, I want making friends. There's an Elf called Kadoh who I think you'd get along with, and he's the second or third most powerful Elf in Tor Lithanel right now." Johann looks doubtful, but doesn't question it. "As for you, Egrimm, that's why I had Johann bring that crate north with him." You nod to Johann. "If you could?" There's a creak of protesting wood as he effortlessly pulls open the nailed-shut lid, revealing the clawed golden arm you'd acquired at Uzkulak within. "What is it?" Egrimm asks, staring transfixed. "Good question. It'll be our job to answer it. The Norscan I acquired it from wasn't very explanative." You were being entirely literal and honest, but it would be easy to take your words as an understated boast about acquiring an unusual combat trophy, and by his expression Egrimm has done just that. As dissatisfied as he was with Alric, it's still rather a step down in prestige to go from the most senior Magister Patriarch of the Orders of Magic to the most junior Lady Magister, so any little thing to shore up your own status in his eyes could be helpful. "There's not a coast in the Great Ocean their vessels haven't reached and he could have got it from someone else, so it could be from anywhere." You nod to Johann, who reseals the box with a splintering crunch. "We've got a rather large building to ourselves in Tor Lithanel, so we'll be able to set up a basic laboratory while we're furnishing the living spaces. Getting there is going to be unpleasant, though. The only path that isn't through Nordland or Marienburg is through the Schadensumpf. Egrimm, do you know how to ride a horse?" "Yes," he says. "Good. A Shadowsteed can get through it if you stick to the path, but you really don't want to be falling off. Johann should be fine, though." "Why?" he asks curiously, turning to Johann, whose golden limbs were completely covered. You smile, imagining a legion of leeches blunting their teeth on his golden skin. "You'll see. But Johann, you might want to wear clothes you won't mind ruining." --- Your first purchase in Tor Lithanel is a bathtub for Johann, but it's far from the last. You plan to have all sorts of visiting contributors over the coming years, and you don't want any of them to be tempted to cut their visit short in favour of the comforts of home. This is your first extended foray into the city of Tor Lithanel, and it's one that proves quite effective, as there's none so helpful and patient as someone who's about to make a substantial sale, whether that someone be human or Elf. And it's through this that you begin your investigation into the people and culture of the 'Toriour' - the Cityborn Eonir. What you quickly discover is that Tor Lithanel is, more than anything, an extremely crowded city, much more so than you had believed to be the case at first glance. For though you do not feel anywhere near as crowded as you do in a typical Altdorf street, the street in question is a great deal wider than the cramped avenues of human settlements, and it's that extra width that misdirected you at first. To be Cityborn, you piece together from answers to artfully offhand questions as you furnish your new dwelling, means exactly that: to have inherited the ancient right to reside within Tor Lithanel. But that right has been inherited by many over the years, and constricted horizontally by the city's walls and vertically by the needs of the plants lining every street for sunlight, living space has become more and more scarce. Those who do not have the fortune to have been born to a Major House - which is much more literal than you expected, as it denotes those families who were granted a large property by the founding charter of Tor Lithanel - find living space at a premium. Few can afford more than space to sleep and store a few items, so most live their waking lives in the streets. Which is, perhaps, not so bad as it first sounds, because such lovely streets they are. In your experience so far, it seems like there is no place on any street in Tor Lithanel where you would be unable to draw line of sight to the Elven equivalent of a tavern, where a single wooden 'coin' roughly equivalent in value to thruppence can buy a lovely meal and a earthenware mug of very agreeable wine, with the price kept low and the quality high by the ubiquity of fruits and nuts free for the taking. Theaters and odeons are plentiful with only the largest charging admission, and in the smaller ones anyone who cares to take the stage is free to do so, so there is a steady stream of entertainment by people who would be considered masters by any shorter-lived race. There are regular festivals in honour to various Gods and the business of governance is all conducted in the Agora in full view of the public. There are public bathhouses and the silk clothing favoured by the populace is hard-wearing enough to only need replacing every few decades, and communal bunkhouses are provided by many of the Major Houses to those who can't or won't rent accommodations of their own. The cost of living in Tor Lithanel can be practically zero, if one has the good fortune to be born Toriour. This second impression Tor Lithanel gives you is a rather favourable one, where the least fortunate is still better off than so many citizens of the Empire. But though the many Elves you talk to speak freely of the floor on quality of life, their words also hint at an equally impenetrable ceiling. Those with ambition can try to better themselves through commerce, but competition is fierce, customers are few, and the rent for even a tiny studio is ruinous. Most that try typically enjoy a modest success off the back of novelty, but when that dries up so too do their funds, and most end up back in the bunkhouses. And off the back of the money from rents and influence from providing beds to those who otherwise would not have them, the Major Houses reinforce an already unassailable position in society. When Maruviel, Handmaiden to and niece of the Everqueen Yvraine, made promises to the families who had enough money and influence to make the colonization of Laurelorn possible, she can't have imagined that millennia later the society that had sprouted from that colony would be strangled by those same promises. So what is an Elf to do, if they yearn for more from a society where so much is monopolized by twenty-one families? Some turn to the Temples to find meaning in the Gods, but those, too, are dominated by the Major Houses. Some seek political power, but the High Council is restricted to the Major Houses, the Senate is strictly advisory, and the only avenue left is to be Champion, which is decided by a series of tests of skill every four years and its exact format is decided by the Temple of Asuryan, which is to say, it is decided by House Malforric. Some immerse themselves in the pursuit of various arts, and verses and tunes and songs of bittersweet yearning fill the air throughout the city. But some do none of these things. Some simply walk away from Tor Lithanel. The unspoken shame of the Toriour is that not all of the Faniour descend from refugees of millennia ago. Many of them are those who threw away the privileges that other Cityborn cling to so tightly and found freedom in the world outside the walls, where food must be hunted or gathered and safety is not guaranteed, but where one can weave a palace out of any unoccupied treetop, and if there are any comforts of the city they still yearn for, they can simply purchase them; all but the right to be within the city walls after dusk. This is where the raw materials for Tor Lithanel comes from, as visiting Faniour sell what they have harvested from the forest and buy them back as finished goods. The mark-up is high, but a Faniour woodsman or hunter or stonecutter has no need to rent a studio, and the few you see walking the streets of Tor Lithanel during the day have a relaxed, almost indulgent air about them that contrasts sharply with the aura of quiet desperation that all but the most successful of those you patronize possess. Beginning an investigation into the Cityborn is as easy as walking out the door, but the Forestborn present some difficulties. Finding their homes is easy enough, but as you stare up at glimpses of a second city among the treetops with nary a ladder or staircase in sight, you realize that the Faniour will present more of a challenge than the Toriour. You were invited inside the walls of Tor Lithanel and thus inside the lives of the Cityborn, but each Forestborn has their own 'walls' provided by the towering height and the smooth bark of the trees they live atop. Eventually you resort to wandering around staring upwards until you find someone looking down at this strange human wandering around below them, and using their befuddled curiosity as a foot in the door. This kind of works, but only to a point. The Cityborn have no choice but to be social, but the Forestborn can and do choose their interactions, and once their curiosity is sated they see no reason not to disappear back into the treetops. It doesn't take long before you to grow frustrated of this approach, and you find a new avenue to investigate when you find yourself drawn into an odeon by a gamine Elf singing longingly of the freedom of the treetops, and over a mug of spiced wine you quiz them on the subject of their song, and they admit sheepishly that they're more longing for one specific person enjoying the freedom of the treetops, namely a member of their 'kithband'. Questioning further, you learn that the Eonir do not have Guilds; the closest that they have is these 'kithbands', loose and voluntary social groups of people who share a vocation, interest, or cause. These relationships can and often do transcend the social classes of Cityborn and Forestborn, and it is through this you find a different way to approach the Forestborn. Just about anyone who dedicates themselves to a creative endeavour is vulnerable to genuine interest in the topic of their work, and you leverage this upon the artists displaying, reciting, or performing work related to the world outside the city walls - of which there are quite a few, as the Forestborn and their lifestyles are exotic, close by, and a little bit taboo. Through this you manage to gain a series of introductions to their Forestborn kith, who are at least cooperative enough to answer a few of your questions before disappearing back into the trees. A handful are as curious about the world inside the walls as their counterparts within are of their own lives, and it's them who prove to be the richest resources, as they're willing to talk at length about the two societies, their interconnections, and the barriers between the two. What you learn is that to many of the Forestborn, the Cityborn Eonir may as well not exist for most purposes. They live their lives in the forest and the only impact the city has on their lives is as a marketplace, and they build their own societies among the treetops as interconnected or as isolated as they please. The two parallel classes exist in their own worlds, each looking down their noses at the other when they notice each other at all. It seems to work well most of the time... but not when conflict intrudes on their domain. When Warherds gather, when Waaaghs form, when Daemons intrude, it is the Forestborn that suffer. When humans encroach on the forest, it is the Forestborn that are squeezed out of their homes and hunting ranges. It seems that all too often the Cityborn must be pestered into action, with the Senate calling for action for months before the High Council finally acknowledges a problem that has been festering for too long... but when they do act, it reminds the Forestborn where power truly lies within Laurelorn, as they emerge from their walled city crackling with magic and glowing with blessings. Ithilmar armour turns blows that punched through armour of leather and bark. Weapons bearing enchantments dating back millennia tear through terrors that ignored the arrows of the Forestborn. Ancient pacts and forgotten legends are called upon, summoning beasts and spirits from the darkest corners of the forest. And then the immediate threat is defeated and the Cityborn return to their precious city, leaving the Forestborn to the day-to-day attrition of the long war for Laurelorn. It's a gripping tale, one that pulls on your heart and makes part of you want to rally against the injustice of it all. But it's a tale that you've heard a hundred times before, one that is always told by the disenfranchised. Sometimes the tale is true, as it so clearly was during the reign of Dieter IV, but you also overheard it in Stirland while it was ruled by Abelhelm, and undoubtedly someone was telling it as he lay dying in a tent in Sylvania. So you take care to remind yourself this is one perspective, not the entire picture. ...or perhaps that's just what you've been trained to think. The Grey Order is very careful to inculcate its Apprentices against populism, but while it's doing so it's also teaching them the skillset that allows them to notice they're being indoctrinated. The result is a lot of second-guessing, which is very appropriate for the pursuit of Ulgu but also rather disquieting to live with. Maybe Queen Marrisith is doing all she can, and for each problem that the Forestborn suffer from there's a dozen she's managed to hold off. Or maybe she acts only when she is directly threatened, and the rest of the time she enjoys a luxurious lifestyle that the Forestborn bleed daily to protect without ever getting to enjoy. The easy conclusion to those extremes is that the truth is somewhere in the middle, but that leads to the more difficult job of determining where, exactly, a given person can be found. Most rulers are neither Magnus nor Dieter, and you've yet to be given enough information to determine where Marrisith lies on that scale. --- Johann and Kadoh seem like they would have a lot in common. Unfortunately, none of those things would be a language. You play with the idea of trying to find an interpreter, but the relationship you're trying to establish here is too important to leave in the hands of an unknown third party, so you end up having to join the two on their adventures. Both of them have pursued a life dedicated to transforming their bodies into an idealized form, they've just taken two very different paths on doing so, and early on their discussions involve the benefits and drawbacks to each approach, usually while bare from the waist up for ease of comparison. You're never fully able to determine whether it would be more awkward for you to look or to not look, but at least the process is making some strides towards better relations between humans and Elves, if the looks from passers-by are anything to judge by. Thankfully the relationship evolves past the two of them flexing at each other and talking about musculature, and your translation only becomes needed when the two of them are planning their day, after which they're able to venture out unescorted to engage in various sports, exercises, and other adventures. Johann starts picking up a smattering of Eltharin from constant exposure, and when he starts coming home smelling faintly of olives instead of sweat you question him and find that a human entering into the public baths was met with no pushback, or at least no pushback that the Queen's Champion couldn't bludgeon his way through. It was a matter you'd given a bit of thought to, but hadn't end up pursuing because of how awkward it would have been, and since you'd become quite used to bathing privately anyway. Johann had previously insisted he had no head for languages, but you suspect he had no head for learning languages in a formal setting, which is rather vindicated by his blooming grasp of the vocabulary without ever picking up a book on the subject for longer than required to look up a word or two. He and Egrimm - who has begun studying the language of his own accord - begin practicing with each other over meals, and eventually you're able to leave him to pursue his new friendship without you there to translate, only checking in every few days to see how it's doing. Between his muscles, forthrightness, and relative lack of book smarts it can be easy to fall into the trap of thinking of him as simple, but you're careful to never let yourself forget that he was concealing his true rank and agenda when you first met. Not in a negative way, of course, merely as an appreciation for a very useful skillset that he happens to possess. And though he seems to be growing genuinely fond of Kadoh, he knows what's at stake and how much influence the Queen's Champion has, and he's in no danger of losing sight of that. [Skill gained: Eonir of Laurelorn: You've lived amongst the Toriour and Faniour of Laurelorn, and learned something of their society. +1 Diplomacy]

The 7010 Council of Kings

In Grungni's name, High King Thorgrim Grudgebearer summons the Kings of the Karaz Ankor to a Council of Kings at Karaz-a-Karak to discuss and decide matters of great import to the realm... King Belegar frowns in thought as he and his brother-kings and sister-queen are led on a long, winding path through the halls of Karaz-a-Karak. He lived his childhood in this mountain, and never before had he stepped foot in these passages. He was quite certain that they, like most of the Karak, had been sealed at some point in the prior generations as the population of the Karak had dwindled. As was so often the case in recent years, Belegar's mind drifts to the question of Karaz-a-Karak. Ever since his ever-reliable Loremaster had uncovered the matter of the siphoned energy, he had wondered what purpose Karaz-a-Karak had been putting it to. Was this part of the answer? Was it somehow needed to reopen sealed portions of the Karak? Was the High King planning to take a page from his own book and start trying to lure in settlers from other Holds? It was hard enough to convince a Clan to uproot themselves to build a new life from scratch already, it would only become more so if Everpeak itself started pursuing the very same goal. Perhaps he should have brought Mathilde along on this, so that her keen senses could have assayed whatever it was the High King was up to in these long-abandoned halls. At last the courtier leads the monarchs through a set of double doors, and despite having travelled throughout the Karaz Ankor and having seen most of the wonders it had to offer, Belegar could not prevent his eyes from growing wide. The hall they entered was larger than his own Clan Hall and every wall was lined with four rows of large and seemingly identical clear jewels. In the middle of the room stood the High King, and Belegar felt his stomach churn. Once he had looked up to the High King, but time and circumstance had revealed to him the true nature of the Dwarf he had once so admired. Thorgrim surveys the array of crowns before him, a veritable mountain range of precious metals studded with the finest of jewels. "I have been your High King for one hundred and eighty-three years," he intones, "and I was chosen to be that King by the Council of Kings of that time for the promises I made, of reclamation and retribution. In doing so I claimed a crown that would otherwise have gone to King Ungrim or to King Belegar's grandfather. To fulfil those promises, the first act I performed with the Dragon Crown atop my brow was to lead the Throng of Karaz-a-Karak against the greenskins of Black Fire Pass alongside the Throng of Karak Hirn, and on that day we struck out several old and bitter Grudges. But Black Fire Pass has significance beyond being a place where the hated enemy dwelled, and beyond the trade that has passed through it ever since. It was the place where High King Kurgan fought alongside a human Chieftain by the name of Sigmar, and in doing so forever entwined the fates of our two peoples. And while there's many a time that Sigmar's heirs have fallen short of the example their ancestor set, I would call a liar any Dawi who would claim that we have not failed the example set by our own forebears. "In the time since the battle in Black Fire Pass, I have spilled much blood to strike out many old Grudges, but never since have I done so much to fulfil the other half of the promise I made. In my focus on thinning the Dammaz Kron I have turned my 'Age of Reckoning' into a Slayer Oath for our entire people. But as I sought a noble doom for the Karaz Ankor, its Kings proved beyond any doubt that the honour of the Dawi still lives. With hope and bravery did Karak Norn, Karak Izor, Karak Hirn, and Barak Varr lend Clan Angrund all the might and materiel they could spare, and Karak Eight Peaks is now reclaimed and redeemed, and Karak Azul reconnected to the rest of the realm. With cunning and ingenuity did Zhufbar and Karak Kadrin devise a way to send an expedition to investigate the fate of fallen Karag Dum, and in doing so found a way to rescue Karak Vlag from the clutches of Chaos. And even as I speak great canals are being dug to link the waters of Zhufbar and Barak Varr with the rivers of the Empire. I sing the death-song for an Empire that has not been so large and interconnected since the Time of Woes. I act as Grimnir striking out alone into the northern wastes, when I should be Grungni leading his people into a golden future! "No more. For the first time in three thousand years, there is a Dwarfhold anchoring four of the five navigable passes through our mountains. If we had all five, we would be in a position to reach agreements with the Umgi nations to guarantee the safety of travellers and vigilance against threats from the east, in exchange for a portion of the wealth that passes through our mountains and promises of mutual support against significant threats. But we cannot yet claim to rule the mountains that our Ancestors left to us. So in the coming years, mercenary forces from Barak Varr will work to secure the western approach to Mad Dog Pass, while Watchtower-Clans who have been living in the Grey Mountains for millennia will re-establish themselves in their ancient homes with every assistance from Karaz-a-Karak. And when sufficient forces have been gathered, I will personally lead an attack to retake Mount Silverspear and return it to the control of Clan Gunnisson. As we all know, it fell to the greenskins during the early centuries of the Time of Woes in what is now known as the Silver Road Wars. What few remember is that part of the reason it was lost is that an ancient wonder from the time of the Ancestor Gods that watched over the Silver Road was blinded by those tumultuous times. "But now..." High King Thorgrim Grudgebearer spreads his arms, and each of the jewels inset on the walls begins to glow. "The Eyes of Grimnir will open once more." With a wave of illumination, an image projects from each one of the thousands of jewels, each showing a different part of a long, rocky road through the mountains. The images change after a few seconds, and then there's a low tone as one becomes framed in red light, and the image grows until it centers on a band of Goblins riding wolves along the road. Another tone sounds, and another image is framed in red, this time warning of a small group of Orcs on a mountainside peering over a rocky barrier at the road below. As more tones sound, the High King's smile grows. "That which is wrong with the world that we cannot fix with the blades of our axes, we shall surely rebuild."

Turn 35 Results - 2487 - Part 2

Spoiler: Unfinished business -[*] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: Golden Arm -[*] MAX: Go through every library of the Colleges you can access for any scrap of information about Waystones. -[*] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (Karak Azul) --[*] COIN: The Gambler -[*] Furnish the living spaces of the Waystone Project HQ (600gc) -[*] EIC: Have a blackpowder factory built in Wurtbad. -[*] SERENITY: Observations of Karag Dum and its unusual guardian "Well," says Egrimm, looking down at the golden arm, "my first thought is the New World. Infamously full of strange golden artefacts, and said to be filled with lizard-men who guard them. If those lizard-men are approximately the size of a man, that would fit." "Are we sure it's gold?" you ask. He considers that. "Good point," he concludes. You summon a Shadowchisel, frown at it, then dismiss it. Better not to introduce unnecessary magic. "Do you have a blade?" He pats his robes. "Ritual or regular?" "Regular, just need to take some scratchings to assay." He frowns as he draws a plain steel dagger from inside his robes and leans over the arm. "It does look pretty battered, so it shouldn't be a problem. If surface damage would discharge the enchantment, it would already have happened." He carefully scratches at part of the arm far from the joints, and then his frown deepens as he puts some force into it. "Must be an alloy," he grunts. "I'm just blunting my knife." "That might imply this has a practical use - a prosthetic rather than an ornament." "That fits with the articulation on the fingers." "You think it's articulation? If so, it's seized tight." You carefully grip one of the clawed 'fingers' to demonstrate. "Maybe fouling, maybe it requires the enchantment to be activated to operate. Though I suppose it could still be ornamental if that's the case. Some sort of poseable statue?" "Or a mobile one. A war-construct, like Nehekharan statues?" You frown. "Are we sure this isn't Nehekharan?" He looks down at the arm in alarm, then relaxes and shakes his head. "No, it would have their runes on it if it was theirs, and would probably be part stone as well. Wouldn't that be a way to endear ourselves to our hosts, bringing a Tomb King's army upon them." He tucks his dagger away. "We need some equipment. A chisel, touchstones. Assaying chemicals, maybe?" "Maximilian should be able to take care of that." "I thought their spells were dangerous to use on things like this?" "No, he can do it normally. He takes an interest in that sort of thing." --- You reconvene several days later with the result of Max's careful assaying of a few chiselled-off slivers: mostly gold, but whatever else is in there isn't identifiable from a few slivers, and testing any more than that would risk endangering the enchantment within. With that initial assumption successfully identified, excised, and tested, you resume the examination of the arm. What you quickly identify with the help of the touchstone is that the entire arm is not made of the same material - the raised circle in the palm is a separate, slightly lighter material, and you find what seems to be the same material in a spiral pattern at the shoulder joint. That fits in with the theory that this had some practical use, and leads you to suspect that whatever the material is, it's magically conductive in some way. With a series of very careful isolation tests, you expose the arm to a spectrum of mono-wind environments to see how it reacts to each, and how each reacts to it. It exhibits a mild repellent effect on every Wind but Hysh, leading you to conclude that the magic stored within must be Hysh. But the exterior Hysh is not outright attracted to or absorbed by the arm, likely because of the insulating effect of the exterior gold alloy, but Egrimm's careful testing with a minute sliver of light on his fingertip confirms that the secondary material is conductive to it. "Prosthetic," Egrimm says confidently as he carefully turns a vice around one clawed finger of the arm. "Not a war-statue. I'm certain of it." "Oh?" you ask curiously. "Have you studied anatomy?" "Some," you hedge. "Probably in a different context to most." He looks up at you, and you can practically see 'oh right, she's a Grey Wizard' run through his mind. "Well, ball-and-socket is an anatomical method of articulation. It works in flesh and bone, but it's a nightmare to get working with metals, or so Maximilian tells me. There's much simpler ways to achieve the same result in ways that work better in the medium. So that says to me that the reason for this being a ball looking for a joint is that it's meant to interface with bipedal anatomy." "Or it was made by an artist instead of an engineer," you counter, more for the sake of argument than out of disagreement. "The finger joints aren't anatomical, though. Revolving joints - or at least they look like them, since it's refusing to revolve - with a wider range of motion than in regular fingers. Hands are where attention is drawn, why would an artist put all that effort into a shoulder joint and then get lazy with the fingers?" "It makes sense," you concede. "And it would explain why it's not cooperating. If you're supposed to install it into flesh and blood, you'd want it immobile while you're installing it." "Which leaves us at something of a crossroads. If it is doing its best to lie dormant, with how magically insulated it is there's only two ways forward - we either go along with it or destroy it. Find a volunteer to install this into and see what happens, or break it down and start examining its innards." "No shortage of people missing an arm out there, it wouldn't be difficult to find someone who wants it back badly enough to cooperate," you say musingly. "But it would mean that it's theirs, at least for the rest of their natural life. Wouldn't be able to get volunteers otherwise." Something occurs to you. "Or... Johann might be willing to volunteer. He's a big believer in self-improvement and already has golden arms. Though the magical interface seems like it would be a problem, Hysh meeting Chamon." "I can't say for sure, but I don't think it would. If this is meant to be a long-term prosthetic, it must work through the body's natural control mechanisms - if it ran a tendril of Hysh all the way to the brain it would have negative long-term effects on the wearer. The only question would be the recharge mechanism. It's possible it absorbs exterior Hysh via the palm, but it's equally possible it's supposed to absorb it from the host, and that could present a problem. Though I think it would be a surmountable one." [ ] [ARM] Johann Attempt to attach the prosthetic arm to Johann, with his full and enthusiastic consent. [ ] [ARM] Amputee Find an amputee in the Empire who is willing to volunteer to have the arm attached to them. [ ] [ARM] Disassemble Attempt to disassemble the prosthetic arm, so you can better study its inner workings. [ ] [ARM] Finish Conclude your study of the prosthetic arm without attaching or disassembling it. --- Protocol dictates that for matters of foreign affairs you go through Karak Azul's King instead of approaching the Runesmiths of Karak Azul directly, but Kazador is an incredibly practical Dwarf: in response to your letter on the matter, he simply states that he has more faith in your judgement than he has in his ability to understand whatever it is you're trying to do and gives his blanket approval to get up to whatever mischief you have in mind with his Master Runelord. Bolstered by this, you pen a carefully-written missive to Thorek Ironbrow and start planning a trip to Karak Azul, but his brusque reply instead proposes a meeting in your penthouse and gives a range of dates when he would be passing through Karak Eight Peaks. Needless to say, this is rather unusual. Unlike Kragg, Thorek is an intensely political Dwarf and would be very aware of the advantages of you coming into his domain as a supplicant, and how much of an advantage he is ceding by instead coming to you at your convenience. You consider the possibility that you are dealing with an impostor, possibly one that is aligning itself for an assassination attempt on your person, and you resist the impulse to dismiss it out of hand. You do end up dismissing it as a virtual impossibility, but only after carefully running through the logic that would make such a counterfeit incredibly difficult to pull off compared to other possible vectors for an attempt on your life. With that worry set aside, you go through the other possible reasons and end up with two likely candidates: that he does not want the rest of his Guild learning of the meeting, or that he wants to negotiate an extreme degree of control over the project and seeks to put you off your guard. Well, the simplest way to find out for sure is to let it play out. You arrange the meeting for the next time your schedules intersect and set the stage in every way you can: you confirm that Kragg is, as usual, firmly ensconced within his workshop, you ask Wolf to be nearby so you can borrow his sense of smell and mental faculties if needed, and you've had Clan Dourback consult with their counterparts in Karak Azul for the preferences of the Runelord so they can supply a suitable keg for the meeting. With the stage as set as it's reasonably likely to get, you sit back and await your guest's arrival. Several minutes before the given time, you're alerted to a visitor outside the entrance, and you're heading towards it before the knocking sounds. With a calm you don't feel you greet the Runelord and his Hammerer escort at the door, introduce the Hammerers to a slightly lesser keg you set aside for them, and you lead Thorek to your meeting room. One-on-one, he is an incredibly intimidating figure, even for someone that has grown used to Kragg. Kragg disapproves of everything on principle, so his disapproval of any one person in particular is reflexive and easy to accept. In contrast, Thorek is constantly scrutinizing everyone around him, forever gathering evidence for a conclusion that you feel will rarely vary from the conclusion Kragg would have reached, but will sting all the more for being so carefully considered. "So," he says, as you draw a mug for him. "We send an Umgi Zhufokri to sup with rebel Elgi to claw back the knowledge of our Ancestors." You take a breath before turning and replying as you lay the mug before him. "We do," you say, "and I feel that, if anything, their rebellion against the Phoenix Crown during the time of Caledor II is a point in their favour." He pulls from the mug as you take a seat across from him, and you have to wrench your mind back on track to keep it from wondering how he manages to keep the ale off his beard. "You know the history of the Middle Mountains?" "The Dwarven history?" He nods. "I know there was a Dwarfhold there, Karaz Ghumzul, that was abandoned at the start of the Time of Woes." "Karaz Ghumzul rebelled," he growls, "and closed their gates to a Throng that went on to march with empty bellies and blunted axes to their doom at the hands of exiled Elgi sorcerers. And when the Time of Woes taught them the true, bitter taste of independence, they abandoned their Hold and sent their own starving children on a march across a ruined continent to beg for food and shelter from the Empire they betrayed while they used their riches to buy a place among the Umgi. Treason seems to be carved into the bedrock of those lands. Elgi, Dawi, Umgi, all seem to find treachery growing in their hearts in the shadows of those cursed peaks." He narrows his eyes at you. "I have marched into worse to seek the relics of the Ancestors, but the world has no shortage of cursed mountains filled with ancient woes. Even now a Throng begins to gather to right the wrongs of the Silver Road Wars, and each heartbeat I spend at the forge will prevent a drop less of Dwarven blood spilled upon Karag Agilwutraz." "You have a price in mind, I take it." One that he does not want widely known, you would guess. That would explain why you're having this meeting here, far from any Dwarven ears except those sworn to Thorek's service. "Two," he says frankly. "First, the descendants of ancient Dawi treason live fat, happy lives within Middenheim. There are many wrongs that must be punished before their own inherited sins are a priority for the Karaz Ankor, but they still hold the keys to Karaz Ghumzul. I need allies in the Empire to bring pressure to bear on them so they will surrender those keys, so that I might harvest a beginning of repayment from its ruins." Most Imperial cities with a substantial population of expatriate Dwarves are very protective of such industrious and knowledgeable citizens, and Middenheim is no exception. Trying to bring pressure to bear on them would be politically fraught. But you knew that partnership with a Runelord as renowned as Thorek Ironbrow would not be cheap. "And the second?" Some of the steel goes out of Thorek, and he takes another pull on his ale as he considers his words. "The Waystones," he says carefully, "are a product of some of the greatest minds of the Golden Age. There are many who would say that there is no question that their workings would be considered secrets of Runesmithing, and therefore cannot be shared with anyone without the blood of Thungni flowing through their veins. But there is another line of argument, that this information was so intimately entwined with Zhuf magic that some knowledge of it must have been shared with the Elgi, and so it cannot be called a sin to share that knowledge without levelling that accusation at those that were taught by the Ancestor Gods incarnate. I look at these facts arrayed before me, and know that you are asking me to choose an interpretation of them that is favourable to you. So I would ask the same of you." "Aye?" you say cautiously, running through the possibilities in your mind. Karag Dum, you'd guess, or Karak Vlag. Either the old scar or the fresh wound in Runesmithing orthodoxy. "Karag Dum," he says. "I've heard much from many, and like with the matter of the Waystones, the facts are inarguable, but the interpretations of those facts are more open. You spent more time with Thane Borek Forkbeard than most, did you not?" "I did." "You heard the last words he spoke before he left the Expedition, and you've proven you have respectable insight in unusual matters. Those that you repeated those words to have repeated them to me, but the only one who heard them from his lips is you. So if any can claim insight to what he meant, it is you." "And you have a particular interpretation in mind?" "Just as you do for the Waystones matter. It seems to me is that Borek was ashamed but not surprised by what he found at Karag Dum. Which would seem to imply that whatever terrible deal they struck with Cor-Dum, it was a final resort that desperation drove them into. Desperation brought on, in no small part, by the schism in the Cult of Thungni, and the southern Runelords abusing their authority to paint Karag Dum as untrustworthy. And as such, when they faced the forces of Chaos, they did so alone." "You once told me that you'd tear the Guild asunder if you knew for sure that that was the case." "And your words would give me the authority to do so. Tear it apart and melt it down, that it may be reforged anew. Since we last spoke I have been travelling the Karaz Ankor, and everywhere I look I see so-called Runelords with beards grown yellow instead of white, squatting atop their secrets as jealously and uselessly as a Dragon atop a hoard. They fail the Karaz Ankor twice over, for in the absence of Thungni, Morgrim grows reckless and hasty in his experimentation as He tries to do alone what should be the work of two. I will correct this in time, but could do so in a more efficient and lasting manner with your testimony as a banner." You consider his words carefully. On one hand, an internal matter of the Empire. Relatively simple, but one that would require you to exert your influence upon some very touchy people, and could cause turbulence in Middenheim - but Middenheim is already out on a limb for the sake of their new allies, and it wouldn't be hard to nudge them further. You're sure the Colleges would feel it is a small price to pay for the cooperation of a Runelord, and it's a decision your rank allows you to make on their behalf. On the other hand, an internal matter of the Karaz Ankor, much more complicated and potentially ugly, but one that would unfold far from you and in a way that would leave your hands clean. It's difficult to weigh the two matters against each other, and against the amount of aid a Runelord of Thorek's calibre could offer. Or you could assist with both. Though you're sure Thorek would grant all the insight he has if his cooperation was purchased, there's a gulf between that and having his full partnership. Being his ally in both matters would firmly align your cause with his, and would mean that he would make time for the Waystone Project, rather than simply lending it whatever he can spare. It would also greatly increase his influence within the Karaz Ankor, for better and for worse. Is that something you want? Is that what's best for the Waystone Project? For the Empire? For the Karaz Ankor? [ ] [THOREK] Karaz Ghumzul Lend your influence to pressuring the expatriate Dwarves of Middenheim into revealing the secrets of their ancestral home. [ ] [THOREK] Karag Dum Pen a testimony of Karag Dum that would be a casus belli for Thorek's bid for power and influence within the Runesmiths Guild. [ ] [THOREK] Both Either possibility would purchase the cooperation of Thorek Ironbrow. Assisting with both would make a partner of him. [ ] [THOREK] Neither There are other Runelords in the Karaz Ankor, ones with less baggage and lesser pricetags. Turn down a partnership with the Runesmiths of Karak Azul. - There will be a six hour moratorium. - Yes, Johann would volunteer for the arm thing. You may have noticed his position on taking large and potentially painful risks to improve his body. If it does go terribly wrong it could be removed and his original arm reattached. - Yes, Mathilde has the authority to make the Thorek decision on behalf of the Empire and the Colleges. That's what being a Lady Magister means.

Turn 35 Results - 2487 - Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results and unfinished business Voting results [*] [ARM] Johann [*] [THOREK] Both Unfinished business: -[*] MAX: Go through every library of the Colleges you can access for any scrap of information about Waystones. -[*] EIC: Have a blackpowder factory built in Wurtbad. -[*] SERENITY: Observations of Karag Dum and its unusual guardian "It seems that quite often of late, I'm given a choice between multiple worthy causes and forced to choose between them," you say to Thorek. "Happily, here and now there's nothing stopping me from supporting both these courses of actions." "Aye?" he says cautiously. "I won't claim to know the Dwarven soul well enough to pinpoint the problems with the Karaz Ankor, but everyone who's heard the echoes inside Karaz-a-Karak knows that the status quo isn't working. Changes are needed, and you're held in high regard by Dwarves I trust the opinion of, so if you're willing to start making what you think are the correct changes, I'm willing to throw my support behind you. Doubly so if you're willing to reciprocate." He gives you a long, searching look. "Then we have an understanding," he finally says. "One that I hope will be to the betterment of both our peoples." He extends his hand and you shake it gladly. Truth be told, you're wary of the amount of strife Thorek might cause within the Runesmiths Guild with your testimony to use as a casus belli. But while you might hesitate to empower him in this way in a vacuum, as a price for a partnership with such a respected and knowledgeable Runelord for what could be such an important project, it's one you're willing to pay. --- With the deal struck, the paper you had already planned to write on the matter of the Karag Dum now needs to serve double duty, as the stakes are too high to risk sabotaging yourself by saying one thing to the Dwarves and another to the Colleges. Instead of focusing entirely on the observations you took of the terrain around Karag Dum and the actions and aura of Cor-Dum, you will need to properly contextualize the matter in the history of Karag Dum's conflict with their southern kin, including the tensions within the Cult of Thungni - but without overstepping cultural boundaries and being seen to be openly meddling in Dwarven affairs. Karag Dum: the Third Schism of the Karaz Ankor You spend quite some time staring at that title on an otherwise blank sheet of paper, constantly being distracted from trying to write the paper by second-guessing it. It's definitely punchy, but Cython's speculation about the Dwarves makes you wonder if the Karaz Ankor shouldn't itself be considered a schism in the first place, and there's also a question about whether Karaz Ghumzul or the other 'Hill Dwarves' might have counted. But in the end you force yourself to forge forward. A bad title on a written paper is still better than a perfect title on no paper at all, and it certainly gets the point across. The paper you end up writing departs from your usual habits of sticking to the facts at first and venturing into the speculation later, as the facts won't achieve the necessary result unless they are properly contextualized. It's very narrative, hovering somewhere between a journal, a memoir, and an adventure story that hits on the notable events of the Expedition and the conversations you had with and about Borek. The climax of the story is, of course, the revelation of Cor-Dum, and Borek's unsurprised and resigned reaction to his home's new guardian, and said guardian's reaction to Borek's approach. "We did the best we could. When it comes time to tell the rest of the Karaz Ankor what has become of us, please tell them that as well. May the Ancestors forgive us." You find yourself hoping that telling his story in this way would, in some way, fulfil Borek's last request of you. After all that, the recital of all your measurements and observations taken at Karag Dum itself in an appendix feels rather prosaic, which is probably a description that has applied very few times in the past to anything related to the Shadowgave. The attribution gives you some trouble as you owe some credit to a great many people, though you're sure having so many respected names, ranks and titles attached to the account will help lend it heft. [Karag Dum: the Third Schism of the Karaz Ankor, including Observations on the Shadowgave, 2487. Subject: Unique, +3. Insight: Shattering, +3. Delivery: Competent, +0. Exotic, +1. Unpopular, -1. Shared Credit, -1. Total: 5.] --- Johann runs his golden fingers over the equally golden surface of the arm. "Explain why you think this is a good idea," he says to you, caution and curiosity warring in his tone. "Okay," you say, "we're sure this is a prosthetic. Compare the shoulder joint to the finger joints - the shoulder joint is an anatomically humanoid ball-and-socket joint, but the finger joints are hinge instead of condyloid, giving them a wider range of movement. For both artistic and war-statue purposes you'd use the same kind of joint in both, the only reason that makes sense for why you'd have one anatomical and one not is if the anatomical one is supposed to interface with a flesh-and-blood body. And speaking of which," you direct his attention to the shoulder ball, "actually, you might be better able to see this than me and Egrimm could. Do you see the separate metal in the ball?" "Do you not?" he replies, running a fingertip over the ball. "Not easily. Our conclusion is that it's a Hysh-conductive metal, which would be used to allow the arm's mechanisms to interface directly with the body's own control mechanisms - and since it's a prosthetic that would be so drastically attached to the wearer, it would need to be safe for long-term use, which means it would have to use that, it couldn't send a tendril of Hysh through the body to the brain without nasty long-term effects." "It seems like you're building a lot of assumptions on whoever made this being competent." "There's a couple of reasons for that. Have you noticed the material?" "Mostly gold," he says, scratching at it with a fingernail and then frowning at it. "Mostly. Huh. It's hard for a gold-based alloy." "Very hard. We had to chisel off samples to test it. And the Hysh stored inside it is very well-isolated, even Chamon is repelled enough to not try to sink into the material. So the material and aethyric sciences applied are unknown to us and rather sophisticated, so it feels like baseline competence can be assumed." "What's the worst-case scenario?" "If whoever made it was actually complete garbage at everything except material sciences and that specific aethyric technique, we lop it back off and reattach your original arm, which we'll be keeping on ice. I'll be observing the entire time, so I'll be able to spot any misbehaving energies and I'll have a Regrowth-based enchantment ready." "Okay, so we're at the point where this isn't a stupid idea. What makes it a good idea?" "There's a lot more Hysh inside than would be needed for a prosthetic enchantment, and presumably it does something through the palm. Considering how sharp the fingers are, some sort of weapon is likely. As you've observed the alloy is very strong, and the joints have shown a lot of resistance to external forces, which we think would translate directly to strength once it's active. And if it does turn out to be a downgrade, we can remove it and reattach the original and we'll still have gathered a lot of information about how it works. That's a paper in itself, and an extremely interesting line of research if Egrimm can reverse-engineer the mechanism it uses to interface with the body." "I do like getting my name on papers without having to actually write any of them," he says thoughtfully. "And the actual attaching?" "The Colleges can recommend properly-accredited Barber-Surgeons that have experience with working with our sort of thing." Johann runs his fingers over the claws of the golden hand, and then flinches away and then looks at the drop of blood beading at his fingertip. "I do like the idea of upgrading," he says, "and I am running out of ways to do so through the tried-and-tested methods. This may not be strictly wise, but it would definitely be interesting." "Like looting and demolishing a Skryre laboratory under a sleeping dragon." The two of you exchange grins, and Johann raps his knuckles against the golden arm. "Okay, I'm convinced. Let's do it." --- The procedure itself is surprisingly distressing. Oh, the Barber-Surgeon is perfectly accommodating, professional, and hygienic, and the detachment of the original arm goes off without a hitch. But though you've seen a great deal worse on quite a few battlefields, seeing the same sort of thing performed in a clean and well-lit room by a man who whistles as he works manages to slip past your callouses and leave you feeling quite light-headed. Johann has no such troubles, as Panoramia had supplied a draught with a bit more heft than the traditional laudanum tincture and he was quite thoroughly absent from the entire situation. Once the detached arm stops dripping, it's swathed in cloth and a runner takes it to the Gold College for it to be safely stored in their ice house, and the prosthetic is introduced to the now-exposed socket. It nestles into place reassuringly, but if you were hoping for something more dramatic to indicate that you were on the right track, you're disappointed. You take a breath, centre yourself, and concentrate your Magesight on the area until you finally see a wiggle of Hysh as a faint tendril wraps itself around what you assume to be the nerve braid. Reassured, you take a seat on the far side of the room as the Barber-Surgeon stitches the wound closed as best he can around the prosthetic. You check in regularly over the next few days, and healing seems to be surprisingly rapid, though you're not sure whether to ascribe this to some property of the prosthetic, or as a result of the superior qualities of Johann's still-gilded shoulder. By the time Johann is up and moving the prosthetic seems firmly anchored. It's yet to respond to any conscious thoughts, but it doesn't quite dangle limply either - it hangs by his side in a neutral position, the claws (which have been safely sheathed in leather) keeping a safe distance from his legs as he moves around. Something about this drives Johann into the academic landscape, and when next he emerges it's with citations from the vaults of the Great Library - where the Verenans keep books that the other Cults might object to, which usually means the Sigmarites but in this case means the Morrites, who take issue not so much with anatomical knowledge as they do with the measures taken to acquire that knowledge in the first place. "I think this arm is female," he says to you, showing you an array of diagrams and references. You look down at them for long enough for it to seem like you're taking it in. "Interesting," you say. "Walk me through your logic." "Carrying angle," he says, pointing. "It's the resting angle of the arm, so that it doesn't collide with the hips as you walk. If you look-" he stands straight, letting his functional arm rest by his side. "Compare my normal arm to my new one. I think it might have been designed to clear wider hips." "Or it might have been designed to keep from shredding your thigh with the razor-sharp claws," you point out. "Still, that would indicate it might have been designed for a human rather than a lizard, which I suppose would foil Egrimm's theory that it was from the New World. I suppose that would leave the East - Ind and Cathay are known for strange magics and fine goldsmithing. Any control or sensation yet?" "Pins and needles, though I can't tell if it's phantom pain or from the prosthetic itself. But it would take time for the shoulder joint to heal around the prosthetic, it makes sense it would be dormant until that happens." You nod. "Well, we'll keep your old arm on ice in case it stays dormant, but for now you seem to be in a state to head back to work." "Wrestling is probably out of the question," Johann says. "Fencing, maybe? Javelins? We'll think of something." "Getting along with Kadoh, I take it?" He nods. "He's pleasant company, and I'm picking up the language fairly well." "Glad to hear it." --- Returning from Altdorf with you is Maximilian, who has been busily scouring the libraries of Altdorf for any trace of Waystone information, and you read through his notes on the gyrocopter ride to Middenheim and have him fill you in verbally in the relative quiet of the trip into Laurelorn. "The Amethysts, Brights, and Celestials were helpful," he reports, "though they didn't have much more information than the Gold library - scraps and speculations and a lot of horror stories. The Amethysts did have a partial map of the Sylvanian Waystones, however. Your Order was mysterious about it, but let me peruse a few volumes - same sort of thing as the others, really. The Ambers... well, you know what they're like. The fellow I talked to said they know where most of them are in the Empire if you need to know, but that you probably didn't." "Understandable. That leaves the Lights and Jades - let me guess, they stonewalled you?" "Sort of. They hemmed and hawed and let me go through their lower-level libraries, but they didn't even have the surface-level information the other Orders had in them." "Which means they definitely know something and they're not sharing. Which I expected of the Jades, but the Lights I only suspected. That tells us where to look, and which arms to twist. Good work, Max." "But I didn't really find anything," he objects. "There were eight Orders who might have known something, you reduced that to two." Unless one of those other six were sneaky enough to have plausible-seeming basic information in their libraries to convince anyone searching that that was all there was to be found. You could see that of the Grey Order, of course, and the Celestials could be circuitous like that when they needed to be... but you didn't need to tell Max that, and it was true that this gave you firm evidence that the Light Order was worth a further look. And the basic materials he had borrowed and copied from the Orders would serve as good introductory reading for anyone. Also coming back to Laurelorn with you is the latest round of reports from the EIC and the Hochlander, including the breaking ground of the blackpowder factory in Wurtbad. You didn't foresee any problems with this and none materialized - Nuln does sometimes object to anywhere else getting in on the business of firepower, but they're not silly enough to try that when the factory is being built in the capital of a province currently at war. The rest of the business of the EIC seems to be ticking along nicely, but you are seeing some new city names pop up, most of them in southern Middenland. Perhaps a natural development from the existing presence in Altdorf and Talabecland, but perhaps Wilhelmina is expecting you to create new trading opportunities for her to jump upon. Perhaps she'd be right. Within all this day-to-day news is something a tad alarming - Ostermark seems to be partially mobilizing again, this time in the north. Rumour has it there's some sort of trouble in the Shirokij Forest, and whatever it is seems to be threatening to spill over the Talabec. This sort of regional disturbance is just a regular part of life in the Empire, and hopefully it's something that can be stamped out cooperatively between Ostermark and Kislev instead of causing tensions. The silver lining to all of this is it turns Ostermarker eyes northwards, away from the operations of the EIC. Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The five with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Laurelorn [ ] Egrimm, to try to sound out more information about the Alric situation. [ ] Vicarius Galenstra, to get to know him and his Ward. [ ] Thorek Ironbrow, to witness the arrival of the first Dwarf in Tor Lithanel for over four thousand years. Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Belegar, to discuss who has been made Loremaster after you. [ ] Gretel, who's apparently spending her newly-earned wealth to make herself at home. [ ] The Karak Azul Architects, to get involved in the design of your Library in detail. [ ] Qrech, who is putting the finishing touches on his tome on the Chaos Dwarves. Foreign Relations [ ] Stirland, to see for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. [ ] Middenland, to see how the Ulricans are going with their new Eonir coreligionists. [ ] Ostermark, because you're curious about this Shirokij business. Friends Abroad [ ] Roswita, to get a sense for who will control Sylvania after you turned down the position. [ ] Julia, to see what she has gotten up to as Stirland's most experienced spy master. Following Up [ ] The Amber College, to check in on the salamanders. [ ] The Gold College, to see what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. - There will be a three hour moratorium, to allow for suggestions for additions to the above. If you have any, please share them, even if it's after the moratorium has ended. - The Ostermark business is a social action instead of a normal one because it is absurdly far removed from being Mathilde's problem. Take it as WoQM that the only reason to investigate would be curiosity.

Turn 35 Social - 2487 - Part 1 - The Dreaming Wood of Laurelorn

Spoiler: Voting results Voting results [*] Thorek Ironbrow, to witness the arrival of the first Dwarf in Tor Lithanel for over four thousand years. [*] Qrech, who is putting the finishing touches on his tome on the Chaos Dwarves. [*] Egrimm, to try to sound out more information about the Alric situation. [*] The Karak Azul Architects, to get involved in the design of your Library in detail. [*] Vicarius Galenstra, to get to know him and his Ward. [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Near Tor Lithanel is a ring of Waystones marking the edge of the Verdan Lithridrom, the Wishing Woods. With shocking abruptness the cultivated beauty of the Laurelorn gives way to dense, dark stands of needle-leaved conifers draped with hanging lichens. It is said that to make an offering at a Waystone and sleep on the outskirts of the Woods is to be visited with prophetic dreams or terrifying nightmares, and many of the Elven artists you've spoken to seem to believe that both are equally useful for pursuing their art. It is also said that to actually enter the woods is to invite the nightmares to take up permanent residence within you. Reason enough to stay away under normal circumstances, but you left normal circumstances behind quite some time ago, and today you have been invited within by Queen Marrisith to meet with what is to be her contribution to the project. Why said delegate couldn't simply knock on your door and introduce themself is a line of thought that keeps you quite occupied as you dwell on the lurid stories you've heard of the place, but the Queen's letter directed you to a specific approach to the woods where the dense branches and curtains give way to a wide and wheel-rutted path leading deeper within, which goes some way to reassuring you. It probably isn't that treacherous if it sees this much traffic. It's a long and eerie walk with only very infrequent shafts of sunlight managing to weave through the foliage overhead and a constant chorus of crunching needles underfoot, and by the end of it you're sure there's something off about these woods, but you're not sure what. The ring of Waystones means there are next to no ambient Winds, but you keep getting an eerily familiar sensation akin to vertigo. Your instincts keep telling you to look down, but that's because your instincts only think in three dimensions. The Aethyr is always lurking just under the fragile skin of reality, but here that skin has been cultivated into a realm of its own. At last you emerge into the centre of the wood, blinking in the sudden sunlight, where the densely-packed trees crowd up against the edge of an ancient, open amphitheatre, the stage sunk deep below ground level. The seating tiers surrounding are filled with what you at first took to be still more trees, but on further examination they prove to lack both leaves and life. The stage itself is crowded with stacked crates and barrels and sitting atop one of them and looking thoroughly bored is Queen Marrisith, glaring up at the sun and drumming her heels against the wood. "Your Majesty," you say, making your way down the ramp towards her. "Lady Magister," she replies. "Mmm. Sounds almost like ladroi nastirr. There used to be a temple by that name - a well-regarded, hmm, let's say a house of worship dedicated to Atharti. I believe you know Her as Vylmar." You're not sure what the proper reaction is to having your title so mangled by a Queen, but you try not to let any of it show on your face. "Worship of Vylmar has been outlawed for centuries in the Empire." She frowns. "Why?" "He was seen as too similar to the Tempter, I believe." Her frown deepens. "Did this forbidding banish all desire for pleasure from the Empire?" "I don't believe it did." "Then why cede all that ground to the Tempter?" She raises a hand. "You needn't answer that. It's a debate I've heard too many times among my own people, and those that champion it the loudest are so often those that stand to gain should House Maeglin fall in stature. Perhaps the same dynamic was at play among your people." She looks up again, frowning at the sun. "My mother told me that there was originally a stone circle that indicated when the time was right to reach the Grey Lords, but it was replaced with this amphitheatre in the time of my grandmother. Easier to move things in and out and easier to defend, but so much less informative." "I take it these Grey Lords are in the liminal realm I can feel?" you ask with deliberate casualness. She raises her eyebrows at you. "You are full of surprises, aren't you? Yes, they're tucked away in the forest's Dreaming Wood. There are entrances scattered throughout the Laurelorn and touching it often takes as little as a thought, but a season's pay for their services," she raps her knuckles on the crate she's sitting atop, "requires the right time and the right place." There's a sudden shimmer of magical energies and she smiles. "That will be them." The sensation of vertigo grows stronger and your senses scream to you that you are falling despite standing upright, and in the space between two heartbeats the woods surrounding you disappears, it and the sky alike replaced by a vast and softly glowing dome of marble encapsulating the amphitheatre. Its only break is at the top of the ramp you entered by, where a narrow corridor extends into darkness. Standing framed in it is an aged Elven man with his white hair and beard cropped close, wearing worn hose and tunic under a long travelling cloak. With his hood up to cover his ears he wouldn't look out of place in any tavern in the Empire. "Dear Marrisethai," he says, striding down the ramp like an actor onto the stage, "you look more like your mother every decade. How have you been?" "All the better to see you're out of your tower once more, Lord Hatalath." She reaches out to embrace him as he approaches, and his hug lifts her off the crate. "I had thought the Lords Thanan would be joining us for this effort." "You know them, they're always happy to visit but they want to disappear home as soon as the sun kisses the horizon. And I had just wrapped up my latest project, and I've actually walked the world since the time when humans were terrified primitives hiding in the woods and mimicking our Waystones, so I was the natural choice. Besides, the other option was your Uncle." Marrisith's smile turns brittle as she is released from the Elf's arms. "Then you doubly bless us with your presence. I take it that means you know what must be done?" "Something about the Dwarves wanting to compare notes, I was told. Lord Sarumar said they were doing something with their network again." "And so I approached them via our new allies in the hopes they could be lured into a joint research project - you and yours keep telling me how much of a setback it is whenever the flow of magic lessens, and with the isolationists of the High Council no longer in the majority we took an opportunity." "And her?" he asks, looking over to you. "A go-between from the human realms, I take it? One who has been dabbling quite a bit in things she shouldn't, by the look of her. Which Emperor does this one belong to?" "They've only the one Emperor now, and this one speaks Eltharin, and will be a party to the research," Queen Marrisith says, smiling and shaking her head. "Don't the others keep you up to date?" "They might, I'm not good at paying attention when I'm busy. How did any of those things happen?" "The latest Everchosen forced them to unite or perish, and Teclis - the current Loremaster of Hoeth, one of the line of Aenarion - convinced them to rethink their opinions on magic, and apparently taught some of them our language in the process. Our guest is from one of their single-Wind Orders of Magic." "So who's the go-between for the Dwarves?" "She is also here on behalf of King Belegar of Karak Eight Peaks." The Elf frowns, his brow furrowing. "They got it back? And they're employing human Mages? Tch, you look away for a few centuries and the whole world changes on you. Greetings, daughter of the Empire," he says, turning to you and switching to archaic but fluent Reikspiel as he looks you up and down. "Greetings to you, daughter of Freya. It's been some time since I walked your realm, but I always found the Asoborns to be a cheerful and sensible lot. Much better than the Styrigen. I am the Grey Lord Hatalath." You do your best to reply in kind. "I am Lady Magister Mathilde Weber of the Grey Order, and Loremaster to King Belegar. I've only known your people for a few months, but I relish the opportunity to know more." He smiles. "My people are but twelve, and I doubt you've met any but I - but fear not, because there is no better place to start. We are the least numerous third of Laurelorn, and we differ as much from the other two as they do from each other, but do just as much to keep our realm alive." He snaps his fingers and with a creak of wood, the not-trees still surrounding you jerk to life as energies flow through the marble. With jerky motions they descend down the stairs, each of them wrapping wooden arms around a different piece of cargo and lifting them effortlessly off the ground, and the bizarre procession disappears up the ramp. "And in turn, they keep us alive. Trying to live entirely on fruits and vegetables harvested from a Dreaming Wood is not an experience I can recommend." "We keep you quite a bit better off than merely 'alive'. And some of our artists swear by the Dreaming Diet," Marrisith replies. "Only ever for as long as it takes for the novelty to wear off. Despite what so many of their works insist, there is a terrible boredom to pain." The last of the wooden golems disappears into the darkness, and moments later another emerges at the head of a similar line, though you cannot tell if it is the same things returned or an entirely new procession. Only the first three are carrying crates, and the others return to their places in the seats surrounding you empty-handed. "That's everything but the uglier of those cuirasses, the widdershins columnar assemblage on it needed to be replaced entirely. It should be ready by the next exchange." "As ever, you have our gratitude," Marrisith says with a smile. "Then I hope it was in one of those boxes, because if not-" he pauses a second and then snaps his fingers - but you could feel the process beginning while he was still talking, so you know that it wasn't the gesture that banished the dome of marble and returned you to the material world. "If not, I'll have it all to myself and the other Lords will have to go without."

Turn 35 Social - 2487 - Part 2

Spoiler: Unfinished business [*] Thorek Ironbrow, to witness the arrival of the first Dwarf in Tor Lithanel for over four thousand years. [*] Qrech, who is putting the finishing touches on his tome on the Chaos Dwarves. [*] Egrimm, to try to sound out more information about the Alric situation. [*] The Karak Azul Architects, to get involved in the design of your Library in detail. [*] Vicarius Galenstra, to get to know him and his Ward. When you first entered Laurelorn, you took a careful and considered approach. You came on your own, went through Middenland and the Schadensumpf to avoid the sticky Nordland situation, and arranged ahead of time for an escort to meet you at the border. You made sure there was as little chance of controversy and misunderstanding as possible to make a smooth entrance into Laurelorn society. Thorek Ironbrow does not do that. He does not carefully organize his entrance with Laurelorn notables, as he takes it as a given you would have taken care of that and made sure that his arrival at some point was expected. He does not carefully circle around tricky political situations when doing so would require him to enter via a swamp: he lands a flight of Gyrocarriages in Salzenmund while flying the flag of Karak Azul and simply lets anyone who had the capacity to be an obstacle realize for themselves that they really shouldn't try it, and marches west with a score of Longbeards as an escort - and these are Clan Ironbrow Longbeards that have served under the Thunderhorn, so they're more like heavily-armoured and extravagantly-Runed Rangers than traditional Dwarven infantry, each of them carrying a crossbow and an axe with a climbing pick on the reverse. You hear later that they were shadowed by a band of Forestborn scouts the entire way, more out of fascination than concern because you had indeed made sure the Elves had known he would be coming, and that the Dwarves apparently spent some time contemplating the ruins of Kor Immarmor before continuing west along the road to Tor Lithanel. Forewarned by a message delivered by a Radiant - one of a great many type of minor forest spirit called 'spites' that the Grey Lords are said to have bound into the service of Laurelorn - you are waiting at the gates of Tor Lithanel when they finally arrive. It seems you're not the only one, as there seems to be a more Elves than usual that just happen to be casually loitering in the area, and there's a lot of looks going your way that quickly redirect themselves when you look back at them. Novelty, you've learned, is always in high demand at Tor Lithanel, and if nothing else, this experience promises to be that. There's a murmur of interest as for the first time in millennia a party of Dwarves emerges from the treeline at the other side of the Schaukel and set eyes upon the marble walls of Tor Lithanel. They must have taken a moment to compose themselves just before emerging from the trees, as their beards are on full display rather than tucked into their belts for marching. If you weren't watching for it, you might have missed the moments of hesitancy in the Dwarven approach, first as they emerged from the trees, second as they reached the bridge, and third when they emerged through the gateway into the city, finding no gatekeeper or official greeting anywhere, only loitering, curious onlookers. Every Dwarven Karak would have challenged a visiting party before now, but Laurelorn's external defences are much further out than the walls of Tor Lithanel and have been watching him since the moment he left Salzenmund. But Thorek will not show a moment of unsureness to the Elves, and you're sure that if he had to he'd have kept marching deeper into the city without pausing and figured something out on the way. Thankfully your presence there that gives him something to work with, and he changes from his course to approach you. "Loremaster," he says to you. "Runelord," you reply. His eyes run over the gathered onlookers. "No guard on the gate. Their defences must either be very good or very bad. Is there to be some kind of official greeting?" You nod - the messenger-Radiant had set off a flurry of activity in Tor Lithanel, though none of that activity had included someone to greet the visitors at the gates. Tor Lithanel's protocols still weren't used to dealing with outsiders. "Members of the High Council are gathering in the Agora to greet you." "Not their Queen?" "She will be observing, but foreign relations is the business of the High Council." "Hmph," is his only response to that. Clearly off-balance and skeptical, but reserving judgement rather than reflexively griping about societal differences - rare restraint for a Dwarf of his age. "Lead the way." --- Tor Lithanel has very many open green areas, but the Agora is foremost of them all. Located at the centre of the city and flanked on one side by the Queen's Silver Tower and on the other by the Temple of Asuryan, the only break in the otherwise open space is a single golden-veined lornalim towering high enough to make a bid for Tor Lithanel's fourth tower, and the circle of marble flagstones around it that marks where the High Council convenes. It's unexpectedly unfurnished, but having taken the opportunity to watch the proceedings of the High Council unfold - a privilege available to all residents and visitors to Tor Lithanel - you quickly saw why. Each of the members of the High Council has an intricately-decorated ivory folding chair as a symbol of their office, and the exact arrangement of who is sitting where at any given time is a visible indication of the current state of politics. Today those chairs are clustered together in a single bloc to signify unity in welcoming the newest guest to Tor Lithanel, though what speaks volumes is the chairs that aren't present, ostensibly because they were unable to be present at such short notice. You're sure that if you were able to put names to faces, you'd find that almost all of those present are those that are in favour of ties with foreign powers, and almost all of those not are those opposed to it. Watching from just outside the circle of marble is the Queen and her Champion for the Triumvirate, with the Warden of the Sun notably absent. As Thorek approaches, there is a crack of metal on marble as the Arbiter slams the haft of his ceremonial halberd on the flagstones. "Master Runelord Thorek Ironbrow of Karak Azul," he intones, his eyes locked on the approaching Dwarf, his expression unreadable. The Arbiter was the very first of the Queen's Champions, making him one of very few beings still living who fought in the War of Vengeance. One of the Elves stands. "On behalf of the High Council, House Miriel greets you, Cytho-cro-kel. To this day the metalwork of Karak Azul is renowned in Tor Lithanel." You suppress a wince at the clumsy attempt at conforming the curt syllables of Khazalid into a complimentary Eltharin pun as Thorek glances sideways at you for a translation - which you perform as best you can, finally settling on 'wise artisan' as the least bad interpretation of the epithet. "Tell them that I've heard much of them from the manlings and they seem more struck from the mold of Bel Shanaar than Caledor the Second, so I see reason to hope that our time together will echo our earliest shared history, rather than the last of it." Suppressing another wince, you translate the general gist of good repute and high hopes. Another member of the High Council stands and delivers a very similar message on behalf of House Ellemakil, and after you translate that for Thorek you have to confirm that, yes, they are saying pretty much the same thing twice. Then thrice more, as House Tindomiel, House Mardil and House Filuan all apparently want their name attached to this endeavour enough to try to mash Khazalid and Eltharin together into a suitable wordplay, and manage each time to land upon something that could easily come across as an insult if it wasn't being translated by someone being very careful to avoid exactly that. When the ordeal finally winds down, you lead the unimpressed Thorek back out of the Agora and towards the manor you're currently calling home. "Was that as pointless as it seemed?" Thorek asks you. "Those wordplays were the Elven equivalent of them inviting you to a meal in their Clan Hall. They're indicating their support for your presence here, and leaving the door open for individual overtures from you." You consult a list you've made a habit of always having on hand in Tor Lithanel. "Miriel are dedicated to Vaul, so they're probably interested in Dwarven artisanry - seemingly very much so, as they're normally one of the isolationist Houses. Ellemakil are the ones most focused on building ties with Middenland, so they're probably supporting this as an extension of that. Tindomiel are one of the more magic-inclined Houses, so they might be the ones with the highest hopes for the Project itself. Mardil are traders, so they might be angling for some sort of trade link with the Karaz Ankor. Filuan... I'm not sure what their angle would be. They're Avelornian and Isha... Ishaists? Ishaites? So they might just be loyalists to the Queen as a descendant of the Everqueen, I suppose." "Which of them would speak Reikspiel?" Thorek asks. "All of them would have access to translators. Ellemakil are the ones who would be most likely to have members that speak it themselves." "I'll reach out to some of them, then. The War of Vengeance might never have happened if we paid more attention to Elven politics, though I'm hoping this splinter state will prove less labyrinthine than their forebears." He runs his eyes over the street. "We'll be here for the next week anyway - I've been told what useful materials might be found in Elven forests by Karak Norn Runesmiths, and I aim to see whether some of them can be bought with gold, rather than steel." You're reminded that Thorek is cannier and more willing to engage in politics than most Dwarves, and you wonder if it might have been better to go with a Runesmith that would have disdained the lot and stuck to the work at hand. But it's too late to change course now. "Let me know if there's anything I can do to help," you say, "or if there's anything that should be done to make your wing of the manor more suitable for when the Project begins in earnest." "Would they object to us digging out a few levels of sub-basements?" "I'm afraid so. The root networks under the city are apparently quite substantial and considered very necessary." He sighs. "Then we'll just have to endure." --- Egrimm, you have learned, keeps close ties with many of his Light Order contemporaries, and you often find him sorting through and sending out correspondence to them. It takes little nudging for him to open up about the topic of most of them: the internal politics of his Order, particularly the power struggle at the top. Alric, it seems, is ousted from the Magister Patriarch position in all but name, with Mira assuming control of everything but the external-facing branches of its infrastructure. It becomes routine that every few days Egrimm catches you up on the latest developments, half venting at the chaos this is causing within his Order and half exulting in the misfortune he feels his former Master deserves. Mira seems to be trying to execute a takeover in a way that leaves Alric with his dignity and doesn't embarrass the Light Order, while Alric and his few remaining loyalists seem determined to fight to the last. And one unfortunate side-effect of Mira's early success is that now she and her supporters are left to keep the College operating normally while Alric is freed from those responsibilities and able to spend all his efforts and attention on seeking support. Through Egrimm's reports and corroborated by a letter here and there to the Provostry to confirm what few details could be confirmed from the outside, you hear of Alric quickly learning that Mira's preparations for this takeover have been extensive and long-running, and there are no friendly ears left to him in Altdorf. A more sensible Wizard might have accepted defeat at this point, but at his core Alric seems to be incapable of knowing when to quit, and he starts looking further afield. You hear of his talks with Grand Count Konstantin of Wissenland, and how they sputter to a halt after Mira tips off her hopefully soon-to-be counterpart of the Amethyst Order, and Elspeth von Draken needs only exert a fraction of her influence for Alric to find that Wissenland is no longer interested in the Light Order's partnership in certain sensitive matters. You hear of him trying to insert himself into the Sylvania situation and being politely but firmly evicted after he demonstrates he's more interested in digging into the fate of the late Magister Patriarch Hexensohn than he is on making any sort of contribution to the ongoing campaign. And then he starts worming his way into Talabecland, and though the Jade and Ambers stand ready to repulse any attempts by him to gain influence within the Royal Academy, he seems to be working instead on some sort of internal matter amongst Talabecland's nobility that neither Egrimm nor the Provostry seem to be able to give you any insight into. News dries up, and you find yourself feeling like you've read half of a story only to find that the rest of it is missing. "This is what he does," Egrimm says to you. "He's a mediocre administrator but, for all his faults, he is still an extremely potent Wizard with keen insight, and extremely good at burnishing any deed into a legend. He's looking for another Apesto so he can ride it back into power." "I think I may be noticing a pattern," you say. "He's thwarted in Nuln by the Lady Matriarch of the Amethysts, so he starts poking around the fate of her predecessor. He's thwarted by Roswita, and then he turns his attention to Talabecland, where she tracked the peat smuggling to." "Roswita? Van Hal?" You nod. "That's right, you worked with her father. Did you get to know her then?" "No, I never knew she existed until she inherited. I got to know her later, as part of being Loremaster to Karak Eight Peaks." "You didn't continue on after she inherited?" Egrimm asks, his voice carefully neutral but his eyes searching. "It was her decision." You consider leaving it at that, but think better of it. "She had something of a phobia of magic - understandable, given her family history. I've worked with her since then, and don't hold any ill will towards her." That wasn't always the case, but Egrimm doesn't need to know the inner thoughts of your younger self. "Ah. Yes, well, you could be right. I don't think Alric would go out of his way to outright sabotage figures that prominent over being slighted, but if there's a way for him to get what he wants while also getting his own back, he'll take it." "Well, he's unlikely to succeed in Talabecland if that's what he's after. The Elector Countess used those merchants as the exemplar for The Neglected Front, and in the process of gathering the information for that she uncovered enough evidence to damn them a dozen times over." "In any case, he seems to have found something there to keep him busy," Egrimm says, flipping through a handful of letters. "I don't like that I'm not hearing any more of it. It would be just like him to manage some last-minute comeback and yank all his puppets back into line." "If it comes to that, I can make it more trouble than it's worth to pull you away from the project. We've got one of the most prominent Runelords of the Karaz Ankor personally involved, as well as an Elven Archmage who was old when Sigmar was young. Nobody's going to want to uproot such a promising tree before it bears fruit." "Mm," Egrimm says, clearly unconvinced. "Let's hope it doesn't come to that."

Turn 35 Social - 2487 - Part 3

Spoiler: Unfinished business [*] Qrech, who is putting the finishing touches on his tome on the Chaos Dwarves. [*] The Karak Azul Architects, to get involved in the design of your Library in detail. [*] Vicarius Galenstra, to get to know him and his Ward. It is commonly believed by the uneducated that swamps are lifeless expanses of death and decay that stand in utter contrast to the fertility of the woods, but apart from a few prominent Dhar-poisoned exceptions, this is entirely untrue. Almost all wetlands are veritably bursting with life in all kinds of forms, often more so than forests, where too unified a canopy can choke all life out of the understory. But a wandering naturalist that seeks to make a judgement of their own and perhaps go on to set the record straight in the public consciousness will find many reasons to believe their efforts best turned towards a less offensive form of landscape: initially as their arrival is heralded by a choking swarm of insects eager to feed or lay eggs on their body, next as they find their way obstructed by murky waters of varying depth, sucking muds thick with strands of rotting vegetation, and stretches of plant life not thick enough to walk on but too thick to push a punt through, and if they are very unfortunate, lastly and often fatally as they run afoul of the larger and more dangerous creatures that like to call these areas home - fen worms, bog octopi, Fimir, Swamp Goblins, and River Trolls, to name a few. The Schadensumpf which fills most of the Ward of Rain is, to its credit, one of the safer examples of its kind. Travellers along the Great North Road between Marienburg and Middenheim can feel confident of making it from one side to the other with no worse than a handful of welts and a strong desire for a bath as long as they stick to the ancient road that divides it down the middle, and until recently the village of Verbegwerk was able to harvest a modest but reliable living from the plentiful wildlife and resources with no more casualties than any other isolated and unprotected village. But as the Beastherd that Laurelorn and Middenland joined forces to defeat discovered, just because it is not directly fatal does not make it easy to pass through. For this reason it serves to defend Laurelorn not just by acting as a formidable barrier to any that would approach from the south, but also an ideal killing grounds to flush intruders into, forcing them into either ignominious retreat through tens of miles of swamp while being harried by Elven archers at every step, or turning and trying to charge back into the teeth of their pursuers who will have fortified their position atop the Misty Hills. "The Warden of Storm," Vicarius Galenstra says to you as the two of you make your way through the Schadensumpf, "must concern herself with a hundred miles of the Old North Road that runs along the western treeline of Laurelorn, and the Marienburger towns and villages built along it, all filled with humans eager to fill the heads of passers-by with tales of fountains of youth and magic swords to be found in our lands. There are holy places less than a dozen miles from a human village. The Warden of the Sun must turn her eyes to the Schaukel and Demst, which can so easily allow anyone with a boat to penetrate into the heart of our realm - such as the innumerable raiders of Norsca, or the Nordlander fleet lurking just down the coast. And the Warden of Frost, such that they are, must stare across three hundred miles of tense borders, upon which are built five of the largest Nordlander towns. "But I?" He laughs. "I need watch only the Schadensumpf, and only three kinds of beings I need watch for. There are those that wish to invade our forests, who are foreign to the swamps and easy prey while they stumble through it. There are those that wish to colonize the Schadensumpf, who are always weak from struggling through the endless forests they would have had to travel through from the Delb or the Mirror Moors. And there are the humans, most of whom only need fishing out of the muck after wandering off the road." "No attempts to retake their village?" "None, though a handful have attempted to return to hunt the crane flocks for their feathers - apparently the human fashion is to wear them in their hats." He draws an arrow from his quiver, studying the shimmering black fletching. "To my eyes they look quite foolish after we assist them with their desire to have feathers jutting from their head, but I never was one for fashion." You're not entirely comfortable with an Elf speaking so casually of slain humans, but if they were caught poaching by Middenland's patrols they'd face the same fate, just from a noose instead of a bowstring. "And the village of Kammendun?" you ask carefully. Vorbegwerk in the north of the Schadensumpf was a tiny village too small to appear on most maps and too poor for anyone to bother to work out who they should pay tax to, but Kammendun in the south is significantly larger and part of the Graf's demesne. "They are far from the temptation of the nesting grounds, and further from the heart of Laurelorn. They know what not to do, and sometimes identify and alert us to a threat before we notice it." He pauses for a moment, an odd look on his face. "They sometimes erect shrines to us. Leaving us rare flowers, or smoked fish, or particularly large lumps of bog ore. Nothing we desperately need, but it's better to have an extra tincture or ration or quiver than not, so we take what might be useful and repay them with the occasional trinket from the city." You're pretty sure Galenstra is ignorant of how much 'trinkets' like that go for in Marienburg, and how much dearer they get as you get further from the sea. No wonder the villagers give offerings. "Does House Fanpatar live in the Pass of Stone?" you ask, changing the subject. He gives you a searching look. "Why do you ask?" Sensing a touchy subject, you form your words carefully. "There seems to be a great deal of importance placed on whether one lives inside or outside the city, yet until recently two of the three most influential families had their powerbase outside of it." He watches you for a moment longer before replying. "It is an observation that has been made a number of times through the years, often by those jealous of that influence. House Fanpatar are Cityborn, and as such we live in Tor Lithanel. The Pass of Stone has only very basic living facilities for when our defence of Laurelorn requires us to spend time away from our true home." "And if it had more than very basic living facilities, it would undermine your claim of being Cityborn?" "There are those that would make that argument. So the majority of the tower remains in ruins as a symbol of our dedication to Tor Lithanel." "That seems like it would be quite a hardship." He gives you another long look. "The contrast is good for the soul. Silk is all the smoother after weeks of bark and leather." He cocks his head, running his eyes along the terrain. "Do you hear that?" You turn your focus to the constant background whine of insects, much of which is trying fruitlessly to find purchase on your Aethyric Armour. "The... sort of a rasping chirp?" "A type of small, timid frog. If there was anything amiss, they would not be calling. The equivalent of a woodlands hunter knowing a predator is near if the birds stop calling, I suppose. You wanted to know about House Fanpatar? This is what we spend much of our time doing - making sure the balance of the swamp is as it should be, and finding out what has changed if it is not." You flinch and jerk your head away as some sort of midge tries to find purchase on your eyeball. "And the insects? Is it some sort of family secret that keeps them from trying to feast on you?" He laughs. "The Grey Lords make a potion that makes Elven blood poisonous to insects. Anything that sees Elves as a meal has long since gone extinct. And that's another sign of change for us to watch for - if we're getting bitten, it means that there's something new doing the biting, and that often indicates some greater source of imbalance. Swamp Goblins especially like to cultivate their own strains of pests." "Ah," you say simply. There's a larger discussion there you're tempted to try to touch on about whether the natural state of the swamp is something to venerate in itself, or simply the raw material to be shaped, but you're worried it might be one of the points of contention between the Cityborn and the Forestborn, and decide not to chance it. If you're going to risk offending, it should be for answers with more meaning to you than mere curiosity. "Is that how you see an alliance with Middenland? One more type of frog to listen for the chirp of?" He gives you an amused smile. "Words are cheap. If a frog had enough of a mind to ask me what I thought of it, I would flatter it for its contribution to the defence of the swamps. But I have no need to do so for your kind. We do not have an island paradise for us to sneer across the waves at the world from. The High Council has spent far too much time contemplating the results of a conflict with Nordland turning into all-out war between your peoples and mine to dismiss you so easily. One cannot spend a lifetime staring up the shaft of extinction at the hands of humanity and still dismiss them so easily. And by all indications, your kind will be easier to coexist with than the beings our erstwhile cousins of Loren Faen joined themselves to." Smarter than a frog, easier to get along with than a tree daemon. Not the most glowing assessment of humanity you've ever heard, but you'll take it. --- If one were to visit the University of Altdorf and ask what the residents thought of Quirin Waramunt BPhSSc(NE)(Alt), one would not encounter anyone who knew the name with a mild opinion of the mysterious correspondence student. There are those who hate him for his relentless inability to let a topic go, there are those frustrated by his constant bombardment of letters to anyone he thinks has information that could be of use, there are those that are driven to distraction by the mystery of who he is and why he is always able to communicate but never able to visit in person. From this last category one might hear all kinds of outlandish theories: that he is a nobleman under house arrest, that he is a secret mutant unable to move in public, that he is a Wizard unwilling or unable to leave his native campus, that he is an Elf or Dwarf rejected by their own species' institutions who has resorted to human ones. But for those interested enough in Near-Eastern Studies and willing to look past his quirks, Quirin Waramunt represents an amazing resource, combining exhaustive knowledge, bottomless interest, access to all sorts of eclectic materials, and a burning hunger to make an impression into an ideal penpal for students and faculty alike. Every now and then an academic feeler goes out as someone grows suspicious of the breadth of knowledge this strange and remote figure seems to hold and tries to determine if the source can be trusted, and the fact that those feelers are invariably intercepted and replied to from the highest level with a very firm 'yes, and all further details are classified' inevitably increases the level of interest and mystery. After the Karag Dum Expedition a rumour begin to spread that Quirin Waramunt had been on that Expedition, and that rumour was incorporated into the cover story by having it listed as a source for fictional research materials to create a fictional source for some of Quirin's knowledge. It is not so outlandish to imagine that the Expedition might have encountered Chaos Dwarves or Ogres and sent bodies or prisoners back west for study, after all, and the point of contact for anyone who might seek to disprove this hypothetical would be yourself. From the center of this spiderweb of correspondence Qrech has been busily evaluating all the information available and finding plenty of room for his own contribution to the corpus. As he once said to you, someone who has ever set eyes on a living Chaos Dwarf represents a rare depth of personal experience among scholars in the Empire, but Qrech spent years clashing with them and their slave-soldiers. It is difficult to say whether having feasted on the flesh of the subject in question represents a tangible academic advantage, but Qrech certainly feels that it does, even after he is convinced to drop all mentions of taste from the tome he is constructing. An unexpected contribution to this quarter is the Grey College's Editors getting involved. The simplest understanding of this office is that these are the people responsible for making sure that all publications of the Grey Order have the proper classification to protect the means, methods, and sources the Order makes use of from enemy scrutiny, but it is also their responsibility to take any information that might be of use to the Empire, separate it from its origin, and launder it in such a way that it develops a plausible new source that cannot be traced back to the Order. Qrech represents an ideal beneficiary of this, as his identity already needs to be kept secret and his correspondence already needs to be monitored. Through this Qrech gains access to two significant sources of information to filter into something more suitable for general consumption: the notes covering bits and pieces that Lady Magister Grey has not gotten around to publishing, and the translation of a book on Chaos Dwarf anatomy by Magister Grey and Journeyman Gold, who you assuredly know nothing about but might venture the observation that they sure sound like wise and insightful individuals. Over two years all of this insight, access, and correspondence has been distilled into a loosely-bound stack of paper covered in scrawled handwriting that always takes you a few minutes to readjust to, and you make your way through it during the time you spend at Karak Eight Peaks. Most extant writings on the Chaos Dwarves and the beings associated with them are written like bestiaries, where each variety is given a general description, notes on habitat, and observations of what they have been seen to be doing, rather as if an outside observer of the Empire wrote a book on it divided into individual sections on humans, horses, pigs, cows, sheep, and dogs, without any mention of provinces or the ranks of nobility. One of many oddities of this approach is that the Chaos Dwarves themselves are the least written about, as the fact that they're seen throughout the Dark Lands doing all sorts of things makes it difficult to draw conclusions from the outside. Qrech has written his own take on the Chaos Dwarves as a study of their society, and at each strata Chaos Dwarves have their own entries, including the insignia and armament one can use to identify their role in the military apparatus of Zharr-Naggrund. There are still a great many parts of their society left uncovered, as Qrech's insights are mainly limited to their military and the parts that proved vulnerable to raids by Skaven or Grey Wizard. But it still represents a sizable step forward from the previous materials. "Li-cen-tiate," Qrech says, squinting at a letter from the University. He seems to be doing that a lot lately, and you make a note to look into eyeglasses for him. "Quirin has not sought lesser title, why does the University give it?" "The timing of it suggests that it is in response to your book - perhaps they want you to have the higher title in the attribution." "Ah, protect many egos from being seen up by a mere buphessc," he says with a pleased chitter, and you suppress a wince at his habit of pronouncing post-nominals as a word. "Much easier for it to be a licphessc. Quirin is no mere Packmaster, Quirin is practically a Moulder, no vulnerability in being surpassed. Perhaps it is not so foolish to leave defeated rivals uneaten, as it is good knowing they will live many, many years knowing that Quirin has bested them. So, this means the University will publish the book?" "My Order has given it the go-ahead for general publishing, as those the Chaos Dwarves might hold responsible for it are either already their enemies or sufficiently protected by secrecy. So it seems so." Qrech pauses for a moment. "Publish how far?" he asks, in that quiet tone of voice that he uses when his instincts are screaming at him not to reveal a vulnerability. You consider the question. "The University of Altdorf has reciprocal agreements with the other provincial institutions, so they'd all get copies - the Collegium Theologica, the Royal Academy, Nuln, Streissen, Salzenmund. Copies would go to each of the Orders. Diesdorf would want a copy, so then Bergo and the Aquilas would want them, so then the Myrmidian institutions would want them. Once you factor in libraries and private collections, I'd say a hundred copies wouldn't be unreasonable." Qrech is quiet for a long time. "Yes," he eventually says. "This is good. Little parts of Quirin everywhere, impossible to stamp out." He's quiet for a moment longer. "Licentiate Quirin, though. Not Doctor Quirin. Not yet. Still not done." He flexes a paw, then takes up his quill. "Still more work to do." You smile as Qrech seems to forget your presence as he returns to his writing, and let yourself out of his cell. It seems that Qrech is still far from done paying dividends for the Empire and its allies. [Book published: The Loathsome Chaos Dwarves and All Their Vile Kin] --- Kvinn-Wyr is the sight of a great deal of work, as the masons of Karak Azul have arrived and are making themselves busy with establishing a more suitable entrance at ground level while they await the decisions of how the library itself will be built. It takes you a while to grapple with the terminology you're bombarded with and wrestle it into terms you can make use of, but eventually you manage to establish a foundation of understanding with the masons that boils the infinite possibilities of unworked stone into a much more manageable list based on what priorities you wish to build in to the very bones of your library. While you will, of course, seek to make a library that is reasonably capacious, comfortable, pious, well-ordered, enduring, and secure, your involvement here lets you decide what you will focus on to a truly unreasonable extent. [ ] Capacity You could focus on sheer size, making a library that can be conveniently scaled pretty much indefinitely. Your library is always going to be able to grow, but if you want to go completely off the rails and dedicate yourself to collecting literally every written work ever made, this library will be able to handle that without any problems. [ ] Comfort You could focus on a library that will be a delight to visit or even study at for prolonged periods, with a focus on easy accessibility, well-lit reading areas, plentiful study rooms, private quarters, and built-in taverns and restaurants. [ ] Holy Most libraries are dedicated to one God or another, so why not follow the trend? Carve dedications to Verena, Valaya, Quinsberry, and Hoeth into the very bedrock alongside subtle nods to Ranald, and make allowances for large public shrines to the more acceptable Gods. [ ] Order Despite the best efforts of librarians, practically every library eventually has to resort to The Stacks when the amount of books outstrips the ability to impose order on them. Every scholar has known the experience of delving deep into a maze of dimly-lit shelves many times their height in search of a volume that the library's records insist is in there somewhere. Seek from the outset to ensure that no visitor to your library ever suffers this fate. [ ] Preservation You could focus from the outset on the preservation of the gathered materials from both natural disaster and the march of time. The masons will use techniques meant for facilities built atop live volcanoes to create a library that could withstand being the epicentre of the beginning of a second Time of Woes, and a great deal of care paid to air shafts and ambient humidity will create separate sections of the library tailored for the different needs of paper, parchment, and papyrus, and a means of completely securing the entire facility such that it could last another few millennia of enemy inhabitation unbreached. [ ] Security Your personal library is split into three sections: general access, Collegiate access, and completely secret. A larger facility will need a commensurately more complex system. Build the library from the ground up so that there will be different sections dedicated to different levels of access, and in such a way that every visitor will be convinced that the highest level they have access to is the highest level that exists. - There will be a three hour moratorium. - If you have ideas for a different general focus for a library, let me know.

Turn 35 Social - 2487 - Part 4

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Order Tally Keep it simple. Books only have purpose if they are used, and they can only be used if they can be found. Though there is a certain romance to delving deep into the stacks of an ancient library in search of an even more ancient tome, that scenario represents a failure on the part of the library, a failure that renders huge swathes of their inventory useless. How much time is wasted in those searches? How much more could have been accomplished with that time? Easy enough said, but certainly not as easily done. It's all well and good to pledge to a library where all the books are in the right places to be found, but it's not like librarians go out of their way to create a disordered jumble - it emerges inevitably despite the best of intentions. To avoid that will require careful thought on your part, but before any of that, the masons require instruction. Well, there's one major advantage you have over the average librarian, and that is that your library will not be hemmed in by immovable streets and expensive buildings. You explain to the masons that the site of the library will require a lot of space and even more room to expand and leave them to survey the existing halls and caverns of the mountain. If no suitable site presents itself then your library can be hewn into untouched stone, but if there's an existing part of the mountain that can be adapted, so much the better. You make your way back home and to your library, and as you enter you try to see it with fresh eyes. Excluding fiction, you currently have ten categories, but these are divisions born of necessity rather than strict logic. You have three categories on magic because of the necessity of your books on subjects like Chaos and Necromancy and Dark Magic to be less accessible than books on magical theory, but in any rational system they would fall under the same category. You have zoology separate from the other sciences because of the number of books you've accumulated on the topic. You have the study of societies divided up on the basis of whether they are friendly or hostile to the Empire. This works well enough for a personal collection, but that won't do for a truly grand library. You turn your mind to the various libraries you've encountered over the years. Some arrange their works entirely by the name of the author or, even worse, by their order of acquisition, and depend entirely on indexes, catalogues, and the memory of the librarians to find works on specific topics. You know some libraries consider all fields of study to be separate branches of philosophy, and once eavesdropped on a rather heated debate on whether aesthetics was a subbranch of applied philosophy or a branch in its own right, which rather highlights the trouble with such lofty divisions - it turns the discussion into one of values, rather than practicality. Other libraries consider the entire corpus of writings split into the three categories of Morals, Science, and Devotion, which seems actively unhelpful to you. The libraries of the Colleges are focused almost entirely on magical theory and the specializations of their Orders, the Great Library of Altdorf is split according to the subjects of the University of Altdorf it adjoins, and you've heard the Great Library of Marienburg is as much an organ of government as it is a body of knowledge and as such focuses a great deal on jurisprudence and the civil records of the city. Well, if you are to avoid the mistakes of the past, then perhaps it is best to break entirely with the way they've done things. The philosophical exactitude of the division is irrelevant, what matters is whether it helps or hinders those looking for books on a specific topic. Any set of divisions will do as long as it is easily comprehended and is consistently and universally applied. All philosophical questions about the nature of knowledge and its most natural divisions can and must be disregarded, as you are not pursuing some abstract truth, you need a robust system of division for the books that exist here and now, in an imperfect world and written by imperfect beings. You look over your shelves again and start planning. Magic, of course, will need to be its own section, as to do otherwise would be to run immediately afoul of the Articles. And as much as an argument might be made for it to be a subheading of magic, divinity would need to be on its own unless you want to grossly insult everyone who would be supplying the books that would fill it. But the rest of the topics can and should be compressed down: geography and zoology are themselves subsets of Natural Philosophy, which covers the study of the natural forces of the world and their applications, which leaves only where the natural world has been supplanted by thinking beings: Social Philosophy. Four neat divisions that can themselves be subdivided into separate fields. At first each subdivision can have its own shelf, and later its own bookshelf, and eventually, perhaps, its own hall, depending on the final design of the library. You run your eye over your current library, mentally dividing up the books in front of you. Your section on Sciences and Arts would need to be split up, as Linguistics and Trade would fall under Social Philosophy while most of the rest would be Natural Philosophy. But Architecture trips you up, as it is, in essence, the application of Natural Philosophy to construct the edifices of Social Philosophy. You uneasily move on, and find yourself frowning again as you reach one of the smaller sections: War. Among many volumes on the art of wielding a greatsword - which itself does not fit as comfortably as you'd like into the heading of Natural Philosophy - are a handful of Skaven books on tactics and logistics, and you again find yourself unsure. It might be accurate to call warfare a subdivision of Social Philosophy, but that itself feels more like an invitation to philosophical musing than it does a clean categorization. This is a problem that most institutions avoid entirely, as the Universities are dedicated to peaceful pursuits while the art of war is studied at places like the Diesdorf Military College and the Aquila Academy, and on the religious side of things Verena leaves the study of war to Myrmidia. Do you carve out a new section entirely for War? Or do you go right back to the drawing board and come up with divisions that don't have this problem? Okay, say you start over. Magic and Divinity can stay. Perhaps the problem is in philosophy, which as a term has a great deal of historical heft but perhaps is not best suited for a library that should be serving those who get dirt and blood on their hands. Let us instead consider science, the term preferred by the worldlier institutions. You can copy the previous divisions over as Natural Science and Social Science, but in this framing a third suggests itself: Applied Science. This would neatly solve the problem of War and Architecture, as both would fall under this new category, but would it create new problems? You're already separating books according to whether they're applied or not, aren't you? If you had books on plants in your library, they'd be alongside the zoological texts, well separate to Agriculture. Books on Physics would be separate to books on Engineering. You'd have to split up your section on Chemistry, but it would not be a difficult division, as the weighty tomes on theoretical chemistry are easily split off from the smaller, hardier books that tell one the precise steps necessary to produce things like acids and explosives. Magic, Divinity, Natural Science, Social Science, Applied Science. You toy with the idea of applying the theme across the board, but Divine Science seems like it might be a controversial heading and Magical Science implies the study of all the headings it would contain, some of which you are bound by the Articles not to do. You might need to add more sections in the future - Fiction, perhaps - but those five seem like they would neatly encompass the earliest additions. You jot down those headings and the thoughts that gave rise to them and tuck them away in a corner of your library. There's still more work to be done, details about bookshelf design and indexing and catalogues and whatnot, but no need to frontload all that effort when the masons are still wandering around looking for a good place to start swinging a pick. There's also the question of acquisitions. From a Dwarven perspective, the Library began existing the moment the masons set eyes on Kvinn-Wyr. This might mean you're going to be stacking up books in awkward corners of your home for a while, but that's a sacrifice you're willing to make. --- Library Purchases: [ ] [LIBRARY] Barak Varr booksellers: name three public topics to acquire all available Empire and Dwarven books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Library of Mournings: name two non-magical topics to hire Cityborn scribes to copy all available Laurelorn books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Back-fill. Instead of seeking books on specific topics, fill in some of the sections of your existing library where you have some of the available books from the Empire and the Dwarves on a subject, but not all. Will acquire more books total than other options, but cannot be directed. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a three hour moratorium. - Mathilde can spend her own money on buying additional books at the usual rate under Other Purchases. The coming turn will have options to unlock new acquisition methods. - 'Science' being used here is a bit anachronistic in English, but the Empire doesn't speak English. 'Wissenschaft' was widely used in German significantly earlier than 'science' was in English. - I've added the Waystone Project and the Library to the Organizations threadmark.

Turn 36 - 2487.5 - Making Old Friends

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [LIBRARY] Library of Mournings: name two non-magical topics to hire Cityborn scribes to copy all available Laurelorn books on. -[*] Eonir of Laurelorn -[*] Weaving Spider silk [*] [DWARF] Runed pistols [*] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [*] [PURCHASE] No purchase. Tally Laurelorn has a great deal of idle and literate citizens who would jump at the chance to earn a few crowns, and it has a very large library open to its general public. With a distribution of Dwarven gold from Kron-Azril-Ungol's acquisitions budget several shelves were emptied and a significant portion of the partitioned study desks filled, and several months later you're left with quite a stack of Yen-Eltharin manuscripts. For this first wave of exotic additions to your nascent library you've focused on two things: the history and culture of Laurelorn in their own words, which you expect to be of great use to you in the coming years, as well as every book that could be found covering their textile industry. As the Karaz Ankor's Weavers Guild once announced, the use of spider-silk is the domain of Elves and Goblins, so you plan to use a stack of tomes as a battering ram to unblock whatever obstruction is keeping Karak Eight Peaks' silk industry from burgeoning. When you next return to Karak Eight Peaks with a Gyrocarriage loaded with books, you transfer the ones on textiles to a wheelbarrow and make your way through Karag Nar until you arrive at the office of the Karag's Viceroy, Francesco Caravello, into whose lap the silk question was dropped when the Dwarven Weavers refused to have anything to do with it. "Lady Magister," he says in confusion, hand moving away from the sword he'd started reaching for when your wheelbarrow slammed his door open. "How can I help you?" "Other way around, I hope. How's the silk business coming along?" you ask cheerily. "We are making progress," he says cautiously. "Got any friends in academia?" Eltharin is the precursor to Classical, Tilea's academic language, so it's as studied there as much as Khazalid is in the Empire. He takes a moment to answer. "I know a few people, and those few people know a few more. Why?" "Round up anyone who knows Eltharin and is looking for work and set them up with the people you've got working on the silk. Here's every book on textiles the Wood Elves of Laurelorn have ever written. Consider yourself the first patron of the Kron-Azril-Ungol, the Library of Kvinn-Wyr." Francesco picks up one of the books and flips through its pages. "Wood Elves? Don't they kill all trespassers?" "Usually, yes. Let me know how it goes." You walk away, dusting off your hands with satisfaction. Furnishing the Project HQ had reminded you that Johann has silk sheets and you still don't. Hopefully this will solve that little problem. --- You next return to Laurelorn via Zhufbar, as they've completed the Gyrocarriage they've been working on in gratitude for your contribution to the Karag Dum Expedition and the safe return of most of its Steam-Wagons. This one has been built from the ground up for that purpose instead of being adapted from a Gyrobomber so it's merely loud and uncomfortable instead of deafening and painful. But it's not as freeing as it otherwise would be because of the question of piloting - though the pilots of Karak Eight Peaks are happy to donate their services to accumulate experience in the air, they'd not be willing to spend weeks or months in Laurelorn or Middenheim to be on hand at a whim. Scheduling your trips in advance isn't a problem - it's what you've been doing already - but it does mean you're not fully taking advantage of your new acquisition, and you toy with the idea of learning to pilot it yourself, possibly alongside one of your WEB-MAT colleagues. Johann is out for obvious reasons, but Max or Egrimm should be willing to learn. Also complete is the work on your Revolvers you'd sent over to the Runesmiths of Zhufbar, taking advantage of your good name among the Dwarves to improve your armament. It's something you've been considering for a while but haven't acted on until now. To the Dwarven perspective firearms are relatively new, especially to the extremely conservative Cult of Thungni, so what few Runesmiths have been willing to work on these newfangled contraptions have only adapted the most basic of Runes to a standard they're happy with. As alternatives you'd been considering either seeking out one of the few radicals amongst the Runesmiths to apply something more adventurous, or seeking an enchantment from the Colleges. But there's always so much to do and so many other ways to expend your influence that turning down an improvement you could get now in favour of something you might eventually get around to at some nebulous point in the future stopped making sense to you. At first glance your revolvers appear unchanged, but taking out the cylinder reveals two runes, a Rune of Fire on the firing mechanism and a Rune of Stone on the cylinder itself. The Rune of Fire ensures that the blackpowder will always catch and will burn hotter, faster and cleaner, allowing for more of its energy to be directed to the projectile itself instead of vented out the sides or left unburned, and the Rune of Stone ensures the cylinder is able to withstand the greater forces involved. Simple changes, but extremely well-tested ones, and they make for a projectile that hits harder and flies truer than it otherwise would. It will take you a bit of time to get used to the greater kickback, but the increase in stopping power will be well worth it. With your marvels of Zhufbar acquired, you turn your mind to the work ahead of you. Six months ago you were dropped into an alien society with a handful of ambitions and no solid direction on where to start pursuing them, but now you have a Runelord and a Grey Lord signed on and ready to begin. The three of you could work together to build a solid theoretical groundwork and give you an idea of where to begin in studying the Waystones, but anyone else you bring in might have an understanding of the Waystones that is incompatible with or far in advance of the model the three of you could create. Or on the other hand, they might not. That's the problem with everyone keeping secrets, you don't have the slightest idea how much information all the various organizations might have tucked up their sleeves. Once that groundwork is completed, the Project will no longer be seen as in its preparatory, recruitment phase. Once you start sending reports to the states and organizations involved, they'll start replying, hopefully with resources and information, but likely with expectations as well. You have five actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. For every two AP spent across all members of WEB-MAT, including recruiting new members, you can spend one 'free' additional AP with any member of WEB-MAT. WEB-MAT actions are performed by Mathilde alongside that person when possible, such as studying something alongside that person, cowriting a paper together, one teaching the other, both of them learning something new, et cetera. Current overwork status: [+] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. WEB-MAT: Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Use kitting out his workshop as a pretext to get to know House Miriel and the local Cult of Vaul. (NEW) [ ] MAX: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which two papers will be written. (NEW-ish) WEB-MAT: Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Train with and study the freshly-attached golden arm. (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, Light Wizard [ ] EGRIMM: Attempt to bring the Light Order into the Waystone Project (NEW) [ ] EGRIMM: Investigate what Alric is up to. (NEW) [ ] EGRIMM: Attempt a Windherder enchantment with Egrimm (specify what) (NEW) [ ] EGRIMM: Learning: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] EGRIMM: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Recruitment [ ] WEB-MAT: Attempt to recruit someone to WEB-MAT (specify who) The Waystone Project, Recruitment [ ] Attempt to bring an Order into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a non-Order magical tradition into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a human Cult into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (specify which) The Waystone Project, Research [ ] Personally scrutinize a Waystone as thoroughly as you possibly can. [ ] Lay the foundations: work with the current members of WEB-MAT and the Waystone Project to build a single unified framework for understanding the Waystones. In theory, the more members there currently are, the more complete this framework will be. Will unlock further investigations. Can be repeated if desired, but will not unlock anything new after the first time, it will just make a new framework incorporating any new recruits. Lovely Laurelorn [ ] Furnish the research spaces of the Waystone Project HQ (specify how much: 100gc for adequate, 500gc for College-grade, 600gc for Runelord-grade, 2000gc for Laurelorn-grade) (NEW-ish) [ ] Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Explore one of the Wards of Laurelorn (specify which: Storm, Rain, Frost) Self-Improvement: [ ] Receive training: specify who and what. (acquaintances may train you for free, or you can hire someone with money or favours) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Attempt to gain control of one of your Arcane Marks (specify which) [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. Aethyric Vitae (16 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item: specify what and how (current skill level allows for Fiendishly Complex spells and lower; you may use Windherder to attempt to enchant something with spells from different Winds) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to codify Rite of Way so that others can learn it. [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff (specify for whom) (optional: specify from what) Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in current affairs: specify what and how. Current examples: Sylvanian campaign, Marienburg affair, Black Waters project Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting or ingratiating yourself with someone else: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 200 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Expansion along the Aver EIC Handler: The Hochlander The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in your fief. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander investigate what Alric is up to. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Improve and expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (optional: specify how) [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. Kron-Azril-Ungol (NEW) Status: Under construction. The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] Seek official recognition of Kron-Azril-Ungol as an affiliated library of the Colleges of Magic This will allow you to start acquiring books on magical subjects from the Colleges of Magic for the Library. [ ] Seek the publishing contacts to start acquiring large amounts of books from a nearby realm (specify which: Bretonnia, Kislev, Tilea/Estalia, Araby) Gives wide and easy access within a language, but is subject to local restrictions and is a less efficient use of the Library's acquisition budget than other methods. [ ] Seek an exchange arrangement with another Library to be able to make copies of their corpus (specify which, eg: Great Library of Marienburg, Great Library of Altdorf, Ancient Library of Carroburg) Difficulty will depend on the size, prestige, and disposition of the library in question, and the relative impressiveness of Kron-Azril-Ungol. [ ] Seek an agreement with a Cult to have access to their libraries (specify which, eg: Verenans, Myrmidians, Sigmarites) Difficulty will vary heavily depending on the Cult in question, but can allow access to rare tomes and esoteric subjects. [ ] Set up a no-questions-asked bounty system for books within the Cult of Ranald Results will be unreliable and depending on what is sought may result in blowback, but this may allow you to acquire books that would otherwise be entirely inaccessible. Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Books and rubbings from an Asur explorer of Lustria and the Southlands Ghyran Nut Kurgan Shrine to Mannsleib Kurgan enchanted weapons Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghur (FADING) Windsoak Mushrooms - Hysh (FADING) Observations on the Windfall north of the Dark Lands (MOSTLY FADED) Observations on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes (MOSTLY FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ulgu (MOSTLY FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Aqshy(MOSTLY FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghyran (MOSTLY FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Azyr (MOSTLY FADED) Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (MOSTLY FADED) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition. (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual. (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae. (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. Windsoak Mushrooms (missing: Chamon, Shyish) The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a twelve hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - If there's an action that you think should be present and isn't already covered, please let me know. - I've tweaked a number of options to try to have less numerous and more flexible actions.

Turn 36 Results - 2487.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan: Slow and Steady Research with Double Recruitment -[*] MAX: Use kitting out his workshop as a pretext to get to know House Miriel and the local Cult of Vaul -[*] EGRIMM: Attempt to bring the Light Order into the Waystone Project -[*] JOHANN: Train with and study the freshly-attached golden arm -[*] Furnish the research spaces of the Waystone Project HQ (specify how much: 2000gc for Laurelorn-grade) -[*] Attempt to bring an organisation into the Waystone Project (The Jade Order) --[*] The Gambler: Attempt to bring the Jade Order into the Waystone Project -[*] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic -[*] EIC: Insert agents into Talabecland administration to start gathering their secrets -[*] Seek official recognition of Kron-Azril-Ungol as an affiliated library of the Colleges of Magic -[*] Write a paper: Observations on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes Tally One oft-debated topic in the Colleges is why Teclis had such a blind spot to the existence of Divine Magic, and one popular explanation is that Elves and humans worshipped the Gods in fundamentally different ways. The Asur, it is said, will worship a God primarily as an embodiment of the part of themself they were choosing to encourage, and the worship of them as an independent being they wish to attract the favour of is either secondary or completely absent. The problem with this theory is that it is largely unprovable, as the Elves of Ulthuan will refuse to answer questions on the matter, except for when they are able to answer in a completely ambiguous way that raises more questions than it answers. Even the question of whether the Asur believe their Gods actually literally exist or whether they believe them to be entirely metaphor is unknown, with some scholars going so far as to say that the Flame of Asuryan that the Phoenix King walks through when crowned is itself a metaphor for the trials of rulership that they are inevitably tested by. You had assumed that the Eonir would operate in much the same way, and you're still not entirely sure whether that's the case. To take the Queen's Champion, Kadoh, as an example, his authority derives from his showing at the festivals dedicated to Asuryan. Does that mean he demonstrated the attributes the Eonir believe to be most closely associated with Asuryan? Do they believe the festival itself is something the being called Asuryan subjectively approves of, and Kadoh inherits that approval as its winner? Or do they think Asuryan actively intervenes to ensure that the product of the festival is His personal favourite of the candidates? You're still not sure, but you are sure that if you outright asked, the answer you'd get would not at all clear up your confusion. The reason this matter is on your mind is that you are about to begin dealing with House Miriel, the House most closely associated with Vaul, and you're still not sure what that actually means, despite the amount of books you've managed to acquire and skim on the Great Houses. From what you've heard, they do seem to be inordinately predisposed towards artisanry, their economic fortunes are based on craftsmanship, and their influence derives in part from their presence in and influence over the priesthood of Vaul. Craft, business, faith. But you're reasonably sure that one of those things would be central to the character of House Miriel, and the other two would merely derive from it, but you don't know enough about Eonir beliefs to be able to know which it is. It is not at all difficult to arrange an audience with House Miriel. Every morning the Great Houses disgorge the segment of the population who had spent the night in their bunkhouses due to being unable or unwilling to pay for a roof over their head, and there's always a member of the House there to remind them whose beneficence sheltered them. Most file by quietly, some who wish to gain the attention of the house give the ritual phrases of thanks that are received in silence, and small gifts are given to those who are in the House's favour and instructions are given to those that wish to be. One morning you wait for the flow to ebb and slip through the doors into House Miriel's entrance hall, taking a moment to admire the decor. Every Great House keeps the public-facing decorations of their House in constant flux, and House Miriel currently favours a small forest of plinths, each holding a beautifully-crafted weapon of some sort - a reaction to recent trends, as the victory over the Beastmen and the possibility of war with Nordland is still fresh in the Eonir mind. Each stands eerily upright, and you can't tell if it's through perfect balance or clever artifice. "Loremaster Weber of the Empire," announces a servant whose job it should have been to notice you much earlier. With a sudden jerk the figure that had been starting to relax from having seen to the morning's duties jerks upright and gives you a rather alarmed look. "Friend Loremaster," says the girl, whose lanky figure would suggest someone in their teens on a human, but on an Elf could signify anywhere from around the same to a decade your senior. "How may House Miriel benefit you?" "I seek to construct as fine a workshop and laboratory as mortal hands can produce," you reply. "In Tor Lithanel, all indications are that House Miriel are the ones to speak to if I am to fulfill that ambition." "You have the truth of it," the girl replies, trying not to smile at the flattery. "And for such an honoured guest, greater than I would be needed to fulfill it. Please excuse my absence as I seek them." With as much of a run that can be achieved while preserving dignity, the girl disappears into the rest of the structure. You make your way through the maze of plinths, trying to spot the trick that keeps them all upright. You'd ruled out cantrips and hidden filaments by the time the girl returns. "This way, if you please," she says, and leads you deeper into the House of Miriel, through corridors crowded with jumbles of ancient treasures. As she pushes open a door the rasp of metal on wood emerges, and you blink in the sudden light as you enter into a well-lit workshop filled with a sharp smell of freshly-worked wood. In the center of the room sits a tall, slender Elf with a lined face and fingers stained a deep crimson, pulling a drawknife along a stave. "Forgive me for not greeting you in the manner of your kind," he says, glancing up from the bow. "The blood of the yew is quite toxic to those not accustomed to it. I am Councillor Galrith of Miriel." "A pleasure to meet you," you reply. "I am Lady Magister Mathilde Weber of the Grey Order." "You wield the Wind of Shadow, I am told," he says as he works. "Much like I hear my distant kin in Ulthuan do, though my ancestors left them when the land was still whole. There is, I feel, more honour in doing what is necessary but not praised, than what is celebrated in story and song." He taps the stave while glancing up at you wryly. "The great hunter gets a canto, the bowyer but a stanza, and the fletcher not a line. And now you want to form your own legend that our labour will make possible." "Elven artisanry is legendary, and among the Eonir it is known that House Miriel dominate the production of the finest-quality works. I do not intend to fail due to substandard equipment, so I came to you." He looks up at you thoughtfully. "You twist words like my children. Perhaps that is what the other Houses see in your kind. But though I will accede to the collective will of the High Council, I will not bleed my own House dry to fund your ambitions. You will pay for our services, as all must." "Would you prefer the coin of the Empire or Dwarven ingots?" "Ingots. As your kind is so aware, many of our hills are rich in silver and gold, but it is needed where it is." --- Once you settle the details of your arrangement with the patriarch of House Miriel, the matter is handed over to his eldest child Laurelin, who you recognize as the girl who you met in the entranceway. Underneath the formality she seems more friendly and curious towards you than her father was, and to both of your surprise you learn she is three years your elder. You're as horrified at the thought of a decades-long adolescence as she is at the thought of being halfway finished with her alotted lifespan at a mere forty, and on that foundation of mutual pity you build something of an understanding of her and her House. As you come to understand it, the central belief of House Miriel is that every single Elf has within them the potential to be truly masterful at a craft, and their purpose is to locate and cultivate that potential within each member of their family. It's a sentiment that strikes you first as rather sweet, second as rather selfish, then third as worryingly compatible with isolationist or supremacist viewpoints. You also gain an understanding of why House Miriel is opposed to cooperation with Middenheim, where genuine doubt about the unreliability of humans is bolstered by concern for their carefully-guarded pride. House Miriel is renowned for their craftsmanship among the Eonir, but will that still be the case if the economy of Tor Lithanel is joined, however tenuously, with that of Ulthuan? What will it do to their reputation if goods from the forges of Caledor, the workshops of Tiranoc, the jewellers of Eataine, begin to trickle in via Marienburg, or possibly by direct trade via the Schaukel? Not the noblest of motivations, but not an uncommon one, either. A similar dynamic plays out fairly often when human craft guilds find themselves competing with imported Dwarven goods. Big fish in small ponds have a habit of getting quite concerned about a sudden connection to the ocean. But despite all that, they are willing to go along with the majority vote, and to do business with yourself at rates no worse than those available to any citizen of Tor Lithanel. If this is the worst of the attitudes of those amongst the isolationist bloc, then there's reason to be optimistic of the future of relationships between the Empire and Laurelorn. Alongside that understanding, you equip the headquarters of the Waystone Project with the finest equipment money can buy in Tor Lithanel. There is glasswork of every size and type, made of a variety of glasses, including some apparently formed from clear crystal. There are ceramic alternatives for when the contents must be kept away from light. There are contraptions of incredibly delicate lenses to aid the eye to observe both the miniscule and the distant. There are multiple sets of alchemical equipment in glass, stone, ceramic, copper, and steel. There are modular runic arrays and stencils for the quick and easy construction of the various kinds of magic circles, and a stunning variey of resonant materials to reinforce them. There is a veritable armoury of ritual knives, daggers, sickles, and hammers of every magically resonant material imaginable, and a second of more mundane tools made of materials chosen for a complete lack of resonance. And not least of all is a smithy the equal of any in the Empire that Max is entirely rapt with, which presents a problem to your plans to use it as a pretext for further investigation. After a great deal of prodding he is finally able to find something to complain about, and you prod him further until you have a set of incredibly exact specifications. Your plan is to make something so complicated that nobody who isn't deeply immersed in the art of metalworking can hope to understanding it, so that you will need to take Max directly to the artisans in question - the Smith-Priests of Vaul - and thus gain better insight into them. While this proves to be impossible, Laurelin's explanations for why that is are as enlightening as you could have hoped for. Laurelorn's Smith-Priests labour in the tunnels and caverns below the Rainbow Falls, where the magic in the waters from the Tarn of Tears flows through after being shattered upon the rocks of the falls. To even enter them takes a great deal of training to allow an utterly neutral mindset, or else part of the flowing Winds will be drawn to that person's soul and cause turbulence that can quickly grow into a vortex of Dhar. Part of that preparation is the ritual blinding common to Priests of Vaul, and the time spent in such close proximity to the constant tumult of the falls as they wield the Winds to bend mundane materials to their will renders these craftsmen as deaf as they are blind, only able to communicate with other members of the Cult of Vaul through methods protected as holy secrets. This creates a virtually unassailable monopoly on craftsmanship, as these artisans communicate only with their correligionists, which is under the unofficial but almost total control of House Miriel. An unexpected upshot of these discoveries is that Max is thrilled to learn that the magical artisanry that he has been pursuing is possible, and far from being discouraged that those that have mastered it are unwilling to share it, he is glad that they are extremely unlikely to share it with anyone among the Colleges, leaving the field clear for him to invent and claim the credit for Chamon-based smithing. That's an unusual point of view, but you suppose he's done more than enough to earn the right to a little eccentricity. --- With the help of yourself and a sort of gauntlet Max made to cover the new arm's dangerously sharp claws, Johann has been working to gain an understanding of his new arm. For quite some time it simply hung limp, swaying with his movements. But Magesight reveals activity just under the surface, with a tendril of Hysh from the arm probing around and releasing small trickles of what Egrimm identifies as healing energies into the socket it finds itself in. Throughout it all Johann seems quite cheery, enthusiastically recounting every errant twitch of the fingers of his new arm. He is, you remind yourself, a wielder of the Wind of Metal and an enthusiastic pursuer of ritual gilding, and thus it makes sense that he would resonate at least as strongly with a prosthetic embodiment of practicality and permanence as he did with his own flesh and blood. Over time the twitches become more pronounced and his fingers begin to flex slightly when he isn't paying attention, but your own observations are more taken with how the tendril of Hysh that seems to be healing and examining the socket it has been implanted into withdraws quite obligingly whenever Johann channels Chamon, allowing him to perform his spells without trouble, and the few times he's unthinkingly tried to send magic through his left arm out of habit the magic has simply rebounded off the metal, indicating either some sort of advanced insulation worked into the metal or a very high density of stored Hysh. You're becoming more and more curious of the inner workings of the arm, and take copious notes of what you can observe in the hopes you might be able to incorporate something similar into some of your future enchanting projects. If part of you had begun to hope that Johann ultimately rejects the arm and returns it to your laboratory for further study, those hopes are dashed one morning when Johann's complaints of phantom sensations up and down his missing arm culminate in a spasm of surprise and pain as Hysh pulses through the prosthetic, revealing an intricate tracework of runic patterns that you try fruitlessly to memorize in the fraction of a second they are visible for. When it fades, Johann has already begun to lift his metal arm, his fingers wriggling and flexing as they begin to respond to impulses that had previously been dashing themselves fruitlessly against severed nerve endings. "Huh," Johann says, and that about summarizes it. It still takes Johann quite some time to adapt, as even though the new arm is responding much the same as if it was his old one, it still differs in length, strength, range of motion, and dozens of other small ways that combine to turn the usually-nimble Johann rather clumsy. The claws prove much stronger than his gilded fist, and Max has to produce several more gauntlets of even stronger designs after Johann accidentally mangles the first few, the golden claws slicing themselves free of their steel sheaths. Tests of exactly how much strength the arm is capable of are discontinued after he badly strains his still-ungilded shoulder muscles, proving that whatever the ceiling of his new strength is, it's higher than the portion of his body that remains merely flesh and blood - though it might not be if he continues the gradual gilding of his torso, he muses aloud one day. Your continued monitoring picks up that the arm has begun to draw in wisps of ambient Hysh through the palm, and comparing the approximate amount drawn in to the activity he is engaged in indicates that the arm draws in more energy after particularly intricate work, but not, interestingly, after work that required an expenditure of strength. Is the Hysh only needed to control the arm, and some other power source is drawn on for the actual movements? Or is controlling more taxing on Hysh than raw strength? Egrimm ventures that the arm might have some mechanism to convert Winds to raw mechanical power in a similar manner to Runecraft, allowing greater efficiency for movement but still requiring the use of raw Hysh for control. It sounds plausible, but with the inner workings of the arms still concealed it's simply one theory among many at this point. The final major question centres on the palm, as the size and location of the raised circle leads you to believe that it is not simply an input. If it only needed to draw in small wisps of ambient Hysh it could have been located anywhere and could have been much smaller. It being on the palm leads you to believe that being able to control where the output is pointing is important, which is why you theorize that it is some sort of weapon. Johann spends a great deal of time in a borrowed firing range pointing his new arm in the direction of the buttes as he tries to prod the arm into doing something. Everything else he has asked of the arm used the same impulses as his original appendage, but now he is trying the equivalent of flexing a muscle he's never had. It's a long and frustrating process, and you were well into questioning your original theory when the first sputters of light finally start to emerge from Johann's palm. It doesn't take him long to be able to exert control over this new impulse, and soon enough he has a beam of light emerging from his arm, which might be somewhat useful if it weren't for his blindness to it. But neither you nor he believe that the only purpose of that mechanism is to save a few coppers on candles, so day after day you return to the field as he contorts his mind around the one mental impulse that seems to work, seeking some sort of neighbour to it that will have a different or stronger effect. And finally one day he achieves it, causing you to drop your book in surprise as Hysh flares and a beam of light slams into the butte, sending soil and burning grass flying. "Huh," Johann says again. Egrimm identifies the effect as being fundamentally the same effect as that known to the Light Order as Shem's Burning Gaze, and further experimentation shows that Johann can only use it twice in succession without affecting the use of his arm, or thrice if he's okay with his arm hanging limp until it absorbs enough ambient Hysh to revive itself. Overall it's as good a result as Johann could have hoped for, but you find yourself slightly frustrated that its inner workings remain completely concealed from you. You have only the slightest idea where one would even begin to create an enchantment able to interface directly with a living body like that, and that it's capable of both precision and power indicates to you that whoever built it must have been incredibly skilled, or had access to a great deal more accumulated knowledge than the Colleges do. Frowning to yourself, you finish writing up your notes on what little information you were able to glean from your observations, hoping you'll be able to make use of at least part of it at some point in the future. - There's less to this update than I wanted there to be, but I'm going to be away from my computer for the next day or so, so here's what I've got so far.

Turn 36 Results - 2487.5 - Part 2 - Truth and Faith

Spoiler: Unfinished business -[*] EGRIMM: Attempt to bring the Light Order into the Waystone Project -[*] Attempt to bring an organisation into the Waystone Project (The Jade Order) --[*] The Gambler: Attempt to bring the Jade Order into the Waystone Project -[*] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic -[*] EIC: Insert agents into Talabecland administration to start gathering their secrets -[*] Seek official recognition of Kron-Azril-Ungol as an affiliated library of the Colleges of Magic -[*] Write a paper: Observations on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes It does occur to you that setting aside several weeks for the experiment you have in mind with the Aethyric Vitae might be considered overkill. The actual methodology of the experiment would take but a few seconds to perform, after all. But you are no petty Magicker or Elementalist to expose an irreplaceable artefact to a poorly-understood substance as casually as one adds seasoning to a meal. You will do as much research as possible first to identify what might go wrong and prepare accordingly, and just because you're unlikely to find much in the texts you possess due to Cult secrecy is no reason not to bother. And the results of the test will need proper recording, and a successful test will likely suggest follow-up tests and an unsuccessful one will need examining and correcting, and if you didn't have the time set aside to do so it would linger in the back of your mind, distracting you from whatever else you would be trying to do with that time. You've told yourself variations on that quite a few times over the years, as your curiosity warred with your caution and an insidious part of your mind insisted that you could perform a full suite of tests with every material imaginable within a few hours if you put aside proper methodology. But now, with research completed, calendar consulted, portents acknowledged, Morrsleib waning and your laboratory prepared, it is finally time to drip a single drop of Aethyric Vitae onto the Coin that Ranald gifted you after your encounter with the Cult of Only-Gork. If you had to guess, you'd say that the most likely result would be the Vitae unravelling into Winds as you've seen it do before, or otherwise completely fail to react to the Coin. A speculative positive result would be the Vitae being channelled through the Coin to Ranald, ideally in a way that would empower Him, though it may have as little effect as a drop of rain onto a fish in an ocean. The possible result you're most concerned about is that it does that in a way that leaves a path between the two open, creating a portal between the material world and the Aethyr. If temporary, such a result would still be very dangerous if the pathway proved accessible to Daemons, and if not, could still be very much to the detriment of the surrounding area. If permanent... well, you're pretty sure it couldn't be permanent. If it was that easy to punch permanent holes through the fabric of reality, there wouldn't be any of it left by now, not with all the ignorant amateurs and all-too-knowledgeable Chaos cultists running around the place. With trepidation firmly tamped down, you release a single drop of Vitae onto a stirring rod, and as it runs down the rod towards the Coin you fall back to the far side of the room. You watch as best you can from a distance as the Vitae impacts, and with a flash of energies it evaporates into nothingness. You frown as you peer at the Coin, then carefully approach and scrutinize it for any changes. Once it passes muster, you pick it up and rotate it in your fingers, counting its four faces. Then you place it back in position. Once you fetch another drop of Vitae, you set up the experiment again, this time observing from much closer, and the drop of Vitae evaporates before your eyes again. This time you can confirm that the unravelling of it seems superficially similar to that of its transformation into Winds that you're quite familiar with, though with less kinetic energy involved, but you can't see anything it transformed into. Was it sublimated into the Aethyr? Or is the sample size just too small for you to spot? Travelling all the way through your living quarters to fetch more of the Vitae is annoying, but you resist the urge to bring up an entire keg of the stuff, only bringing a phial's worth this time. With more of the Vitae involved you reverse the experiment, dribbling the Vitae into a watch glass and gently lowering the Coin to make contact with it by means of a long string through an overhead tackle. Again the Vitae evaporates, but in a gentler and more gradual manner radiating out from where the Coin had contacted the puddle than the swift deflagration of the Winds transformation. But again, you can't see- Ranald is watching. You resist the urge to try to hide the evidence like you were still an Apprentice and had just been walked in on while reading an unexpectedly spicy chapter of The Spokes of Altdorf, and instead exhale and examine that sudden assumption that had arrived fully-formed in your conscious mind. Ranald, you know, is often watching, and often your only indication of it is a series of coincidences that makes His will known. You only ever know for certain when He's watching when He wants you to know, and He announces His presence with the sudden presence of His divine energy. But with your eyes on a not-quite-Winds transformation caused by exposure to a divine artefact, you're wondering if you may have replicated that effect without His personal involvement. And if that's the case, of course you wouldn't be able to see the transformation - looking for a tiny amount of freshly-created Divine energy against the backdrop of a Divine artefact would be like looking for a candleflame next to a forge. You press the activation Rune that opens the flushing mechanism intended to disperse the Winds, and while the feeling doesn't disappear, it does begin to ease, you presume as background amounts of Divine energy diffuse through the openings. Once the feeling of Ranald's presence has fully faded, you run through the experiment again with another phial of Vitae, and once more the sense of Ranald's presence suddenly waxes and then gradually wanes. While it's not impossible that Ranald is deliberately leaking His energy in at just the right time to mislead you, you feel like that would not fit His character - He does like to play games, but they're games with a purpose. In the past He's been very clear when your experimentation crossed a line, so He wouldn't follow that up by throwing off your experiments if you had done so again. Displeased Gods are not what you might call subtle. So assuming that Ranald is not actively intervening in the experiment, the result shows that when exposed to Divine energies, the Vitae transforms into more Divine energy in a way similar, but not identical, to the Winds transformation. It also appears to be a complete transformation, as instead of splitting into a number of different energies it completely and cleanly transforms. That does make sense to you. If the Vitae is the compressed matter of the realm in which the Gods reside, it would... submit to the presence of a God? Perhaps that is ascribing too much agency to the Vitae. Perhaps it 'submits' to the God only in the same way that air 'submits' to your lungs. It's a solid hypothesis, now you simply need to prove it. How does one confirm the presence of divine energy? You could use enough volume for it to be visible, but that could cost you a fair bit of Vitae. Can you confirm it with the current amounts? Well, you'd need to remove the Coin, and for that you need the Divine energy to not dissipate for a while. So, a storage and stabilization medium. You have that on hand, actually - the same sort of crystals used to store aethyric signatures for the Eye of Gazul, except these are of Eonir make, as you'd appropriated a few from the WEB-MAT facilities for your own personal laboratories. So they should be quite able to stand up to the much higher energy density this would involve. Then you simply separate the crystal from the Coin and inspect it at your leisure - there'd be no rush, as the crystal would preserve the energy indefinitely. You're halfway through setting up the experiment when the implications of that occur to you, and you freeze for a moment before forcefully returning your focus to the matter at hand. You do not freak out over hypotheticals, it's a waste of perfectly good gibbering. Once more the shimmering fluid fills the watch glass, and this time you lower a perfectly-formed shard of crystal into it, waiting a moment for the Vitae to settle and ensuring that the two don't react. Then once more you lower the Coin into the Vitae, and once more it ripples into nothingness as the sense of Ranald's presence returns. You reopen the vents as you remove the Coin from the string, carefully inspect it to make sure it remains unchanged, then take it downstairs to place in Wolf's watchful care, and give him a few pats for good measure to centre yourself before returning to the laboratory. And when you do, the sense of Ranald's presence is gone once more, but within the crystal is a wisp of frozen energy. At first it seems like no more than a flicker of light, but as your Windsight adjusts to the lack of other energies it grows in your mind and blooms into a seemingly endless tapestry of recursive complexity, interwoven with colours no mortal language has words for. It is beautiful, but it is beautiful like a butterfly pinned to a board is beautiful. Perhaps that is why Ranald warned you so harshly about inspecting Him - if this tiny fragment of Him is so impossibly intricate, what mortal mind could withstand witnessing the entirety? The longer you look, the more sure you are that there is nothing in all of reality and unreality that could look exactly like this, and though you have no names or concepts for any of it, it all somehow reminds you of the many facets of your oldest friend. This is, in your hand, the fingerprint of a God. The replicable, comparable, definitive fingerprint of a God. This is divine energy that has never directly touched the divinity whose nature it echoes. The Gods can turn Their attention in unfathomably large numbers of directions at once, but it is generally agreed That they cannot see all things at all times - They are great, but not infinite. With no reason for Him to be watching you at this time, it may be that Ranald does not even realize what you have. It may be that the same would apply if you did the same with other artefacts. Almost against your will, various plans unfold in your mind. Plans like: the Sacred Flame of Ulric is accessible to the public, and it is not uncommon for people to light their own fires off of it. It would be trivial to bundle a phial of Vitae and a crystal inside an oil lamp, and then appear to light it from the Sacred Flame. Then walk away, with Ulric's fingerprint alongside Ranald's in your collection. Similar plans in dozens of other places - the Great Cathedral of Sigmar, the Taalwelt, the Black Sepulchre, the High Temple of Manann... You remember the Cult of Karnos, and your puzzling over their almost-Elven Runes. You remember conversations with Asarnil and Deathfang, about Taal and Kurnous and Isha and Rhya. You remember Cython drawing lines between the Classical Gods and the Cadai. You remember the strange sense of familiarity you got from the cobra sigil of a Nehekharan God. You remember that your ignorance in these matters is not because the Gods have simply not gotten around to revealing the truth of the matter. You roll the crystal in your hand. Doing this once is curiosity and ignorance. But doing it again? That would be a declaration of war against the secrecy of the Gods and the Cults. One they might not realize you have made, but if they ever do... But they might not, not if you're clever and careful. And through collection and careful study you might be able to achieve an understanding of the Gods that perhaps only They can currently boast. You sit in your laboratory, stare at the crystal, and think. [ ] Truth Prepare a secure container to store the crystal in, with room for many more to come. [ ] Faith Sacrifice the crystal to Ranald in an act of dedication to Him. [ ] Prudence Break the crystal, burn your notes, and never again allow the Vitae to touch the Divine. - There will be a four hour moratorium. - The result of this vote should be considered permanent.

Turn 36 Results - 2487.5 - Part 3 - Faith

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Faith Tally You stare at the crystal in your hand for what feels like days, internally debating the matter. The intriguing nature of the recursive facets makes part of you itch for a larger sample size so you can start drawing conclusions about what the patterns mean. But another part of you keeps seeing something you almost recognize in the facets, as it matches your oldest friend in every respect except for that it is eerily frozen and inert. On another level you look at the scale of the responsibilities you've already taken on and fret at where you might find the time to pursue another avenue of research, which wars against the possible benefits to the Empire of being better able to sniff out dark Gods under false guises. Eventually a conclusion begins to emerge from the almost perfect balance of forces in your mind, and as it crystallizes it grow layers of justifications. You are one person. You only have so many hours in the day and days in the week. Spreading yourself even thinner than you already are jeopardizes all you are already doing, and threatens to do so even more if your ambitions are discovered. Cython may have the luxury of spending millennia pursuing the most ambitious puzzles for their own sake, but you are not Cython. You are, by your own choices, bound to the Empire, to the Colleges, to the Karaz Ankor... and to Ranald. You feel pangs of regret as you make your way downstairs towards the shrine, but not enough to halt your steps, nor enough to stop you from picking up a rock hammer from the workshop on the way. If things had been just slightly different, if you had slightly less irons in the fire already, if you had slightly more resources, if you had come across this in a way that didn't inescapably drag Ranald Himself into the study... perhaps, perhaps, perhaps. Well, it's not the first regret you've ever had blossom inside you and is far from the largest, so you force it down with ease of practice and your steps grow surer as you approach Ranald's shrine, and you find yourself smiling as you enter it. The choughs are currently in the middle of their breeding season, but where once they would have been concerned and defensive they simply crane their heads to see if you've brought anything for them to eat. Some of the choughs laying their first clutch this season hatched in this very shrine, and they've long since grown accustomed to your comings and goings. There are rituals and supplications for this sort of thing, but you've never really been one for them. You sit cross-legged on the bare stone floor, place the crystal on the ground, and line up the rock hammer with the crystal while giving a mental nudge in the direction of your connection to Him. Then you swing, and shards and energies skitter across the stone in a tinkling chorus as the choughs squawk and give you reproachful looks. But something else slips into those looks, and more of the birds appear from sheltered nooks as their eyes fix on the crystalline shining. One by one they hop down, and the boldest pecks cautiously at a fragment, and emboldened by its lack of response, plucks it from the ground and returns triumphantly to its nest with its shiny prize. The others follow suit in a flapping crowd, and within moments the ground is picked entirely clean and left bare again. All that remains is the mark of the impact on the stone and you're not at all surprised to see that it forms an X. But then you frown and lean a little closer. It looks like an X at first glance, but it's bisected horizontally, leaving a line of unmarked stone between the V above and the chevron below. You run your fingers over the shape and as you do you feel the Coin around your neck grow warm against your skin, and when you pull it out you find the same shape on the first face you see. You rotate it through and find that this is a new fifth side of your Coin, which is all well and good, but what does it mean? You scrutinize both Coin and the mark on the ground, but both refuse to give any further insight. So you sigh, stand to leave, and then freeze as you turn towards the door and catch sight of the painting of Ranald and Shallya, because now among the picnicking couple and Their twin flocks of crows and doves are two small girls, one who heavily resembles Her father with a hint of Her mother, and the other Her mother with a hint of Her father. And you feel a smile spreading across your face. From one perspective you sacrificed answers to your God, and in doing so received more questions. But from another, Ranald has followed the example of Heidi and Wilhelmina by introducing you, His friend, to His offspring. Though He has done so while remaining faithful to his usual mien, and you're certain a corner of your mind will be speculating about Their actual identities for quite some time. [New face of the Coin - The Father: Ranald's daughters, and Their followers, will recognize you as being worthy of trust and faith.]

Turn 36 Results - 2487.5 - Part 4

Spoiler: Unfinished business -[*] EGRIMM: Attempt to bring the Light Order into the Waystone Project -[*] Attempt to bring an organisation into the Waystone Project (The Jade Order) --[*] The Gambler: Attempt to bring the Jade Order into the Waystone Project -[*] EIC: Insert agents into Talabecland administration to start gathering their secrets -[*] Seek official recognition of Kron-Azril-Ungol as an affiliated library of the Colleges of Magic -[*] Write a paper: Observations on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes Altdorf's Southbank is one of the most wealthy and prestigious neighbourhoods in Altdorf, and it is one engaged in a very slow and genteel war where the ancient and somewhat crumbling abodes of many old-money families are being encroached upon by the relentless spread of upper-class commercial interests catering to wealthy and influential visitors to Altdorf. In this the old money have found a rather unusual advantage, as the unseen presence of the Light College on the western edge of the Southbank distorts the streets nearest it to an even greater extent than the rest of Altdorf, rendering it all but impossible to navigate to those unfamiliar with it. Here has formed the heartland of families of aged but diminished fortunes, who cling all the tighter to a status they can no longer afford to maintain and so rely on an abode within a supernatural maze to deter creditors and developers. Nestled within this odd neighbourhood is an equally odd tearoom, supplying exotic beverages at affordable prices to those who wish to be seen drinking them, who will staunchly refuse to acknowledge the middling quality of the drinks or the counterfeit crockery they are served in. The courtyard outside it is laid out in a triangular pattern radiating out from a central point, and most of its visitors would take the neatness of this pattern as a sign of how upmarket the business is pretending to be. It may be that nobody working here realizes why they feel so compelled to correct even the slightest crookedness in the layout, as they would lack the senses to perceive the immaterial Waystone in the middle of the pattern, and would be equally blind to the currents of Hysh being drawn in from the radiant sunlight and eddying unnervingly around misplaced furniture. All they would know is the subtle wrongness they would feel, and would correct it without ever knowing the source of that sensation. In a shaded corner of this spiralling pattern sits the Magister Matriarch of the Light Order in all but name, and that two of the tables nearest to her are also in use despite others being available indicates a level of comfort around Wizards that is rare even in Altdorf. Also indicative is that you are meeting her here at all, in a public place quite close to her campus. No more must Lady Magister Mira lurk in the Tempelgarten twilight for her meetings, now she takes tea in clear view of the public with her allies. "Lady Magister," she greets as you approach, and instead of being surreptitiously side-eyed by the others, they openly and politely look over for long enough to acknowledge your presence, as seeing and being seen is as much a purpose of this place as the tea is. "Lady Magister," you reply, taking a seat across from her. "How fares your Order?" "More so every day," she says with a pleased smile. "The longer Alric prods at the dark corners of the world for some evil to expunge, the greater an evil it would take him to restore himself to glory." You nod. "Thank you for agreeing to meet with me." "Not at all, it's always a delight to meet with such a rising star, especially one who is taking such good care of our Egrimm. He seems more himself now than I've ever seen him. How can we help you?" "I wish to bring the Light Order into the Project formally." "More so than we already are?" You glance at the nearest tables. "Teclis did not start from scratch," you say in Lingua Praestantia. "Nor should we." She nods. "Dietlinde!" she calls out, and a young woman in an apron hurries over. "Is the back room free?" "Yes, Lady. Shall I have it readied for you?" "Please. Tea, Lady Magister?" "Blue, if they have it." "Dark for me, water for my guest." --- "You've been getting yours from Tileans, I take it?" You nod as Mira leads you into the back room. "The variety of tea the Tileans call 'blue', the Cathayans call 'water'. Of course, most Imperial tea-drinkers who have adopted that style of naming teas don't realize it's based on the Cathayan understanding of the Winds." You close the door with a click behind you. "Now, let's talk business." "We can speak freely here?" "Of course. The back room of an upmarket Altdorf teahouse is sacrosanct." "Very well." You take a sip of the tea that had been waiting for you, and find it quite similar to what you've grown accustomed to in Eight Peaks, though the taste is somewhat duller than you're used to. "The Dwarves and the Elves are coming into this Project with millennia of accumulated knowledge. For this Project to work, we must do the same." "Dear Teclis was not exactly forthcoming with information on the Waystones, even to his favourite pupils." "If the Light Order wanted to pretend they were all autodidacts in the style of Volans, it should have chosen a less exotic building style. I aim to sit us at a table where Hoeth and Thungni already have seats. We must meet their antes with our own, and ours have lineages to match theirs. Let us bring Tahoth Trisheros to the table." Egrimm had been either unable or unwilling to uncover more for you than that name, but as Mira narrows her eyes at you over her cup of tea, it seems that it had struck home. "You ask much," she eventually says. You frown. "I ask on behalf of the world." "You misunderstand. I do not question the price, I question the wisdom of paying it." She swirls her remaining tea. "Anything we might achieve would be useless if it is subsequently squandered by a resurgent Alric. There are few Light Wizards who can be fully trusted with the information required, and those who are aligned with me are already busy keeping the Order in order, and those that are neutral would require swaying." You suppress a sigh, and nod as you see where she's going with this. "So you would need external assistance to be able to freely rally the resources I ask for." She nods, and you take a breath as you ready yourself for the negotiations. Contributions: [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann (free) If nothing else, Mira would allow Egrimm access to some of the inherited secrets of the Order of Light on the weight of Mathilde's deeds and reputation alone. [ ] Lord Magister Egrimm van Horstmann (1 Favour) With your vouching for him, Mira would be willing to fast-track Egrimm for promotion and clear him for even more information on the subject. [ ] Choirmaster Stephen (2 Favours) Many Light Wizards can lead a choir, but very few can lead them for the weeks at a time it takes for the most potent of enchantments. [ ] Lady Magister Elrisse (2 Favours) The Porter equivalent of the Light Order, Lady Magister Elrisse's loyalty to the Order and to the Empire is unimpeachable, and she is cleared for more access to information than any other living Light Wizard. [ ] Lady Magister Mira (4 Favours) The personal attention of the acting Magister Matriarch of the Light Order would be quite a coup even before you consider her impressive knowledge and capabilities. Favours: [ ] Denounce Alric (1 Favour) Getting openly involved in an internal matter of the Light Order might have consequences down the line, but a respected Grey Wizard casting doubt on his loyalties could sway many. [ ] Investigate Alric (2 Favours) Promise to personally investigate what Alric is up to in Talabecland, and to inform Mira of all the details. [ ] Sabotage Alric (2 Favours) Promise to indirectly interfere with whatever it is Alric is up to. Can be stacked with Investigate Alric. [ ] Introduction to the Order of Guardians (1 Favour) The Order of Guardians has millennia of experience against the dark forces of the world, but are usually unwilling to share what they know. Making an introduction between Mira and Gunnars could give the Light Order a foot in the door. [ ] Permanent access to KAU (1 Favour) Grant permanent copying permissions to much of your future Library. While this won't directly cost you anything, it will make it rather difficult to renegotiate a more reciprocal arrangement with the Light Order and their Ancient Library in the future. - There will be a 24-hour moratorium, since I'll be away from my computer for about that long. Voting will be in plan format. - If you have other ideas for Light Wizards to recruit, or other favours with which to recruit them, feel free to bring them up. 'The Light Wizard who knows the most about X' is a valid sort of Wizard to seek - Mathilde does not know the entire Light Order by name. You can recruit multiple contributing Light Wizards. - My original plan was to post this alongside the rest of the turn being resolved, but I went down a number of false starts with this and the Jade equivalent and at this point I just want to get something posted.

Turn 36 Results - 2487.5 - Part 5

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan Measured Support -[*] Lord Magister Egrimm van Horstmann (1 Favour) -[*] Lady Magister Elrisse (2 Favours) -[*] Investigate Alric (2 Favours) -[*] Introduction to the Order of Guardians (1 Favour) Vote tally Unfinished business: -[*] Attempt to bring an organisation into the Waystone Project (The Jade Order) --[*] The Gambler: Attempt to bring the Jade Order into the Waystone Project -[*] EIC: Insert agents into Talabecland administration to start gathering their secrets -[*] Seek official recognition of Kron-Azril-Ungol as an affiliated library of the Colleges of Magic -[*] Write a paper: Observations on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes After a fair bit of genteel haggling you reach an agreement with Lady Magister Mira: Lady Magister Elrisse will join the Waystone Project and Egrimm will be fast-tracked for promotion to Lord Magister, and in exchange you'll personally investigate what Alric is up to in Talabecland and organize an introduction between Elrisse and Gunnars. In the process you casually mention that you have agents in Talabecland who would be able to point you in the right direction, without mentioning that this is a new development based in part on your already-existing intention to keep an eye on what Alric is up to, instead framing it as a simple matter of fact that a Grey Wizard leaves fully-formed spy cells in their wake. You shake hands with the possibly soon-to-be Magister Matriarch of the Order of Light, finish your tea, and head back out into the city. --- Having promised yourself to an investigation of Alric, your infiltration of Talabecland has become rather more important than you originally expected, and you turn your full attention to the reports that have been coming in from those who had been able to work their ways into the social circles of Talabecland's administrators, and then forwarded to the Altdorf branch of the EIC for you to collect while you were in the area. Alric's presence in Talabecland is an open secret among them, and his latest doings are very frequently the subject of gossip and rumours that all make their way back to the Hochlander and onwards to you. It becomes quickly clear that Alric seems to have involved himself in the doings of one of Talabecland's most prominent noble families, the Unfähigers, once the most powerful dynasty in the Empire but quite fallen from grace in modern times after the disastrous rule of Emperor Dieter IV Unfähiger. For a moment you have a moment of giddy shock at the idea that Alric might be plotting with them to return them to power, but as you go deeper into the reported rumours it becomes clear that the Unfähigers are in no position to be making any attempt of the sort, as several prominent members of the family have died in mysterious circumstances in recent years, all of which are surrounded by contradictory but universally brutal rumours. It's exactly the sort of thing Alric has been searching for: something suitably dramatic for him to uncover, defeat, and cover himself in glory from. The benefactors could be better chosen, but you suppose after being countered in Wissenland and Stirland he might not be too choosy, and at the end of the day nobles of the Empire aren't supposed to be brutally murdered. You take careful notes and start to consider how best to start prodding at the mystery yourself. You also go through the rest of your messages from the EIC while you're at it, frowning at the increased volume of messages concerning some sort of trouble brewing in Ostermark while still maintaining the complete dearth of useful information. Everything else appears to be business as usual, with the output of the blackpowder factory in Wurtbad steadily increasing as the workers grow used to the process. There is, however, a build-up of activity in Sylvania, possibly hinting at a resumption of active warfare in the coming year after such a very long siege. An uptick in traffic through Barak Varr, apparently as a result of more infighting than usual among the pirates of Sartosa. And rumours of unrest between Marienburg and Couronne, possible a reignition of the eternal question of where, exactly, the border between Couronne and the Wasteland can be found. While you're in Altdorf and dealing with paperwork anyway, you also see to pursuing official recognition of Kron-Azril-Ungol as an affiliated library of the Colleges of Magic. While technically any collection of books owned by a Wizard could be considered such, official recognition comes with various rights and responsibilities. Most notably for your purposes, the acquisition of books on restricted magical topics is currently limited to ones directly applicable to your current circumstances, and having the status of an officially affiliated library would bypass that requirement. It would also be a good foundation with which to begin negotiations with other institutions of the Old World. Unfortunately, it does require quite a bit of documentation. You can understand why this is. You don't want the entire corpus of the Colleges of Magic to be easy pickings for any sneak-thief or warband that happens to be in the area of an official library, so it makes sense to properly vet applications for that status to make sure they're sufficiently secure and well-protected. But the process of acquiring official recognition was made with the assumption that the libraries would be within the borders of the Empire, so it takes some creativity on your part to answer a number of them. One particular sticking point is that of religious dedication, and eventually you settle for Valaya, which the mountain itself is named for and was once dedicated to. It's as correct as if you had put 'none', and you're trying to emphasize 'it's in a Dwarfhold' as much as you can. No, you haven't reached a formal agreement with a nearby population centre for their militia to come to the defence of your library, because the entrance to it is within Karak Eight Peaks. You could make a strong case that Kron-Azril-Ungol is more heavily defended than the Colleges themselves, it's just the answers don't fit the format that this paperwork was expecting. When you finally finish and submit the application, you expect to wait months as a proper assessment is made, possibly involving hosting an inspection committee to study the grounds themselves. You're a little outraged when within the hour one of Altdorf's pigeons, grown large and confident from a city steeped in Ghur, drops in your lap the official recognition of KAU's new status with Dragomas' blocky signature on it. --- [Paper writing: Learning, 91+29=120.] Your paper on the Chaos Wastes in the western Great Steppes is a bit of a challenge, as instead of being based entirely on your own notes and fading memories, it requires you to distill down the notes you had all the Wizards on the Expedition take. Sense-memories resurge of the variety of the sights and smells of that sickly landscape, and you fight past them to note down more tangible details: the strange culling of the vegetation where some plants withered and others thrived, the fungal forests that were feasted on by the herds of the Kul, the strange flying beasts in the distance, the bizarre ruins worn down by the passage of so many years that you have to speculate on even time itself being warped, or on some race predating even the Elves building monuments in the far north. The Fimir, perhaps? The Shartak? Or had it once been ocean, and some ancient turmoil beached a temple built by the Prometheans? By itself, the paper is not particularly useful. It does present a rarely-seen breadth of magical senses, but your time in the Wastes was short, shallow, and largely uneventful. But this is a collection of trustworthy data points in a field where most knowledge has to be gleaned from the ravings of the insane and the rantings of the fallen. In future studies of the Chaos Wastes it could present a rare trustworthy landmark in an ever-shifting sea that threatens to claw any who venture into it down to madness and heresy. And for every Wizard who consults it for scholarly purposes, there will be ten who do so for the vicarious thrill of being able to peek off the edge of the map. And you have to admit you play to that a little, weaving a narrative a lot more compelling than that stretch of the actual journey had been, especially when interwoven with mentions of the diverse and exotic company you kept and the hints at the terrible mystery you risked so much to catch a glimpse of. [Observations on the Borderlands of Chaos, 2487. Subject: Rare, +1. Insight: Confirming, +1. Delivery: Thrilling +2. Exotic, +1. Varied, +1. Shared Credit, -1. Total: +5.] So you're quite surprised when Wolf lets you know one morning that there's an aged Wizard in green exploring the fields and leaving a wake of Ghyran rippling through the earth behind him. This is a visitor you're quite surprised to get, despite having explicitly requested it. Magister Patriarch Paranoth the Wanderer is rather aptly named, and it's more difficult to get in touch with him than it is your own Order's leader. Normally this would mean that you would deal with whoever is authorized to make the relevant decisions in his absence, but for something of this magnitude you had needed to at least try to get in touch with him. So you sent a letter to his pigeonhole, a request through the provostry, and asked Panoramia to send word through the Jade Order, and put the matter aside while you wait out the amount of time politeness would dictate. But now, here he is. You drop what you're doing, let Panoramia know of the visitor, and dress for a meeting with one of the most powerful Wizards in the Empire, a circumstance that has become dizzyingly common of late. --- Paranoth is a man of advanced but indeterminate age with a long, white beard that even the most fastidious of Dwarves could find little fault with. His robes still bear the trimmings of a Magister Patriarch if you really look for them, but they've faded over years of hard travel under sun and rain into a shade of green so pale it might be more accurate to call it off-white. But where careless eyes might see only a ageing vagabond, to mystical senses he is unmistakably more, as with every step Ghyran from the soil beneath his feet is drawn into him. Some of it he appears to keep for himself, but most radiates back off of him, soaking into the plants of the fields he walks through. "Welcome to Karak Eight Peaks, Magister Patriarch", Panoramia says as she approaches him. You'd discussed it on the way down, and with you no longer the Court Wizard of Karak Eight Peaks, protocol dictates that her greeting her superior takes precedence. "Thank you, Journeywoman Panoramia," he says in a rich and warm voice, and he gestures to the fields around him. "So this is your work?" "The Halflings' work, but done under my guidance." You step forward in response to her gesture. "This is Lady Magister Mathilde Weber of the Grey Order, the ranking Wizard of Karak Eight Peaks." "Greetings, Magister Patriarch Paranoth," you say. "And to you, Lady Magister," he replies with a nod. "I apologize that you weren't greeted at the gates, Magister Patriarch," Panoramia says. "We hadn't anticipated your visit." "No way for you to have. I wanted to visit the 'green slate' myself at some point, and the Order happened to reach me with news that the Lady Magister was trying to get in touch while I was passing through Barak Varr. Any word I sent would have travelled alongside me. Seeing all this for myself, I can see why you've been calling the Valley that. Elevated, isolated, sheltered, well-drained of rain and Winds, and with thousands of years of Dwarven records saying that only greenskins have lived here. This was a rare opportunity, and you took it." "Thank you, Magister Patriarch." "How is the local water table? I haven't seen any wells, just those artificial rivers." "It's fairly deep down, but not inaccessible. I've tested it and it appears wholesome, but the Dwarves don't want to rely on it, instead putting their trust in the spring-fed tarn halfway up Karagril." "How usable are your results so far?" "Not widely, I'm afraid. I've been relying on the density of skilled farmers here. Even if I can refine the techniques, it would still be far more labour-intensive than assarting the equivalent acreage out of the forests." "Not everywhere. There are valleys in the southern Grey Mountains that might be reclaimed from the local greenskin tribes if there was a way to turn them into farmable land. And there's the mountains near Pugno in Tilea, the northern bank of the Lynsk upstream of Erengrad, a lot of Bretonnia, of course... you just focus on streamlining what you've done into something that can be taught to the average Journeyman, as once you do there'll be a lot of good that can be done with them." Panoramia frowns. "I had intended this to be a testbed for agrology, not a proof of concept against greenskin spores." Paranoth gives her an amused smile. "If you go into the forest to hunt for herbs and find a bush heavy with ripe berries, do you hate it for ruining your plans?" Panoramia considers that and nods. "Of course not. Thank you, Magister Patriarch." But Paranoth isn't done. "The first time I visited Araby, I wanted to see an oasis, but instead I got caught up in a fight between Malaluk and Ghutani nomads over a treasure they had found in the ruins of Bel-Aliad. I could have ignored them all and pushed on, but instead I stayed and tried to find peace between them, being young and naïve. When they proved unwilling to listen to the ignorant prattling of a foreign Wizard, I instead sold my services to the side that was willing to pay more, and came home richer and wiser for it. And a few years later I used a small part of that money to buy passage on a ship to Al-Haikk and joined a caravan that was travelling to the oasis I had originally intended to visit." He smiles. "I've sidetracked myself, but with a story about the value of sidetracks. That is why they call me the Wanderer, you know. Not because I travel without purpose, but because I welcome new purpose where and when I find it. Where was I actually going, though?" He muses. "Oh, yes. Take in the unexpected harvest. It will cost you time, but gain you resources and respect and interest in your original goal." "Yes, Magister Patriarch." "Now if you'll excuse us, I need to discuss inter-Order business with the Lady Magister." "Of course, Magister Patriarch." He turns to you as Panoramia retreats. "So," he says. "Waystones, hmm? Was this your idea, or Algard's?" "It was the Eonir's idea. The Karak Eight Peaks Waystones reactivated when the Karak was reconquered, and the Eonir believed me to be partially responsible." "And you weren't?" "I believe it to have been autonomous. Something to do with the crown, if I had to guess. But I haven't dissuaded them of the notion, due to the opportunity it represents." "And you want our help to hoodwink them?" "It's no secret the Order of Life are more familiar with the Waystones than any other of the Orders. I want your help to preserve that impression they got, and hopefully make it true in the process. The Grey Lords of Laurelorn and the Runelords of the Karaz Ankor are already coming to the table, and if we can get information flowing, there's no telling how much we could learn about the Waystones we live among and die to protect." "You might be just as fooled as the Eonir. Do you know how Teclis proved himself to the Druids? With a wave, he awoke a Waystone we had been worshipping since before the coming of Sigmar, that we believed had been put up by our own ancestors in honour of the Great Mother. We used what he taught us to rework sacred rites into profane rituals to channel the power of the Waystones. Any secrets the Druids once knew were worn away by the centuries of being pushed aside by the modern Cults." "That's still more than I have to go with currently. We need to come to the table with insight that lacks Teclis' fingerprints, or we'll miss the opportunity to engage with the elder races as equals." "I don't think we have what you're looking for," he says, but appears to be thinking. "But there are those in the Order who disagree with me, who still practice the Old Faith, and who think there is more truth than we have extracted in the ancient mysteries. Their belief might add the appearance of truth to your bluff. But I would be empowering a faction that anchors the Order in our past ignorance." You're pretty sure you know where this is going. "If I have to busy myself with undoing the damage this will do to the forward progress of my Order, I'll need you to do what I would otherwise be taking care of." There it is. "Do you know anything of Gryphon's Wood?" "The part of the Great Forest in northern Ostermark?" "The part of the Forest of Shadows in northern Ostermark. There's trouble brewing there, but whatever it is keeps hopping across the Upper Talabec into Kislev. And the Jades don't have much reach in Ostermark, never have, even before Teclis. But you of the Grey might be able to find friends there. Plus you got along with the Ice Witches. Uncover what's to blame for the goings-on there, and I'll send one of ours to the table." It would be nice if someone were to agree to help you for the common good of the Old World, rather than for the opportunity to get you to do something for them. Do you agree to investigate Gryphon's Wood in exchange for the Jade Order joining the Project? [ ] Yes [ ] No If you do agree to investigate the trouble in Gryphon's Wood, which representative from the Jade Order will join the Project in exchange? [ ] Lady Magister Arburg A former Battle Wizard who has spent a fair bit of time defending the northern provinces against Beastmen and Norscans, which might be appreciated by the Eonir. She has spilled blood to defend more Waystones than most have ever seen. [ ] Magister Tochter Grunfeld An ambitious pioneer in Jade rituals who has spent recent years engaged in the Sylvanian campaign, experimenting with ways to purify the soil. She knows more than any other about the rituals that descended from Druidic rites. [ ] Magister Cyrston von Danling Recently promoted and far junior to the other candidates, but you already know you can work well with him. He is extremely perceptive to the rhythms of Ghyran's flow, and thus suited to the study of Waystones. [ ] Perpetual Apprentice Culloch One of the most respected Perpetuals of the Jade Order, only partly due to his rather intimidating Lady Magister wife. He is the secular expert on the history of the Cult of the Mother. --- Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The five with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Laurelorn [ ] Egrimm, to celebrate his imminent promotion and gauge his reaction to it. [ ] Elrisse, to get to know the most recent contributor to the Project. Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Belegar, to discuss who has been made Loremaster after you. [ ] Gretel, who's apparently getting involved in the Karaz Ankor's ambitions in the Border Princes. [ ] Panoramia, to talk about how well her project in the Eastern Valley seems to be going. [ ] Cython, to talk obliquely of what it means for a God to have offspring. Foreign Relations [ ] Stirland, to see for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. [ ] Middenland, to see how the Ulricans are going with their new Eonir coreligionists. Friends Abroad [ ] Roswita, to get a sense for who will control Sylvania after you turned down the position. [ ] Kasmir, to see how partnership with Sylvania's native faith has been going. Following Up [ ] The Amber College, to check in on the salamanders. [ ] The Gold College, to see what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. - There will be a three hour moratorium. - You can still vote for a Jade Order representative if you vote against investigating Gryphon's Wood. - If you have ideas for other social encounters, feel free to suggest them.

Turn 36 Social - 2487.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Yes [*] Magister Tochter Grunfeld [*] Egrimm, to celebrate his imminent promotion and gauge his reaction to it. [*] Elrisse, to get to know the most recent contributor to the Project. [*] Cython, to talk obliquely of what it means for a God to have offspring. [*] Panoramia, to talk about how well her project in the Eastern Valley seems to be going. [*] Belegar, to discuss who has been made Loremaster after you. Vote tally "I've been hearing rumours of troubles in Gryphon's Wood myself, and I'd be happy to satisfy both our curiosities," you say to Paranoth with a smile. "And I would be equally happy to welcome Magister Grunfeld to the Waystone Project." He nods. "She's a staunch traditionalist, but more self-aware about it than most. If there is wheat in that chaff, she should be able to help you find it. If not, she might be able to string together enough of it to sound convincing." He extends a hand for you to shake, and his grip is firm and calloused. "But enough of all that business. I have a powerful desire for Halfling food and Dwarven ale. Any recommendations?" --- By the time Paranoth wanders onwards once more, leaving the Halflings a great deal of food and ale poorer but a few interesting seeds and cuttings richer, Panoramia is more than a little frazzled after spending so much time with the leader of her Order. She particularly seems torn between preening at attention from such a high level and offended that the high-minded blue sky research she intended is being ignored. "Don't take it personally," you say soothingly to her the evening after Paranoth's departure, sitting close together in front of the fire. "Long-term investment needs to take a back seat to the immediate realities. That's the entire history of the Karaz Ankor too, and it's not like the Dwarves don't value ambitious projects." She sighs. "I suppose, but it's still frustrating. It's... it's like I'm building a great cathedral, but everyone's paying attention to the way I poured the concrete for the foundations." "From what I understand, you built those foundations on the botanical equivalent of a swamp. I think you've been too close to it for too long to remember how big a deal that is. You're feeding a big part of a Karak out of what was very recently a wasteland, and that's something that's bankable now. There's a lot of wasteland out there, and a lot of people that could use more feeding." "Yes, that's... that's true, I know that. I do. And I do appreciate being appreciated, but now it's... well, now I've got no excuse, do I? The Magister Patriarch came here and told me to write up how I did it, and considering he ate the crops that came from that soil I can't really argue that it's not ready, can I? And if I'm writing and submitting it anyway, if I don't submit it as a Masterpiece then it's not me just taking my time any more, it's me actively refusing to be promoted. And then it..." She trails off, and sighs. "And then it becomes a thing?" "Then it becomes a thing. And it's a... I don't know what promotion is like for the Greys, but for Jade Apprentices, every year after Mitterfruhl is a month and a half of ceremony and study and then at the end you either get your sickle or you don't. I hated it, I hated it every time. You know what I'm like in late Spring, I want to be out there doing things, not trapped with all the other Apprentices, mouthing along with the stupid rituals and being resented by the outsiders for being an insider, being resented by the traditionalists for not believing, and being resented by the modernists for my mother. So when I got the silver, I left. Ostermark first, because it was as far as I could get from Altdorf without leaving the Empire, and the Mordheim campaign, then King Belegar put the call out. You know the rest. You've been there for the rest." She smiles at you, and finds your hand with hers, and you smile back. You sit there for a while, and Panoramia's smile fades as she turns her attention inwards, organizing her thoughts into something that can be said. "Ma taught me," she eventually says, "but Da raised me. And Da doesn't believe in the Old Faith. Ma never saw it that way, Ma sees it as him staying out of proper Druid business because he's not a proper Druid. She doesn't think men have a place in the Order, I don't think she even thinks we should be recruiting outsiders. 'Mother teaching daughter, since the dawn of time'. It makes me so angry, and from both directions. I'm angry that she can't accept me believing the same thing that Da believes, and I'm angry that she doesn't see Da as a proper part of the Order." She sighs and is quiet for a while, then looks at you and grimances. "I'm sorry, I know it's nothing compared to what you went through with your family-" "No," you interrupt, "don't do that. This is hurting you now, that's what matters." Her hand squeezes yours. "I guess I had fooled myself into thinking that I could just put it off forever. The worst part is, if I had just done it as soon as possible, Ma would have still been just a Magister. But now she's a Lady Magister, so she'll be part of the Sonnstill gathering, who adjudicate the Magister tests. So half the High Druids will be going easy on me because of her, and the other half will be twice as hard because of her, and she'll be damn sure to use the old oaths and the full ceremonies, and no part of any of it would be about me. It would all be about her." You don't know what to say about that, so you don't say anything. You just put your arm around her and pull her to your side, and she exhales and rests her head on your shoulder. Sometimes you're very glad to be part of the sensible Order. --- With the winter snows turning every peak as white as that of its home, Cython is most active during this part of the year, and between hunting trips and visits to your library it is quite willing to entertain your latest curiosity. "What does it mean for a God to have children," Cython echoes, musingly. "It is a pleasingly faceted question, and one I have given considerable consideration to myself. Shall we begin by defining our sample space?" "That seems sensible," you reply. "Of the Elves, the Ellinilli are easily the most numerous, even after Their culling. And then there is Nethu, born of a dalliance between Asuryan and Ereth Khial. Already we have a strong contrast, as Ellinill sired a hundred alone, budding them off from his individual facets, while Nethu's origin is very biological for beings lacking in flesh." "Among the Old Gods, Manann is said to be the son of Taal and Rhya, and Shallya and Myrmidia the daughters of Morr and Verena." "And the Gods of the Dwarves consist of a single family, with three biological children and one adopted child of their pinnacle triumvirate. What conclusions can be drawn from this group?" You frown. "There's not that many, for a start." "Wherever it is that Gods typically come from, it seems parentage is an oddity - or perhaps They have reason to keep it secret most of the time. There's also significant variation in what that relationship means. Ellinill budded off children as a path to power, splitting Them off from His individual facets, and when that relationship threatened more than it benefited He sought to reverse that process and regain the power lost. In this we find support for my 'territory' model of divinity. Ellinill lessened Himself by withdrawing from individual facets of disaster to create His children, and attempted to regain that strength by retaking that conceptual territory." "So Him 'devouring' his children was metaphorical? He instead reclaimed the territory He had granted Them, and in doing so starved Them?" "It depends how separable a God is from Their domain. The intuitive models for beings of flesh is that a God is a single discrete entity that lives within Its domain, but beings of spirit may not be so limited. It could be that a God expands and contracts to match the territory It exists within, thus there would be little difference between supplanting and consuming. In either case, it seems that a God can create another God by either withdrawing from enough territory for a new God to emerge, or by splitting off the part of Themselves that occupies that territory. Similar to how a dragon with a greater territory than it requires might grant some to a child, so that a possible ally would be close at hand." You frown in concentration as you consider this. This would make a God more like a nation than a single being, drawing belief from those living within a conceptual territory just as a nation draws tax from those living within its borders. If you take this metaphor further... Ellinill split off a hundred city-states from Its territory for... probably similar reasons that the Empire grants Imperial City charters, but then reconquered Them over fears they would secede completely? If you turned this metaphor on its head and considered nations to be like Gods, would Marienburg be a son of the Empire? You explain this line of thinking to Cython, and it considers it for a while before nodding. "The 'nation' model might be a more familiar fit for you, and does not differ meaningfully from my 'territory' model. Let us move to the example set by the Gods of your people - firstly, Manann." Cython waves its head from side to side in the draconic equivalent of a furrowed brow. "Let us say, for the sake of argument, that Taal and Kurnous are entirely separate, that Rhya and Isha are entirely separate, and so on. I do not believe this to be the case, but I acknowledge it as unlikely but possible that the wilds of one continent might be conceptually separate to the wilds of another, and that the similarities could be coincidence, resonance, and cultural osmosis. But I do not believe there is any rational argument for Manann and Mathlann to be separate beings. On top of all the same similarities, both Gods are of the same ocean. The same waters the Elves say are dominated by Mathlann, your people say are dominated by Manann, and despite close contact between the sailors of your people and they, there is no conflict between the two. This raises an immediate problem with the idea that Manann is the child of Taal and Rhya, because Mathlann is one of the Ellinilli." "Unless the concept is sufficiently different for Gods that it is possible for two separate sets of parents to make sense." Cython gives an amused slow-blink. "But we have already mentioned an example of this very phenomena among the Gods." You run back the conversation in your mind. "Are you suggesting Manann was adopted?" "Here we arrive at the second type of parentage: metaphor. Manann grew beyond the constrains of His original family, becoming a God of the ocean in general instead of a single variety of disaster related to it - the question of how exactly that occurred is one for another time. And as a result of this transformation, He became more accepted by His worshippers. On Ulthuan, He is part of the inner ring of their Pantheonic Mandala, while Estreuth, Addaioth, Hukon, Drakira, and even Ellinill languish in the outer. And among the humans of your continent, just as Valaya and Grungni and Grimnir adopted Gazul, Taal and Rhya adopted Manann." You nod slowly as you digest this. "That does make sense. Do you have a similar argument for Shallya and Myrmidia?" Cython exhales. "Not while I am constrained by the possibility of the separation of the Ulthuan and Classical Pantheons. Instead I have something much more ephemeral. It is..." It snorts. "It is too neat. Where death meets wisdom, you find mercy and martial prowess? It is too elegant to have arisen from the random strife of existence. There is some invisible hand at play here. To me this can only be an extension of parentage as metaphor, either from the Gods themselves or from mere mortal theologians stumbling across poetry too beguiling not to incorporate." You consider retorting, but Cython appears perfectly aware that this is an idea that needs considerable more time in the soil to sprout, and that digging it up would do it no favours. "Very well. I take it that next is a third model of parentage, a more biological one?" "The Dwarves have extensive records of the births of each of the three children of their triumvirate. By all appearances, the Dwarven Ancestor-Gods were biological when They were walking the earth. I do not think there is insight to be found in the nature of Gods by studying Them before They had ascended. But there is one left in our sample, is there not?" "Nethu," you say. "Son of Asuryan, you said? Isn't Asuryan supposed to be married?" "And Ulthuani belief would tell you that when Ereth Khial attempted to seduce Him, He rebuffed her and remained loyal to Lileath. But Nehekhara has the very same myth between the Sun God Ptra, the Moon Goddess Neru, and the jealous usurper Sakhmet, but in this version Sakhmet uses trickery and illusion to usurp the position of Neru for a night. While it is easy to see this as a mythologization of the phenomena you know as Hexensnacht, the similarities are too many to be coincidence. I believe the Kingdom of the Dead preserves a tale that the orthodoxy of modern Ulthuan rejects - the conception of Nethu, who I believe to be known to Nehekhara as Sokth." "If this is the case, then we have a very biological birth among the Gods." "That would seem to be the case. And I do not think it too unlikely. While the Gods themselves may owe nothing to biology, they are bound to mortal beings that very much do. In the same way that Gods can reasonably be thought of as having two arms and two legs, it is entirely possible that they may be similarly equipped with the more distracting paraphernalia of flesh, and the consequences that those distractions can lead to." While there's a great deal of opinion, speculation, and pure guesswork in all of that, it's definitely thought provoking. Three models of Godly children: territorial, metaphorical, and biological. A territorial child of Ranald and Shallya would originate in a conceptual subset of one or the other, or perhaps one on the cusp of both. Righteous vigilantism? Protection of the weak? Stealing from the rich, giving to the poor? The overlaps between Shallya the Merciful and Ranald the Protector make it very easy to invent possible identities for territorial children. And if they follow the example of Mathlann, it's possible that the children could have evolved beyond this conceptual nursery. A metaphorical child of Ranald and Shallya would represent an adoption, a God that had abandoned a previous position to take up one aligned with Ranald and Shallya. You're reminded of the pilgrimage of the followers of the Ancient Widow, and their abandonment of Chaos worship in the Great Steppes to build a bulwark against Chaos in the lands now known as Kislev - but you already know something of the relationship between the Widow and Ranald, and it is a frosty one, not one enshrined in metaphor. And that these children are ones not generally known goes against the entire concept of metaphorical familial relationships among the Gods, does it not? Thirdly, biological. Ranald and Shallya are often depicted with human forms, and according to this theory those forms would still be able to... engage in the sorts of activities that result in children. But if you discount the Dwarven examples, then you are left with only Nethu, who you know next to nothing about. You make a foray into your library, returning with the few Dwarven books on the Elves that might have mention of Him. Several hours later you're left with a very few scraps of information: Nethu is the Gatekeeper of Mirai, where the souls of those stolen or seduced away from Morai-heg toil in servitude to Ereth Khial. This is the trouble of a sample size of one: you cannot tell if this close tie to the mother is part of being a 'biological' child of a God, or a product of Ereth Khial's controlling personality that would not apply to what you would hope to be a healthier relationship between Ranald and Shallya and Their own children. You do find mention that Nethu is also the God of Dark Pegasi, the bat-winged, flesh-eating flying horses of Naggarond, and this appears to be unique to Him, rather than something shared with His mother - though you do not have anywhere near enough sources to say that with any confidence. You sigh in frustration, looking up from your book and blinking at the dragon across from you that you'd completely forgotten about. "I'm sorry, I just dropped completely out of that conversation. That was very rude of me." Cython looks up from its own book, tilting its head in mild confusion. "Why apologize? You stopped talking because you had gathered so many questions, you had no choice but to pursue them. I know of very few better ways for a conversation to end." --- "My initial thought was a diplomat of some sort, but I eventually decided to take the opportunity to do some further reorganizing," Belegar says to you as the two of you walk through the construction site of your library. "Edda will be stepping down as Steward in the coming months." "Is everything okay with her?" you ask, concerned. It's not unknown for Advisors to Dwarven Kings to be dismissed, but it's normally prepared for far in advance when the person involved would be entangled in so many ongoing projects. "She's grumbling, but she understands the necessity. Between you and me, her Clan and Kazador's are in some rather hurried nuptial negotiations. The sort with an immovable deadline." You take that in. In theory, a child conceived out of wedlock is a source of great shame. In practice, Dwarven children are rare enough that everyone will pretend not to notice a heavily pregnant bride, and will swear on their beard that the child born a month later must be extremely premature and declare it a miracle from Valaya that it was born in perfect health despite that. "Then I suppose I will soon owe them my congratulations." "Her Clan back in Karak Izor are grumbling - I think they still had hopes of her marrying me - but her Clan here are overjoyed. I'm pleased with it, myself. The more ties with Karak Azul, the better. With Edda having established Dwarven industry so thoroughly, we have the opportunity to turn our attention to less traditional methods, so I'm going to make Francesco Caravello the new Steward when the time comes. There's going to be a lot of trade negotiations happening once the five passes are fully secured, and he has the knowledge and he's proven himself trustworthy. And I want him keeping an eye on the east, too - there's rumours of a new Overtyrant among the Ogres, and that could really interfere with trade. But while that worked out nicely, it put me rather at a loss for Loremaster. For the same reasons you stepped down, I suppose." "Nothing weird left that needs poking," you say with a nod. "More or less. So if we don't have troubles today, we should lay in for the troubles of tomorrow. I've brought in a promising young Engineer named Okri Drakkisson of Clan Bronzebeard - Karak Norn's offshoot of Karak Drazh's Stonebeards, cousins to the Karak Eight Peaks Stonebeards." "'Promising' and 'young' seem a bit less than what Karak Eight Peaks could have attracted," you observe sceptically. "Aye, though I've heard good things about him. I'm hoping that through him I can bring in others from his Clan to refound the Karak Drazh Stonebeards, one more general in purpose than the modern Gyrocopter-focused Karak Eight Peaks Stonebeards. His father would be the real catch, he's said to be a genius with steam and hydraulics." You refrain from further comment, somewhat disappointed that your successor is so prosaic. But you suppose it's a good thing that Karak Eight Peaks no longer needs a strange and exotic troubleshooter any more. If anyone's earned the right to some boring and run-of-the-mill build-up, it's the Dwarves. "I'm glad Karak Eight Peaks is secure enough to invest in the future in this way." He nods. "As am I. The only downside is that now my Clan is pushing more than ever for me to get married, and I've run out of reasons why not to." "Does the thought terrify you so?" "Of a wife? Not so much. But of having children I could fail... that scares me more than anything. There's been times over the years where I've drawn great comfort that if I failed, I've failed no worse than a great many of my ancestors. But the thought of having children to pass the crown to, children I might fail to pass the crown to..." He shakes his head. "The price of climbing higher, it seems, is that it gives you further to fall." "So don't fall." He chuckles. "That simple, eh?" "Nothing we've achieved here has been simple, but we've achieved it anyway. It would be good to have some little Princes or Princesses Ironhammer running around the place. If you truly don't want to then by all means let the crown pass to a nephew or something, but don't let fear be the only reason you don't." He frowns at you. "Didn't you step down from giving advice?" "I stepped down from being paid for giving advice. You're still getting it, whether you want it or not." He gives you a scrutinizing look. "What?" "Just checking your plaits for grey hairs. You've spent so long around us Dwarves that you're turning into a longbeard." "Have you forgotten you're more than twice my age?" "Aye, I often do." You pat him companionably on the shoulder, and the two of you continue your walk through the construction site.

Turn 36 Social - 2487.5 - Part 2

With Egrimm already in and out of the Light College while trying to uncover usable details on their origins, it was very easy to transition that into him remaining there for a prolonged period while preparing for whatever tests or rituals mark a promotion to Lord Magister among the Light Order. But you're a little worried about how Egrimm might take this meddling in his career, so you rearrange your own schedule so you can be nearby when he is either promoted or passed over to congratulate or commiserate. This will also give you an opportunity to touch base with one of your newest partners in the Waystone Project. The Light Order is rather more open to guests than the Grey, and part of that means that as the guest of a Magister, you have one of their guest rooms made available to you. Despite this welcoming gesture, you find yourself far from comfortable as you do your best to settle in, and can't seem to shake a feeling of being exposed. Part of that is undoubtedly metaphysical in origin as your Ulgu-rich self is smothered in its cardinal opposite, but it's also a result of the ambient light seeping into the room from every angle. You're undoubtedly far from the first to not be entirely comfortable in these environs, and there's a freshly-laundered sleep mask waiting for you on the bedside table. You rise early the next morning from uneasy sleep for your meeting with Lady Magister Elrisse. Her full title is High Luminary, Treatite, and Abjurer Elrisse, which signify a Lord Magister who focuses on the pursuit of practitioners of unsanctioned magic and has secondary specializations in academia and the banishment of Daemons. Her role in the Order's hierarchy is that of Gatekeeper, which is a surprisingly grounded title for the Light Order, and you can only conclude that it refers to more esoteric and metaphorical gates rather than the mere front doors of the College, which is equivalent to the Grey Order's Porter - the one responsible for internal security. You don't doubt that between your involvement in Light Order affairs and her future involvement in your Project, she'd have done some digging into your own background. You wonder how many roadblocks she would have encountered in doing so, and how she would have reacted to them. Your meeting is to take place in the Sun Room of Volans, and you wonder if it originally belonged to the Light Order's founder or whether it was merely named for him. You take a moment to consider the bust of him beside the door; the offputtingly blank stare of marble eyes would be accurate in this case, as every depiction of him you've seen had solid white eyes that the touch of Hysh sometimes imparts. Considering his history, you wonder if he developed them under Teclis' tutelage, or whether they were a result of his disastrous early experimentations with magic in a long foreshadowing of his future path. You also wonder how he'd feel about the modern strife within his Order. Inside the room there are a pair of reclining chairs parallel and separated by a few feet in the middle of a sunbeam that appears to come from nowhere in particular. According to your mental map you're too deep within the structure to be receiving direct sunlight, but you suppose moving sunlight around would be a triviality to the Light Order in the heart of their power. One of the chairs occupied by who you presume to be Lady Magister Elrisse. Her eyes open and she gives you a long, considering look before speaking. "Lady Magister." "Lady Magister," you respond, hiding your reluctance as you take your place in the chair beside her, refusing to show that this setting is about as comfortable to a Grey Wizard as a mounting board would be to a butterfly. You also resist the urge to feel resentment over this arrangement. As the woman in charge of internal security for the Order of Light, not taking every advantage she can would be disrespecting your capabilities. She shifts onto her side to look directly at you, and you copy her movements with some awkwardness. These chairs go in and out of vogue every few years among the nobility, but your only encounters with them had been in books, and you'd much rather be upright and with a table between the two of you. "I am told we are to work together," she says, "in exchange for services performed for the good of the Order of Light. I am leery of a Grey Wizard having a part in our internal politics, but you have been vouched for at the highest levels." "I am honoured by their trust in me," you say, wondering precisely which highest levels she's been talking to. "Trust is hard to find between Light and Grey, but if we are to be colleagues, we must cultivate it. I would ask that you explain to me how this Project came about." Her tone is steady and well-enunciated and just short of being rhythmic, as though they had been hammered into place in an attempt to bulwark against the vagaries of the spoken word. "Do you know what a Karak-Waystone is?" you ask, knowing for a fact that she has no way to, and sure enough she shakes her head. "The oldest Dwarfholds have built-in mechanisms to drain magical energies from their surrounds. Those of Karak Eight Peaks were reactivated during the final stages of the reconquest. Through means I can only guess at, the Grey Lords of Laurelorn were able to detect this, and reached out to me via Middenland in the hopes of pooling information to hopefully be able to slow or stop the long decline of the network, or even reverse it." "So you are building a magical conclave." "That's a good way to put it." She nods. "My own credentials are in counterespionage, counter-daemonology, and Article 13 enforcement. I have relevant experience in the purging of malign energies and in encounters with Waystones corrupted for fell purposes, two of which were restored and one necessitated destruction. I also have access to many relevant accounts of events involving Waystones in the Luminarian Archives, the vaults of the Librarium Secularum, and the sacristies of the Order of the Silver Hammer." You consider both her and your reply. She makes all the proper expressions and replies one does in conversation, but there's a moment of blank concentration before each, as though she has to take a moment to conceive of the right reply. You wonder if this is a mark left by Hysh she is attempting to work around, or a more personal idiosyncrasy. "And what of the wisdom Volans was inheritor to?" "I know what all of my rank know, and have access to more, should it be necessary." "I believe that you should operate under the assumption that it will be necessary." She considers you. "I will take that under advisement," she eventually concludes. "But it will not benefit the Empire if we surrender the wisdom of ancients to the first Elf who asks nicely." "We will not benefit anyone at all if we sit upon a hoard of secrets until Chaos overtakes the world." She considers you for a long moment. "The Elves are not your Dwarves," she finally says. "If they can extract all of our secrets and give us nothing in exchange, they will do so gladly, and without the faintest twinge of conscience." "I'm aware. If they were Dwarves, I wouldn't be trying to bluff them." You're not entirely sure if her smile in response to that is amused or condescending. "You would seek to use lies and deceit to manipulate them into a mutually beneficial arrangement?" "The only thing wrong with that sentence is the tense it's in. I am using lies and deceit to manipulate them into a mutually beneficial arrangement." "Then I believe I have established an understanding. Thank you." "A question in response, if I may." She nods. "It is odd to me that someone in a position that would demand loyalty, or at least neutrality, to the Magister Patriarch is aligned against him." She considers that for a time. "I can see why you would believe that to be the case, but it isn't," she finally says. "I am here talking to you, not nipping at his heels in Talabecland. What Alric wants most of all is for his Order to finally outgrow him, and if this Project is a success, that serves Alric's ultimate objective and Mira's immediate goal." "You're hedging your bets." "I suppose one could describe it that way." You nod. "Thank you for your honesty. I am glad we could go into this with an understanding of each other." --- The time where a dejected and rejected Egrimm would have emerged comes and goes, and you go off to have a meal while you wait for the next time of possible emergence. And finally, at the end of what you're absolutely sure was an unnecessarily long-winded ceremony, Egrimm emerges from the inner chambers of the Light College in the ceremonial garb of a Lord Magister of the Order of Light. Well, in most of it. He's already removed the very tall mitre, which would be completely unwearable anywhere with normal-size doorways, and is staring at the embossed snake on it like he's worried it will bite him. "Congratulations, Lord Magister Egrimm," you say, patting him on the shoulder as best you can around the large and intricate coiled snake pauldrons. "Rather belatedly, but well-deservedly." "Thank you," he says, tucking the mitre under his arm. "And not just for the congratulations. I know you had a part in it. There's no way someone so tied to Alric would be getting promoted right now otherwise." "You're quite welcome," you say with a smile. "Now you don't outrank me, though," he says, the unasked question is clear in his expression. You could pretend you don't know what he means, or just say it was the right thing to do, but that wouldn't be the way to handle him now. "Outranking you gives me no utility," you say instead. "If you don't want to be a part of what I'm doing, then using rank to force you would be the same stupid mistake Alric made. I'd rather have no help at all than rightfully recalcitrant help." He nods slowly as he considers that. "Thank you," he says again. "And I will be sticking with you. If nothing else - and in truth you've provided a lot of 'else' - then because Tor Lithanel is a great place to hunker down and wait for this conflict to be over." You smile. "So, how was it? Esoteric and ominous?" "Funnily enough, not so much," he says with a smile. "I just got done swearing terrible oaths not to reveal the details, but I can tell you that it's extremely obvious where someone, or more likely a lot of someones, went in there and carefully reworded everything so that everything has an entirely secular meaning if you examine it from a post-Teclisean lens. Trying to make a metaphor fit the old traditions and the new truth at the same time makes for a lot of really bad metaphors. What about yours?" "They showed me an ancient and powerful secret and gave me seven different and mutually exclusive explanations for it." "Wizards," he sighs. You nod in agreement. "Sometimes I think they're just making it up as they go along." --- The next morning you're up almost as early as usual, feeling only slightly worse for wear and probably a great deal better than Egrimm. Celebratory drinks with him demonstrated to you what you would have guessed: that the lifestyle of the Light College leaves one with much less of a head for alcohol than that of a Dwarven Karak, but a much better singing voice. As you're packing your things for your departure from Altdorf, you receive a short note delivered by the Light College's staff from your own Order - specifically, from Lord Magister Reiner Starke, asking for you to drop by his office at your convenience. That he specifies his office instead of a more general meeting indicates it's on the business of his office, and it's rarely a good sign for anyone to receive an unexpected invitation to the Porter's office. You suppose this was inevitable, you tell yourself after running through the first dozen disastrous scenarios. Getting entangled in the business of other Orders would always mean more eyes on you, and eventually those eyes would find something of some shade of untoward. That you received a polite invitation at a reasonable hour indicates that whatever was turned up wasn't too bad. That rules out the Liber Mortis, the former Empress, and probably the current Empress. That just leaves... well, a lot of things, none of which strictly wrong, but lots that could look bad if stumbled over by someone unused to the shades of grey that your occupation requires. The embezzlement would be the most uncomfortable possibility, you suppose. Oh. No, actually that is a very distant second. The Underwear Incident, that would absolutely be the most uncomfortable. Then there's involvement with various frowned-upon groups - thieves, tricksters, spies, radical sects, merchants. Dubious experimentation that you weren't ever explicitly cleared for. Involvement with foreign magic-users. Encounters with the forces of Chaos... You suppose the whole Only Mork thing might also be a possibility. But while it is the sort of thing that would raise a great deal of questions, only five other beings know about that and you can't really see any of them gossiping to the rumour mill of the Colleges about it. Well, you could think yourself in knots for hours going over the possibilities, but the only way to get an answer is to go to the meeting. You reconsider that last thought, and mentally edit it. The only way to get an answer, excluding methods unacceptably likely to cause even more trouble, is to go to the meeting. --- "Lady Magister Weber," Lord Magister Reiner Starke greets you as you step into the room. You're very careful to leave that 'step' unmodified by descriptors - you do not step cautiously, or hesitantly, or brashly. You simply... step. "Thank you for visiting me on such short notice." "The security of the Grey Order is ever my concern," you say as you take a seat across from him. He had called you in as soon as you knocked, which can't be taken as a good or bad sign on its own. It could be good that he's not playing games by making you wait, but it could be bad that this is so important that he's dropped whatever else he was doing. "That may be overstating my purpose for this meeting. This is a courtesy to you. A counterpart of mine in another Order-" Elrisse, you guess immediately, and then second-guess that. If it was her, she surely could have timed it better to make it less obvious, so perhaps it is the Jade equivalent. Or perhaps Elrisse knew that you'd think that, so she- you remember that Reiner is still talking, and force your attention to return to his words, quickly running through what he has been saying that a corner of your mind had been paying attention to the whole time. "-was doing a routine investigation and came across some irregularities. Do you recall your involvement with the Wurtbad Watch?" Ah, yes. The Watch you put a professional thief in charge of. The Watch you tried to convert to the worship of Ranald. The Watch you sort of stole the Gong Farmers from. And a saltpeter factory. "Yes, I recall." "I understand that your handling of their spiritual welfare was... what some might describe as unconventional." His voice and expression are worryingly neutral. You're careful to keep your expression unmoved. "We're Grey Wizards, Reiner. Conventional isn't our purview." He gives you a long look at that, and then his expression softens. "That's fair. Okay, let me be clear. The Grey Order has unambiguously endorsed the actions of Journeyman Mathilde Weber twice over. I'm not here to autopsy the events of a decade ago, and even if I were inclined to do so, this particular event wouldn't be worth any of our time. Each one of us has many events in our past that can be pointed to as mishandled with the luxury of hindsight. But while you and I and every other Grey Wizard worth a damn knows this, there's a lot of important people out there who aren't Grey Wizards, and they might stumble across traces of things that aren't problems, and between misunderstanding and skewed perspectives, mistake them for problems. Or if they come at it with ill intent, they could make them into problems. You can end this conversation right now and walk away if you want, that is your prerogative, and I'll consider the matter closed and if I have my way we'll never have to talk about this again. But if we do have that conversation here and now, then I'll have your version of those events right here on file, not the garbled misunderstandings some outsider spills all over my desk. And having that means I'd be a lot more able to get ahead of possible future manufactured discreditation before it has a chance to begin." You take a few breaths as you study the man in front of you. Everything he says makes sense, and he definitely seems to be sincere, but he has the kind of job where one would need to develop an ability to seem sincere on command. So, for the moment, let's assume for the sake of argument that he's being completely honest. The attempted conversion of the Watch was... not your finest moment. With the Watch already grumbling and Abelhelm's death still raw, you'd funnelled your grief into what might have been a punitive war against Sigmarism among the Watch and expelled a number of watchmen from it over the vandalism of the shrines to Ranald the Protector. That would have left quite a trail of bitter men willing to tell the tale to anyone who stood still long enough. And Reiner is right: if someone heard the worst version from someone who'd been letting their bitterness marinate for a decade, or if they went out of their way to spin it as badly as possible, this could lead to future discomfort. It would make sense to have a justification here in Altdorf, ready to go. But what explanation to give? [ ] Piety You converted the Wurtbad Watch to Ranald because you worship Ranald, and it would have given you a better hold over the organization. Simple and true, but it would mean revealing your faith. [ ] Grief You acted rashly after the death of Abelhelm, a death that Sigmar could have prevented, and acted out against a largely Sigmarite institution under your control. While true and understandable, it does hint towards the extent of your rather complicated feelings towards your former liege, and you might not want those hints available for cross-referencing if the Underwear Incident ever comes to light. [ ] Trauma You stood over your dying liege and fought against an endless tide of undead, waiting for reinforcements that almost never came. You took command when nobody else would and gave orders that led to the deaths of thousands. You sentenced a Necromancer to death and smiled as you watched him burn alive. In the aftermath of all that, you were not at your best. That's why you mishandled the situation. [ ] Skaven Sure, you didn't know about them then, but Reiner doesn't know that. Say that you had plans to turn the Watch into an instrument for defending against the Skaven. As part of the Conspiracy of Silence, Sigmarite creed denies the existence of the Skaven, so it was necessary to convert the Watch to some other God, and the Night Prowler was the best fit for a subterranean war. [ ] Nothing Give a non-answer. You don't fully remember the details, but you made the best decision you could with the information you had available to you at the time. With the benefit of hindsight you would have done things differently. [ ] Leave Reiner has been very clear that you can just leave. Do so. [ ] Other (write-in) - There will be a fourteen-hour moratorium. - Write-ins can be Mathilde's exact words or a more general description of Mathilde's justification. - Something that Mathilde would know but didn't acknowledge in her internal monologue because she's off-balance: this is not a huge deal. This will not lead to disaster unless you answer something like "I was too busy reading my newly-acquired copy of the Liber Mortis to do my job properly". Don't think of this in terms of 'if we answer wrong Mathilde goes to Azkaban', think in terms of 'what answer will be least disruptive and/or most beneficial to Mathilde's ongoing relationships within the Colleges'.

Turn 36 Social - 2487.5 - Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Grief You acted rashly after the death of Abelhelm, a death that Sigmar could have prevented, and acted out against a largely Sigmarite institution under your control. While true and understandable, it does hint towards the extent of your rather complicated feelings towards your former liege, and you might not want those hints available for cross-referencing if the Underwear Incident ever comes to light. Tally Once you decide to tell most of the truth, it doesn't take much effort to bring the memories, and the emotions, back to the forefront. Most of the hurt has faded, but the bitterness never has. "During the Purge of the Haunted Hills, I saw, and felt, Sigmar's intervention multiple times. Most notably in the Battle of Fang Island, where it struck down a great deal of Undead, including the Strigoi vampire known as the Singing King. Brother Kasmir channelled the might of Sigmar with considerable skill and finesse, before, during, and after that campaign. In fact, the only time I ever saw him fail to do so is when he called on it to heal Abelhelm Van Hal." "Ah," Starke says. "I think I see." By how guarded his expression has suddenly become, you suspect that either he doesn't, or he does extremely well. "Abelhelm was a great man, and I admired him a great deal. After he had been allowed to die..." You sigh. "Well, I did have good reasons for seeking a new patron for the Watch, but the way I responded when they did not cooperate was entirely down to my personal feelings at the time." He nods and leans forward to start writing. "Entirely understandable. A lot of Journeyman have done much more, and for worse reasons." His expression of concentration as he writes is more natural than the poker face he had before, but gives just as little away. "I hope this will be the last I hear of the matter." "It should be," Starke says distractedly. "I do not foresee a time when we have nothing more important to deal with than a few disgruntled former thief-takers. I would not have brought it up at all if we weren't in the business of guarding against the unforeseen." You nod and rise, giving Starke a thoughtful look before you leave. Somewhere in the Grey College there must be a room filled with documents like the one he is now working on, filled with details of embarassing missteps by prominent Wizards and the way best to explain them away should they come to light. This is, you suppose, a requirement of being the Order tasked with wielding a Wind so easy to misuse - that those who wield it must be above suspicion. Such a reputation must take a great deal of very careful maintenance. You let your mind linger on that as a welcome distraction while your emotions settle. The memories of Abelhelm's passing are a lot easier to call up than they are to dismiss. --- In Karak Eight Peaks, Kvinn-Wyr is a hive of industrious activity. The excavation crews, drawn from the local mining population, have begun work on what is to be the fifth hall. In the fourth, masons have begun work on the rough edges of the pickmarked stone with chisels and polishing pads to create the smooth surfaces of the finished rooms. In the third, flagstones are being laid out to protect the natural stone from the wear of passing feet. In the second, metalsmiths are laying down an inset pattern of branching minecart tracks in gaps left between the flagstones, with masons following behind and filling the space between the tracks with cobblestone. And in the first hall, the prototype of the first bookcase waits for your approval. Your priority was simple: everything goes in its section. Simple enough at first glance, but it gets trickier as your collection grows more diverse and esoteric. A regular shelf is fine for the products of Altdorf booksellers, but what about older, more delicate books that need to lie flat, lest gravity wrest the pages free from the grip of fraying threads and decaying glue? What about scrolls and tablets and slips? What about monstrously oversized tomes like the Modest Treatise? What about things like tapestries and rubbings? The usual answer is to put them in storage and then inevitably forget about them, while the less bad answer is to transfer everything into book format and simply accept a certain amount of copying errors creeping in. You, however, are building a library that will be beyond the usual ravages of budget and necessity. While this does mean you will have the power to create a bespoke solution for every oddity and edge case you encounter, a certain amount of uniformity is still preferable for the sake of efficiency and aesthetics. Enter this: the Mark One 'Kvinn' Wheeled Modular Bookcase. The skeleton of the Kvinn looks very much like a short and sturdy stone bookcase with the shelves removed, and it theoretically could be used that way, and perhaps sections could be set up for copies of the more in-demand books if the library starts to attract enough visitors that individual tomes could become bottlenecks. But for the initial collection, your priority is that everything will stay where it is left until it is needed, whether that be an hour or a week or a century later, and over a long enough time period the forces of gravity, moving air, ambient damp, and the friction of books being pulled out and returned begins to accumulate. So in place of shelves can go an array of other carefully-crafted modules. For most books, labelled sliding shelves of varying size will be the answer, with individually-crafted felt-lined cavities for each item. A clever latching mechanism leaves a handle visibly protruding if a shelf isn't fully closed and locked in place, and it requires the proper weight inside of it before it will allow itself to be latched. This is intended to be more a proof against misplaced books than a security mechanism, and it can be replaced with a key lock for the more valuable or dangerous tomes. A similar module has been designed for holding scrolls of various widths and diameters, and as a proof of concept, purpose-built modules for containing various awkward items ranging from a broken pick to a large boulder have been roughly hewn from scrap stone to demonstrate that the system could be adjusted to almost any contents. There is another, subtler bugbear of would-be librarians who yearn for order: that of expansion. Dedicating a shelf to a single topic is all well and good, but as you acquire more document you reach the limit of that shelf. The question can be put off by balancing additional books atop the row of spines, but eventually one must succumb to the inevitable and displace the contents of an adjoining shelf. This is annoying on a personal scale, but could be disastrous on the scale of a library that wishes to maintain proper order. The displaced shelf must displace another, and that a third, until the displacement dominoes through the entire contents of the hall it is in. And this would happen every time a shelf reaches capacity. Well, this is where the minecart tracks come in. Each bookcase will be dedicated to a single category only, and when one reaches the capacity of its case, a new one can be wheeled in. A single moderately-fit librarian with a can of axle grease and the key to release the locking mechanism of the wheels could move entire bookcases around with ease, and with no risk to the secured contents. At a stroke, the Kvinn solves a great variety of potential problems. In exchange the amount of space it will take up and the amount of effort it will take to build them is greatly increased, but that is the benefit of being bankrolled by a King: not only does Belegar have the wealth to afford this, it actually isn't that expensive to him because all the labour is being drawn from the local population, with local mining, mason, and metalsmithing clans paying labour in lieu of their usual tax obligations. And the physical space, usually the most expensive component of any library located in a city, is something the Karak actually has too much of, and it laying empty is a vulnerability. You consider suggesting a taller bookcase, noting that it is shorter than even the ones you use personally, but leave it unsaid. A height ideal for human sizes would be awkwardly tall to Dwarven and Halfling patrons, and a human can kneel easier than a Dwarf can find a stepladder. You give the Kvinn your approval, and seal the fate of a great many blocks of quarried stone. --- Library Purchases: [ ] [LIBRARY] Colleges of Magic: name four magical, non-divine topics to acquire all available Empire books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Barak Varr booksellers: name three public topics to acquire all available Empire and Dwarven books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Library of Mournings: name two non-magical topics to hire Cityborn scribes to copy all available Laurelorn books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Back-fill. Instead of seeking books on specific topics, fill in some of the sections of your existing library where you have some of the available books from the Empire and the Dwarves on a subject, but not all. Will acquire more books total than other options, but cannot be directed. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a three hour moratorium.

Turn 37 - 2488 - Trading Favours

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [LIBRARY] Library of Mournings: name two non-magical topics to hire Cityborn scribes to copy all available Laurelorn books on. -[*] Hekarti -[*] Loec [*] [DWARF] No purchase. [*] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [*] [PURCHASE] Minor Gods (The Empire) Extensive and Esoteric (250 Gold) Tally A brief skim of your recent purchases highlights the difference between the human and Elven perspective of Gods. A human book on a God will tell you how one should act to attract the attention and approval of a God, whereas an Elven book instead instructs the reader to find the place in themselves where that God is already reflected, how to give that part primacy when needed, and the situations in which doing so would be most beneficial. Parts of the books dedicated to Hekarti read like a very mystical version of a set of Wind attunement and attenuation techniques, and parts of the books dedicated to Loec would function well as guide to music, dance, or ambush tactics. You wonder if this difference arises from the Elves or their Gods - are the Elven Gods more willing to share worshippers, or are Elves just poorly-suited to dedication to a single God? You find the question resonates with very similar ones about the Winds, how Elves are capable of weaving all of them in concert but humans delve much deeper into just one. As in all things, the Elves have a tendency to claim this as a sign of superiority, but an argument can be made - and Cython has already done so - that this is a form of cowardice. To choose one is to reject the others, but to choose none is to master none. This difference in perspective is also why you were able to secure this many books at all. In any human Cult, a large amount of these would be considered Cult secrets and only available to those that have dedicated their lives to the God in question. But to an Eonir perspective, it makes no sense to try to conceal these things because they are simply transcriptions of information that lies within every Elven soul. And because no non-Eonir have had access to the Library of Mournings for millennia, it would make no sense to have any sort of safeguard against that information reaching non-Elves. Perhaps they will identify this as an oversight and close it in time, or perhaps they won't, as this is all information available to polities as distant and inscrutable as Ulthuan and Naggaroth and Athel Loren. Divine secrets exist that aren't on the shelves for any reader to access, of course, but they represent a much narrower portion of the corpus and would fill perhaps a tome or two, rather than entire shelves. With some effort, you put the metaphysical examination of specific psychology and sociology out of your mind to turn your attention to more worldly matters. With the cooperation of the Order of Light and the Order of Life secured, if not yet fully paid for, you now have quite an array of contributors, including inheritors of each of the major parties that was present for the raising of the Old World's Runestones - Thorek for the Dwarves, Lord Hatalath for the Elves, and Elrisse and Tochter for the humans. While there's undoubtedly still value to be found among other groups, this foundation should bring enough perspectives to the table that a groundwork established here and now should be able to incorporate all of those you're likely to be able to bring in in the future. Part of you does want to bring in practically every magical tradition on the continent before you begin, but that's hardly practical. Another part of you does rankle at beginning work on credit, so it might be preferable to fully pay for the presence of Elrisse and Tochter before you put them to work. You did agree to investigate Alric personally, and while you technically didn't promise personal investigation for Gryphon's Wood, a lot of the reasons why Paranoth thought you'd be suited for it wouldn't apply if you merely delegated it. You have five actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. For every two AP spent across all members of WEB-MAT, including recruiting new members, you can spend one 'free' additional AP with any member of WEB-MAT. WEB-MAT actions are performed by Mathilde alongside that person when possible, such as studying something alongside that person, cowriting a paper together, one teaching the other, both of them learning something new, et cetera. Current overwork status: [-] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. WEB-MAT: Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which two papers or one book will be written. WEB-MAT: Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Lord Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, Light Wizard [ ] EGRIMM: Attempt a Windherder enchantment with Egrimm (specify what) [ ] EGRIMM: Learning: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] EGRIMM: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Other [ ] WEB-MAT: Attempt to recruit someone to WEB-MAT (specify who) [ ] WEB-MAT: Investigate Alric with one or more members of WEB-MAT (specify who) (NEW) [ ] WEB-MAT: Investigate Gryphon Wood with one or more members of WEB-MAT (specify who) (NEW) [ ] WEB-MAT: Hire someone as a full-time Gyrocopter pilot (optional: specify who) (NEW) The Waystone Project, Recruitment [ ] Attempt to bring an Order into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a non-Order magical tradition into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a human Cult into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (specify which) The Waystone Project, Research [ ] Personally scrutinize a Waystone as thoroughly as you possibly can. [ ] Lay the foundations: work with the current members of WEB-MAT and the Waystone Project to build a single unified framework for understanding the Waystones. In theory, the more members there currently are, the more complete this framework will be. Will unlock further investigations. Can be repeated if desired, but will not unlock anything new after the first time, it will just make a new framework incorporating any new recruits. Lovely Laurelorn [ ] Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Explore one of the Wards of Laurelorn (specify which: Storm, Rain, Frost) Self-Improvement: [ ] Receive training: specify who and what. (acquaintances may train you for free, or you can hire someone with money or favours) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Attempt to gain control of one of your Arcane Marks (specify which) [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. Aethyric Vitae (17 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item: specify what and how (current skill level allows for Fiendishly Complex spells and lower; you may use Windherder to attempt to enchant something with spells from different Winds) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to codify Rite of Way so that others can learn it. [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff (specify for whom) (optional: specify from what) Foreign Relations: [ ] Investigate Alric (NEW) [ ] Investigate Gryphon Wood (NEW) [ ] Involve yourself in current affairs: specify what and how. Current examples: Sylvanian campaign, Marienburg affair, Black Waters project Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting or ingratiating yourself with someone else: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 200 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Southern Middenland EIC Handler: The Hochlander The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in your fief. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Improve and expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (optional: specify how) [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. [ ] EIC: Investigate what trade goods the Eonir might be willing to import from the Empire. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Try to uncover what's going on in Gryphon's Wood. (NEW) Kron-Azril-Ungol Status: Under construction. The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] Seek the publishing contacts to start acquiring large amounts of books from a nearby realm (specify which: Bretonnia, Kislev, Tilea/Estalia, Araby) Gives wide and easy access within a language, but is subject to local restrictions and is a less efficient use of the Library's acquisition budget than other methods. [ ] Seek an exchange arrangement with another Library to be able to make copies of their corpus (specify which, eg: Great Library of Marienburg, Great Library of Altdorf, Ancient Library of Carroburg) Difficulty will depend on the size, prestige, and disposition of the library in question, and the relative impressiveness of Kron-Azril-Ungol. [ ] Seek an agreement with a Cult to have access to their libraries (specify which, eg: Verenans, Myrmidians, Sigmarites) Difficulty will vary heavily depending on the Cult in question, but can allow access to rare tomes and esoteric subjects. [ ] Set up a no-questions-asked bounty system for books within the Cult of Ranald Results will be unreliable and depending on what is sought may result in blowback, but this may allow you to acquire books that would otherwise be entirely inaccessible. Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. [ ] The Father Ranald's daughters, and Their followers, will recognize you as being worthy of trust and faith. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Books and rubbings from an Asur explorer of Lustria and the Southlands Ghyran Nut Kurgan Shrine to Mannsleib Kurgan enchanted weapons Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Observations of Johann's prosthetic arm (FRESH) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghur (MOSTLY FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Hysh (MOSTLY FADED) Observations on the Windfall north of the Dark Lands (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ulgu (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Aqshy(FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghyran (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Azyr (FADED) Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (FADED) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. Windsoak Mushrooms (missing: Chamon, Shyish) The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a twelve hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - If there's an action that you think should be present and isn't already covered, please let me know. - The Alric and Gryphon Wood actions can be taken either alone or with WEB-MAT, and will be separate mini-turns if/when taken.

Turn 37 Results - 2488 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan Compromise -[*] MAX: Learning: Rituals from the colleges. Mathilde pays gold costs. -[*] EGRIMM: Attempt a Windherder enchantment with Egrimm --[*] Shadowsteed & Clarity, allowing the user to ride all night without sleep -[*] WEB-MAT: Investigate Gryphon Wood with one or more members of WEB-MAT (JOHANN) -[*] Personally scrutinize a Waystone as thoroughly as you possibly can. -[*] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (Frost) -[*] Investigate Alric -[*] EIC: Try to uncover what's going on in Gryphon's Wood. -[*] LIBRARY: Seek an agreement with a Cult to have access to their libraries (Quinsberry) -[*] SERENITY: Write a paper: Observations of Johann's prosthetic arm (FRESH) -[*] COIN: The Night Prowler Tally As your own experience and experimentation can attest, making the Winds act as you want them to is very difficult to do reliably. The most basic and common method of achieving this is for a living soul to attune to the Wind and corral it along the desired path, countering whatever the Wind attempts to regain its freedom. This does, of course, require a living soul and a thinking mind. A workaround to this requirement is to spend days, weeks, or even months laboriously and forcefully altering the nature of the Wind to something static and reliable, sacrificing its adaptability and mutability in the process. But Waystones present a clear challenge to this understanding of the options available, as by all appearances they possess neither soul nor mind, and they clearly don't take prolonged periods to prepare each individual strand of Wind being sent along the leylines. While you would like very much to tackle this fundamental question, your personal study of Waystones has to begin at the beginning. As you attend to other duties you take the time to detour to known local Waystones to study each in search of any differences. The archetypal Waystone is an upright square frustum topped by a square pyramid standing at about the height of a human. On each of the exposed faces of the frustum, if they have not been covered by accumulated dirt or grime, is the Rune used in Eltharin to represent Waystones: a diamond atop a pyramid, and above that, a teardrop. Whether this Rune is upon the Waystones simply as a label of its purpose, or whether the Rune in Eltharin is based off the Rune that marks each Waystone and the marking on the Waystone serves a deeper purpose, is an open question. At the base of the Waystone, though this is almost always underground, is a much larger square base ringed with an eight-pointed star that align precisely with the cardinal and ordinal directions. These Waystones absorb magic and, through means you seek to determine, add it to the leylines flowing beneath them. Unfortunately, this 'basic' model is far from the only one that exists. For each of these 'normal' Waystones there are many menhirs, large standing stones of irregular shape. Many possess no Runes at all, and those that do have carvings of ancient Belthani script. What few that have been partially translated usually tell a tale of some ancient figure or another, leading most historians to believe them to be mere memorials, and many have been toppled or harvested for stone over the millennia. But they, too, absorb the ambient Winds, and to those who can see the direction of the leyline flow below, they always point towards one of the Elven Waystones. From what you've heard, a similar dynamic can be found in the east, with Scythian-made standing stones supplementing the Elven network. Most scholars who note the connection believe the ancient humans were merely aping the Elven visitors, but it's seeming to you that the original network of Elven waystones was supplemented by a titanic effort by the much more primitive local populations that increased the covering of the full Waystone network substantially. On the other extreme are the nexus points, where multiple Waystone-controlled leylines come together into one place to form a larger deluge of energy leading directly towards Ulthuan. Most were erected in easily-accessed areas, many at the heart of ancient Elven communities, so most of these nexuses can be found in the heart of modern human cities. The Waystone at the heart of the Jade College in Altdorf is one of these great nexuses, and it is fed not only by nearby 'regular' Waystones but also by much greater tributaries from the direction of Talabheim and Nuln, and all this energy flows 'downstream' towards Marienburg. You speculate from there it would flow to Castle L'Anguille, and then either further along the Bretonnian coast or directly towards Ulthuan. You don't have access to enough of these to draw conclusions, but the one at the heart of the Jade College seems like a massively upsized version of the Belthani menhirs, rather than being visibly Elven in any way. After having examined in brief enough of the Waystones to get a good impression of them, you seek to select one to be your candidate for more extensive scrutiny, which is easier said than done. Ideally it would be outside of a city to be far from the many distractions of that many souls in close proximity, but also protected in some way so that you aren't rudely awakened from deep meditation by a passing wolf or Beastman. It would also need to be outside of Laurelorn, because you want to use something that's part of the 'normal' Old World network as your prototype, rather than one that is part of the Laurelorn network and therefore may differ in some way. Eventually you settle on a garrison of the Army of Reikland called Fort Brachsenbr체cke that has a Waystone just outside of its main gate, leaving you protected by the patrols and sentries as you turn your full attention to the Waystone. [Study the Waystone: Learning, 28+29+10(Windsage)=67.] It proves to be a rather frustrating study. This area has a typical level of background magic for the countryside of Reikland, which means it is still distractingly awash with magical energy - that is how you are able to perform spells, after all, by calling on the ever-present Winds. Normally very useful, but when you're trying to study the operation of an extremely efficient magical device through the insulating stone it is made of, it instead becomes very annoying. You feel like a daytime stargazer as you try to ignore the beautiful glow of everyday life around you in favour of peering at the impossibly dim workings of the Waystone before you, but over time and with concentration, your 'vision' adjusts to the purpose you are putting it to. The first thing you begin to make out is the leylines thrumming below you, streams flowing in from other Waystones and trickles from Belthani runestones and being redirected onwards to meet the great magical river at Altdorf. Then you are able to notice the faint glows of trapped magic below at specific points in the day - Ulgu at dawn and dusk, Hysh at midday, Azyr on moonless nights. Judging by their position relative to the Waystone, you theorize that the buried eight-pointed star has a storage mechanism in each of the points, one for each Wind, for when the amounts of energy being absorbed temporarily outstrips the Waystone's ability to add it to the stream below. After almost a week spent in concentration, you finally begin to make out the precise point when magic enters the leylines, as constellations of tiny sparks drip from the points of the foundational star into a position directly below the Waystone, and then drop with sudden speed downwards to join the leyline. Sometimes eight, but often less, as there is definitely not exactly equal amounts of each Wind present here. But though at certain points during the daily cycle the amount of Winds being dropped into the leyline sometimes falls as low as two at a time, you never see a single Wind being dropped in, always at least two. You suppose this explains why in Altdorf, a city practically riddled with Waystones, mono-Wind environments such as the Colleges still exist - because the Waystones seem to need at least two Winds to be present to drain away magical energies, and thus a specific Waystone would only be able to drain away as much of a given Wind as there exists the total of the other seven Winds. The final night of observation happens with Morrslieb's baleful influence overhead, with the hideous throb of Dhar creeping along the landscape and being drawn into the Waystone. To your consternation, it proves impossible for you to see anything of the Dhar after it enters the Waystone itself, even as the Waystone absorbs amounts of it that would leave one of the storage mechanisms visible if it were one of the Winds. Perhaps the Waystones are built to contain the malign energies of Dhar and so not even a glimmer of them can be seen by the sharpest of Windsight, or perhaps they are dumped into the leylines below immediately, rather than a few sparks at a time. You carefully make notes on your observations and then finally break camp, passing along your thanks to the fort's captain before heading back towards civilization. --- Meeting with the Ward of Frost is nowhere near as straightforward as it is to meet with any other major figure of Laurelorn. The Ward of Frost has not had a fixed capital since the fall of Kor Immarmor, and apparently has not had a fixed Warden since the death of Lord Lindialoc of House Elwyn. Instead a representative from the newly-empowered Council of Frost is chosen whenever one is needed, and the power apparently surrendered immediately after the need has passed. Not the most conventional of arrangements, but with nobody left with a claim to power from the ruins of Kor Immarmor, there's nobody to try to challenge it. So there's no embassy to visit, no local representative to question, no royal palace to travel to. Unless you're willing to rearrange all of your plans to wait for the next meeting of the High Council, the best course of action available to you is to make your way along the road from Tor Lithanel to Salzenmund and see what happens. If nothing else, you're sure that you'll be noticed as you enter the sprouting lornalim grove of Oldenlitz. Since your last meeting with the memorable Vicereine of Oldenlitz, you've heard quite a few stories about the nature of the beings of the Ward of Frost, many of them quite fanciful, and in the past days you've sought out even more. In other parts of Laurelorn, the Faniour and Dryads keep a cautious distance between each other, but in the Ward of Frost the two have intermingled so thoroughly and for so long that it may no longer be possible to draw a meaningful distinction between them - or at least so go the stories told in Tor Lithanel, which straddle the line between horror and titillation at the exact nature of the intermingling. While biologically there's no way to make sense of a cross between flesh and wood, on a spiritual level there's more possibilities, especially since the Tree Kin of Athel Loren are quite well attested and seem to be the result of an Elven soul being forcefully inserted into a Dryad's body. If said insertion was more, well, gentle and consensual, who knows what the result may be? As soon as you cross the Demst into the Ward of Frost, you find yourself shadowed by an escort of marshlights, which you presume to be the variety of spite known as Mischiefs. In most of the Old World an encounter with the aptly-named spites is quite likely to lead to disaster, but here in Laurelorn they serve the Eonir rather than their own whims, and you take this as a sign that your passage into the Ward of Frost has been noticed. Sure enough it doesn't take long until you are accosted, and you're quite sure that if you had entered the Ward from the other end of the road you would be met with an arrow, rather than a pair of Elves stepping from the treeline into your path, all bared limbs and gleaming muscle and garments made of very few leaves protecting their modesty. Their bows are nocked, but not yet drawn. "Traveller," they address you in unison. "Greetings," you respond. "I am Mathilde Weber, and seek an audience with the Council of Frost." "You are known to the Ward of Frost," one says. "You are welcome in the Ward of Frost," says the other. "But the Council is scattered, and will not meet until necessity drags them from their home soil." "What is your purpose?" You look thoughtfully at the two, and need only a moment's concentration to spot the tendril of magical energy linking the two. A Familiar bond, or something very similar to it. An Elf and a Dryad, perhaps? But which would be the Master? "I seek the wisdom of those of the Ward of Frost to join the effort to unlock the secrets of the Waystones." The two look at each other. "There are perhaps those better suited to that business," one of them says with a smile. "But none more desirous, or more likely to seek vengeance should they be thwarted, than the one you are already on course to find," continues the other. "The Vicereine of Oldenlitz?" you ask, and take the two of them disappearing back into the treeline as confirmation. Still shadowed by the Mischiefs, you spur your Shadowsteed onwards once more. --- In the year and a half since your last visit, the ruins of Oldenlitz have receded even more into the soil, and the saplings have grown into... well, you don't have the vocabulary for tree sizes, so whatever comes after saplings, and now most of them have grown slightly taller than you. But unlike your previous visit you are not expected by Vicereine Cadaeth, and it seems you are not awaited either. As the Mischiefs titter to each other over your head you wander through the ruined roads, carefully giving each of the lornalim plenty of space as you do so, and probe your surroundings with your Magesight. If Cadaeth is an Elf then she will have some sort of residence here, and if she is a Dryad she will have a tree that she resides within, and if the lurid tales of Tor Lithanel are correct and she is a little of each, then she will... have a dungeon within which she will lure innocent yet consenting young Elves into for all sorts of wondrous torments. Perhaps there's only so much accurate insight that can be distilled from those tales. At any rate, you find neither the treetop residence of the Faniour nor a tree glowing with the large and complicated soul that you know Cadaeth to possess. Instead, you find what you presume to have once been a cottage of Oldenlitz, except instead of being torn down it has been almost completely buried by the undergrowth, and you have to look quite closely to see even a single brick beneath the layers of vines, shrubbery, and leaf litter. With some difficulty you identify part of the solid wall of green that the door is buried under and work your wrist through the foliage to knock upon it, and after a moment a vine covering a nearby window twitches aside for a startled and familiar face to peer out at you, before slamming back into position. You carefully keep from laughing and wait patiently until the Vicereine finally emerges, the foliage sliding away from the door as she steps out dressed in leather and bark. "Lady Magister," she says to you in greeting. "I had no forewarning," she pauses to direct a glare upwards at the Mischiefs, which zoom away with a chorus of tinkling laughs, "of your visit." "I apologize for the abruptness, but none of Tor Lithanel could give me a better way to get in touch with the Council of Frost than to wander into your territory, and the sentries on the western road said that you were the most suitable to take the matter to." "And what matter would that be," she says, and you allow her to lead you back into the ruins as the door swings closed and is once more wrapped in green. "The Waystone Project. You were the one that first broached the subject, and though you may have simply been the messenger, I had the impression that you would be interested in the research itself, not just the results." Well, you had a vague idea she might be, but it had just been pretty much confirmed by the road sentries. "We will have the contribution of Lord Hatalath, but though his familiarity with the arcane is clear, he may not possess as grounded a perspective as someone like yourself." "You are correct. I have... some measure of curiosity about the nature of your kind," and you very carefully do not look back at the stolen cottage she had chosen to live within, "and I doubt that even the Grey Lords would know as much about the lornalim as those that tend them." "So you would be willing to join the Project?" "As often as I am able. My children grow strong, but I would not be willing to leave them untended for too long." "If you'll forgive my lack of understanding, would you be representing simply yourself, or the Ward of Frost?" "No one person can represent an entire Ward, but I will serve as a conduit to those within the Ward with greater understanding of relevant matters than myself, if that is your concern." "It is." Or near enough, anyway. The tacit support of the Ward of Frost will serve as one more tool on the belt of the Project. "I was also wondering if you could entertain my curiosity as to the nature of your children. Are you familiar with the standing stones of the Belthani?" She evidently is not, which makes sense - Laurelorn has been continuously occupied by the Elves since before the arrival of the Belthani, so they never would have had any opportunity to erect their runestones within the forest. But you explain the concept to her, and she does confirm that the lornalim fulfil a very similar function to the runestones. You take a great deal of mental notes on what she is willing to reveal about the lornalim, glad that your latest recruit to the Project is already proving as useful as she is charming. --- You spend the chilly months of late winter and early spring working with your employees on various subsets of magical academia. With Max, you alternate between lessons in Altdorf and research in Tor Lithanel as you grapple with the bizarre and confusing world of ritual magic. This field serves the purpose of proving that the Colleges of Magic are far from a thorough understanding of the underpinning logic of magic, as the connections between cause and effect are as tenuous and fleeting as dream logic. It makes a certain amount of vague sense that the blood of a judge might be used in a ritual to force an oathbreaker to follow through on their promise, but trying to look deeper into it than that is a sure path to madness. Why blood, specifically? And why does it need to be written on the skin of a stillborn lamb? Despite involving a great deal of research, the creation of a new ritual is more similar to a fever dream or a vision quest than any form of logical undertaking, and involves many months of meditation, experimentation, and trial and error, and the requirements of it accumulate new and often ungainly accoutrements along the way. By the end of the lessons, you reach the conclusion that neither of you have actually been taught how to perform or invent rituals - you have simply been shown how to get started, and have to let instinct and mysticism take you the rest of the way, and been told in exhaustive detail how terribly it can all go wrong. Both you and Max agree that it would probably be for the best if you never need to engage in ritual, but at least now you have the option. [Skill gained: Ritual. Able to perform rituals, and to attempt to invent entirely new ones.] --- With Egrimm, you take your first tentative step into the art you're thinking of as 'Windherding' by working together to try to enchant a saddle with a Light and Grey spell simultaneously - Shadowsteed to provide a steed to ride upon, and Clarity to keep the rider's mind free of exhaustion for the duration of the ride. Not the most dramatic of enchantments, but both spells are relatively simple, so it should serve as a testbed and proof of concept. [Mathilde Windherding: Learning, 6+29+10(Enchanter)=45.] [Egrimm's contribution: Learning, 92+22=114.] [Miscast roll: Unnatural Aura. Chance of Arcane Mark. Rolling: Shrouded.] That is, it would if you didn't keep flinching and fumbling the Ulgu whenever Hysh got within the same room as it. It seems some foundational lesson that had been drummed into you as an Apprentice had stuck harder than you thought, as every time Egrimm tries to work on his part of the enchantment while you've got a fistful of magic, it takes all your concentration to keep from hastily grounding the Ulgu, and that leaves none of it left to actually do your half of the work. It comes to a head one day as you try to plow through the hesitation and overcompensate, and are barely able to shout a warning that has Egrimm jumping away and grounding his Hysh with a flare of harsh light before the magic tears itself entirely free of your control, some of it exploding into raw magic and the rest burrowing itself deep into your being. The two of you stand there, hands on weapons and senses alert for any sign of Daemons or other malignancy, and after nothing visibly occurs you exhale shakily. "Nothing," you say. "I'm sorry about that." "I'm wearing the wrong outfit to be put off by a little miscasting between friends," he says breezily. "And I get it, I really do. I have the voice of my Master in me screaming to ground the magic and get clear too. I suppose I just have a bit more practice in disregarding mine." You wrap up work for the day and you take yourself back to your quarters on shaky feet. It takes you some time examining yourself in the mirror to notice the difference, but you felt the Ulgu sinking into your soul and you know that something's changed. Eventually you spot that some of the dark wisps that conceal your form are shadow itself clinging to you tighter than usual, rather than simply shadows cast by the smoke that has been drawn to you for some time already. You've acquired the Arcane Mark known as Shrouded, and descended deeper into the grip of Ulgu. [Arcane Mark acquired: Shrouded. Shadows you are in grow deeper and cling more tightly to you. +2 Intrigue.] You return to work, and eventually you manage to eke out possibly the worst enchantment you've ever performed, and only because Egrimm had managed to squeeze his own enchantment into the pommel and left almost the entirety of the saddle for your own sloppy work. Still, the fact that there's no leakage between the two and no disruption of either effect proves that there's merit to what you're attempting, you're confident that if you manage to contribute at least basic competence to a future enchantment you'd be capable of even better things. What will you do with the Nightrider Saddle? [ ] [SADDLE] Give it to the EIC [ ] [SADDLE] Give it to the Hochlander [ ] [SADDLE] Give it to your fief [ ] [SADDLE] Donate it to Stirland [ ] [SADDLE] Donate it to Ulrikadrin [ ] [SADDLE] Donate it to the Undumgi [ ] [SADDLE] Donate it to the Colleges --- With Johann and Egrimm, you sit down to write a paper on your observations of the prosthetic arm. After a few false starts, you and Egrimm take Johann to his quarters to sleep off the concussion he managed to pick up in his latest adventures with Kadoh. It's slightly more difficult to write a paper on the prosthetic with the bearer no longer involved, but you took copious notes and your memories of the investigation are still fresh enough that it doesn't matter too much. You know the paper itself isn't really going to make much difference in the grand scheme of things, as there's only one of these arms and there's unlikely to be any other users of it in the near future, but it's not just utility that makes a paper have an impact, but also novelty. A prosthetic arm of completely unknown origins - no, a prosthetic talon, acquired in hazy circumstances, and stitched onto a bold volunteer? That gets attention. And perhaps there might be some utility to this paper. Though the arm is unwilling to give up its secrets, being able to state for a fact that it's possible for Hysh to interface with the nerves of the human body could make some people more willing to experiment with achieving that, especially since it's confirmed it can be done without harmful leak-through to a non-Hysh Wizard. The Empire has quite a few amputees, and some of them would be in positions to pay quite well for a functional prosthetic, or would be of sufficient importance that the Empire would pay on their behalf. Perhaps one day this paper could lead to some sort of replication of this phenomenon by the Colleges. By the time you and Egrimm wrap up the paper, you're feeling a lot happier about having spent the time to write it than you had been at the start. There is no such thing as useless information, you remind yourself, merely information you haven't found the use for yet. [Mathilde's contribution: Learning, 87+29+10(Fresh)=126.] [Johann's contribution: Learning, 1+19=20.] [Egrimm's contribution: Learning, 39+23=62.] [Observations on a Golden Prosthetic Talon of Unknown Origin, 2488. Subject: Unique, +3. Insight: Revolutionary, +2. Delivery: Compelling, +1. Exotic, +1. Total: +7.] --- On the very few occasions in your life you have gone unnoticed in a crowd, it has been by dint of a carefully-crafted disguise. To be dressed as you usually are and still go unnoticed in the crowd takes a bit of getting used to, as instead of people staying a polite distance as they usually do in Altdorf or Karag Nar, or a wider and more cautious berth as they usually do anywhere else, with the blessing of the Night Prowler coiled around you the crowd flows closely around you like water flows around a rock. It's a deceptively subtle effect, but one with a great deal of utility for those who intend mischief. You spend some time testing the exact extent of the effect and causing a handful of minor disturbances in the street of Altdorf before setting off on your mission to investigate Alric's investigation into the serial murders of members of the Unf채higer dynasty. You arrive at the docks of Taalagad with your supernatural unnoticeability enhanced with a carefully bland disguise of a moderately well-off clerk by way of a ferry from Altdorf whose captain has already had all memory of his brief encounter with you snatched from his mind, and from there you make your way into the tunnel through the rim of the Taalbaston crater that leads into Talabheim proper with the help of a counterfeit letter of passage. According to legend, Taal once encountered and subsequently fought a particularly large and ill-tempered Dragon, with the Dragon's lashing tail carving out the Talabec and the fight ending with Taal throwing the Dragon into the air with so much velocity that its return carved out a crater sixty miles wide. The legend goes on to say that the crater went uninhabited until the arrival of Taal's chosen people, the Taleutens. Noticeably absent from this tale is mention of the Dwarven highway that runs right alongside this allegedly undiscovered crater, the Dwarf-carved tunnel through its walls, and the ruins of the Elven trading city of Athel Maraya that you know for a fact Talabheim is built upon. The supernaturally fertile fields within are simply the result of the Dragon's flesh mixed with the soil, and the fragments of supernaturally tough metals occasionally found by farmers are clearly its scales. All credit goes to Taal. [Examining EIC reports: Learning, 86+29=115.] You casually collect the latest reports from the EIC's agents in Talabheim from a dead drop in an alley and find a moderately upmarket tavern to read them in. You frown as you do so, something about the latest rumours of the terrible fates suffered by members of the Unf채higer dynasty tickling a memory you can't quite reach, and you frown with frustration at being so far away from the shelves of notes you've accumulated over the years. But long meditation and several surprisingly decent local ales eventually uncover why this seems so familiar - the chain of dynastic death seems to be violent parodies of the apparent 'natural causes' that carried off the Haupt-Anderssens of Stirland in rapid succession, and led to the title being vacant for the Van Hals. That is cause for concern. The conspiracy that is likely to have performed the assassinations of the Haupt-Anderssens included the former Empress, and the current incumbent is posing as a part of that dynasty. That matter coming under scrutiny could cause that whole house of cards to come crumbling down. Hopefully nobody else has made that connection yet - the whole matter was classified rather severely, initially because the final genuine Haupt-Anderssen managed to suck himself into the Warp in a botched Daemonic summoning and later even more so due to the connection to the fate of the Vampiric conspiracy. You consider your options carefully as you indulge in another flagon of the best of Hargrinson's Brewery. Vote for as many as you prefer from the below options; the one with the most votes will be taken. The two sections are divided only for legibility. [ ] Approach the Unfahigers openly [ ] Approach the Unfahigers in disguise (specify: as what) The Unf채higers should be scared enough to take any help they can get at this point. [ ] Interrogate the Unfahigers Sneak your way in, interrogate, Mindhole, sneak your way out. [ ] Approach the Hunter's Council They have authority over the City Watch, and the rank to know not to gossip about a Lord Magister of the Grey Order. See what they can tell you. [ ] Approach the local Witch Hunters The Longshanks of Taal are a lot easier for Wizards to get along with than most Witch Hunters, and would know about strange goings-on in Talabheim. [ ] Other (write in) [ ] Approach Alric directly This is too serious to play politics over. Team up with Alric and bury this matter as efficiently as possible. [ ] Bring in Regimand He was both your Master and your partner in dismantling the conspiracy that killed the Haupt-Anderssens, and likely knows more about them than anyone living. [ ] Bring in Heidi As a counterfeit Haupt-Anderssen, this is a matter that she would have a great deal of interest in keeping quiet, and she enough influence to open just about every door there is. - There will be a four hour moratorium. - If I've missed any blindingly obvious destinations for the saddle or approaches to the riddle of the Unfahigers, let me know and I'll add them.

Trouble in Talabheim, Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Bring in Regimand [*] [SADDLE] Give it to the Hochlander Tally There are a variety of ways for a Lord Magister to send an urgent message at considerable speed, but unfortunately none of them were intended to be kept secret from an extremely well-connected Magister Patriarch in good standing. You spend some time balancing stealth against speed and eventually settle on sending a message through the local EIC office, who would be able to find a trustworthy ship captain or reliable messenger bird to send a message downstream to Altdorf, from where the Grey Order can get it on its way to wherever Regimand happens to be. And you know the code-phrases the Hochlander has set up for the local agents, so you don't even need to reveal yourself to the staff of the office. And even if the office is under surveillance it would be reasonable enough for the clerk Alys Schmidt to have business with the EIC. It is technically possible that someone very thoroughly surveilling the office might connect Alys Schmidt to a coded letter being sent by messenger pigeon, extremely unlikely but not completely impossible they'd be able to connect that pigeon's departure to another pigeon's arrival in Altdorf, and perhaps they'd be well-informed enough to know that the apparent receiver of that letter is actually under the employ of the Grey Order, but even then the most likely conclusion that they'd reach is that Alys Schmidt is one of the Hochlander's agents, and the letter being sent to the Grey Order is intended for Lady Magister Mathilde Weber. [Rolling...] Unbeknownst to you, the letter turns right back around in Altdorf and comes back to Talabheim before being handed off to a mounted courier. Not knowing how long you had to wait, you prepare an entire itinerary for Alys Schmidt's visit to Talabheim. First priority, of course, was seeing if you could snatch a glimpse of the local Waystone nexus, but after eyeing the local leylines and consulting a map you suspect it to be the namesake of the sacred grove known as the Horn of Taal within the Taalgrunhaar Forest, and the local Priesthood is rather protective of the place. You do, however, find a Waystone known to the locals as the Obelisk of Laws, upon which local laws and commentary on them are posted, and one of those laws is it's forbidden to remove anything posted on the Obelisk of Laws, so over the years it has accumulated quite a density of faded paper around its base. The part of the Obelisk emerging from the paper is in the same shape and proportions as the Elven Waystones, but is made of black marble and the part of it that is visible is unadorned by runes. You make a mental note of another Waystone oddity and add it to the growing list. You barely have time to also visit the public park of the Taalgarten and the conservatory of the Sea of Roses, taking advantage of the Coin's effects to take a few interesting cuttings for Panoramia while you do so, before your vacation plans are interrupted by an Illusion-clad Regimand arriving at the daily rendezvous point a mere four days after the letter was sent. Alys Schmidt makes a show of greeting him politely while he wraps the two of you in Cloak Activity. "Thank you for coming," you say, as the magic conceals you from prying eyes. "I wasn't expecting you to be here so soon, though." "I was up in Bek, keeping an eye on the biggest agitators for Talabecland-Ostermark conflict over the canals. A favour for Lady Magister Wilhelmine." "I thought that business was settled years back?" "It was, but there's a few sparks left. They'd usually go out on their own if left be, but we can't really trust the Empire's many enemies to pass up such an opportunity to sow discord, can we? So while there's even a hint of bitterness, it's best to keep a careful eye on the situation. But it can wait. What's the trouble here?" You hand over a piece of paper you'd been using to cross-reference the rumours of bloody fates of Unf채higers with the supposedly natural deaths of the Haupt-Anderssens, supplemented by the archives of local newspapers that you'd been breaking into at night. "A chapter that I'd been rather hoping we'd closed." He examines the chart you'd made, his face growing blank. Eight dead Haupt-Anderssens, five dead Unf채higers. "Even the time between the deaths lines up," he observes, "just with months instead of years. Which gives us two months until the next murder." "Someone knows more than they should, and is bringing attention to where it shouldn't be." He considers that for a while. "No," he rebuts simply. "No?" "If they had something on us - either the original business or, Gods forbid, the way we solved it - they'd have either outed it or tried to get their hooks back into us. Instead they're putting on a sanguine pantomime unrelated to anything that would endanger us. Getting involved seems like it has a higher chance of bringing unwanted attention to you and I than just sitting back and letting things play out." He frowns down at the paper. "And that's if that's what's actually happening." "You don't think so?" "It's too much trouble to go to if you don't have to, so I'd say they have to, or they want to. I'd normally say a Spectre or even a Wraith, but considering what happened to the last Haupt-Anderssen Elector Count, I'd say he made new friends where he ended up, and is trying to get his revenge on who he believes to be to blame for his family. He might even be right, the Unf채higers were Elector Counts of Stirland before they were Emperors, they might have thought they'd be the natural choice to re-inherit if the Haupt-Anderssens went extinct." He taps the descriptions of the killings. "The methods seem like the Violent, the pageantry of the Tempter, the echo of past events smacks of the Changer, and the mood this'd be inflicting on the rest of the Unf채higers rounds out the Four. There's been a fair bit of activity from that lot lately, and this is the sort of game They like to play." "And if that was the case..." "Then the perfect man for the job is already on top of it." He eyes you thoughtfully. "What's this really about? You never struck me as the sort to get involved in College politics, and as far as I know you're one of the few of your rank without an axe to grind against Alric." Perhaps you've gotten too used to being distant and inscrutable. Though you've outstripped him in rank, Regimand has known you since you were a girl of ten, and has spent large parts of his life matching wits with beings older, cleverer, and more sinister than you. If you want him in on this, you're going to have to tell him something more. And if it is the last Haupt-Anderssen behind this, then it just became even more important that this be resolved quietly. [ ] Favour to Mira Tell him you're getting involved in this as a favour to Mira in exchange for Light Order assistance with the Waystone Project. While almost true, it does mean the stakes aren't high enough to demand his attention, and he may return to his previous task. [ ] Favour to the Empress Tell him you're getting involved in this as a favour to the Empress, who has a natural interest in the fate of her dynasty. Not exactly a lie, but definitely misleading, and far from the whole story. [ ] It's important Say that it's important, and that's all that you can say about the matter. That would probably be enough to sway him and he would probably understand, but it will also inflame his curiosity. [ ] Say nothing Thank him for his insight, and for putting your mind at rest about the matter, and allow him to return to his business in Bek. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium.

Trouble in Talabheim, Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Favour to Mira Tally "Favour trading with the Light Order for the Waystone Project," you explain. "They've got the largest libraries, good relations with the Witch Hunters, and they were Teclis' favourites. Plus I have reason to believe they've inherited some relevant information from their pre-Teclisean roots. So I went all in to bring in Lord Magister Egrimm van Horstmann and Lady Magister Elrisse." All completely true, but you're leaving out that you could fulfill the letter of your agreement now and the spirit of it with a bit of light surveillance, leading him towards the conclusion that you promised more than simply information. [Does Regimand help? Roll: 78-10(busy)-20(college politics)+100(wants to spend time with Mathilde)=148.] Regimand exhales. "I don't like that you're swimming in these waters, but that's because part of me still sees my Apprentice of twenty years ago, not the Lady Magister in front of me. I trust you to know what you're doing." He drums his fingers on the table as he thinks. "Bek can wait. I'll tap my local contacts and see what I can find out. Usual rendezvous rotation?" You nod. "See you tomorrow." --- Regimand has tailored today's disguise to Alys, and today she is meeting with a plain-looking and middle-aged clerk with ink-stained fingers and an unfortunate taste in hats. "Found them," he says as soon as Cloak Activity forms around the two of you. "The current head of the family and the members in his favour are holed up with Alric in Bad Dankerode, on the external southeastern flank of the Taalbaston." You rack your memory. "The spa town? They're holed up in a spa?" "Not as stupid an idea as it first seems. The waters are believed to come from the same source as Crater Lake, and would therefore be sacred to Taal. A spa full of holy water would be a good spot for a confrontation with Chaos. And it being on the outside of the Taalbaston means it has the usual fortifications that the settlements inside lack, and means it'd see less interference from local authorities." "I suppose he doesn't want to share any of the credit. What about the rest of the family?" "A hunting lodge in the Crater Marsh, near Sumpfrand. Again, holy water, and presumably a fair few weapons. Clear sightlines, difficult to sneak up on. Not the stupidest of plans, I suppose." "Not holed up in the Unfähiger manor?" "They call it Krieglitz Manor, they try to distance themselves from the Unfähiger name these days. And no, that's where all the previous murders happened. They might be hoping that whatever is doing it is stuck there. If it was a Spectre that might work, but I doubt it'd help much." "So the Manor's just sitting empty?" "Sealed tight, nobody wants to be murder number six. Thinking about breaking in and inspecting the murder sites?" "Might be worth doing." Part of you was thinking about breaking in for less salubrious reasons. The Unfähigers bled the Empire white during the reign of Dieter IV, and part of you is tempted to put some of that wealth towards more worthy causes. To banish temptation for the moment, you look back at your notes. "Are you seeing a pattern in who the murderer is targeting?" "Apart from all being members of the family, nothing I can see. Might be random, might be opportunistic." "I don't see anything either. So I'd guess Alric isn't protecting the most likely next victim, simply the most influential one." "Seems that way." He grins at you. "Now, Apprentice," he says in his teaching voice. "If you were the one investigating this, what would you do?" That's the question, isn't it? There are eight weeks until the next murder. You are currently planning what to do for the next three weeks. Each of the below actions will take one week, so you have three actions. Voting will be in plan format. Your implied objective: Limit or prevent Alric getting credit for saving the Unfähigers. Your actual objective: Ensure this matter is resolved without revealing the Empress is not a Haupt-Anderssen. [ ] Bring in the Empress She will bring with her a lot of influence, a lot of skill, a lot of attention, and a lot of questions. But she has quite the vested interest in seeing this wrapped up quietly. [ ] Bring in Lord Magister Egrimm [ ] Bring in Lady Magister Elrisse [ ] Bring in Egrimm and Elrisse What better way to counter a Light Wizard than with one or two of your own? But they do know what you actually promised to Mira, and things could get awkward if they mention it to Regimand. [ ] Renegotiate with Mira If you're going to have to interfere with Alric anyway, you might as well see what Mira is willing to offer for you to do so, and clear the way to bring in your own Light Wizards. [ ] Bring in someone else: specify who You have all sorts of allies, contacts, and favours that you might call upon. [ ] Approach Alric directly Working with him means splitting the credit, which would partly fulfil your implied objective and let you be on hand to perform your actual objective. But while refusing your assistance would put him in an uncomfortable position should he fail, it does mean he'd know you're involved, and he may work against you. [ ] Interrogate the spa Unfahigers Break in, interrogate, Mindhole, leave. Risky and difficult under Alric's nose, but they'd have the most information. [ ] Approach the hunting lodge Unfahigers They've been left to dry by Alric and the head of the family. If you offer help, they're all but certain to take it. [ ] Interrogate the hunting lodge Unfahigers Break in, interrogate, Mindhole, leave. They have no protection against the likes of you, and may know something useful. [ ] Investigate Krieglitz Manor Investigate the sites of the five brutal murders of members of the Unfähiger dynasty. [ ] Plunder Krieglitz Manor It's unstaffed and unguarded, protected only by locked doors, boarded windows, and a sinister reputation. Who knows what riches the Unfähigers squirreled away during their time in power? [ ] Research: Alberich's life For all the time you spent cleaning up the mess he made, you never learned much about Alberich as a person. Find out what sort of ruler he was, and that might give you insight into whatever he is now. [ ] Research: Alberich's fate Abelhelm would have had what happened to the last Haupt-Anderssen looked into. Someone has that report. Maybe Roswita, maybe the Witch Hunters, maybe the Cult of Sigmar. Find it. [ ] Research: Alberich's form Alberich would not have been unchanged from a trip to and return from the Chaos realm. Research what changes may have occurred to him that may help you locate him. [ ] Research: Chaotic Vengeance This would be far from the first time someone's sold themselves to the Dark Gods for vengeance, and the Dark Gods tend to act in patterns. Research earlier examples of the same phenomenon. [ ] Research: Murder Rituals Eight quiet murders in one family in forty years. Eight brutal murders in one family in forty months. This smacks of some sort of ritual. Go digging through every resource you can find for what this might be about, and what might happen if it goes uninterrupted. [ ] Research: Underworld Turbulence 'A fair bit of activity from that lot lately' is not really actionable. See if anyone knows exactly what's got the Chaos cults of the Empire in a tizzy lately. [ ] Other: write in - There will be a four hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - The sections are separated only for legibility, you can take any combination of actions from any section. - If timing is particularly important, specify the order of what is done first/second/third in the plan. Otherwise I'll put it in what I judge to be the most advantageous order. - If the sixth murder occurs on schedule, there will be three weeks until the seventh, then four until the time Alberich disappeared.

Trouble in Talabheim, Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan CoolPlanName -[*] Research: Murder Rituals Eight quiet murders in one family in forty years. Eight brutal murders in one family in forty months. This smacks of some sort of ritual. Go digging through every resource you can find for what this might be about, and what might happen if it goes uninterrupted. -[*] Research: Alberich's fate Abelhelm would have had what happened to the last Haupt-Anderssen looked into. Someone has that report. Maybe Roswita, maybe the Witch Hunters, maybe the Cult of Sigmar. Find it. -[*] Investigate Krieglitz Manor Investigate the sites of the five brutal murders of members of the Unfähiger dynasty. Tally "The timing, the family links, and the means of death all smacks of ritual," you say. "Which is not my strongest suit..." "Kill the one doing them and they tend to end," Regimand advises helpfully. "Noted, but I'd rather go into things armed with a little more than that, so I'm going to head back to Altdorf to do some digging. After that, Alberich himself - Abelhelm had his Witch Hunter contacts doing a lot of digging while I was there, and some of that would have been into his predecessor. The question is where the report would be - if Roswita inherited I've got a good working relationship with her, if it's the Witch Hunters I've got a contact or two there." Well, the Hochlander does. "If it's the Cult of Sigmar, Kasmir or Starke might be able to get their hands on it." "I know a fellow or two I've been on the same side of a battle of that might be able to do some digging." "And after all of that prepwork, I'll have enough information to make an examination of Krieglitz Manor worthwhile. If it is a ritual, then it's still in progress, so I'm hoping I'll be able to pick up something about it at the sites of the first five murders." "That sounds like a solid plan," Regimand says after some thought. "If it was my operation I'd openly throw my lot in with the outcast Unfähigers, but my operation would only be worrying about thwarting the ritual, so it'd see Alric as an asset, rather than a complication." "I still might, that'd muddy the waters enough that Alric wouldn't be able to claim sole credit. Right now I suspect his plans might be to very publicly protect the favoured Unfähigers, let two or three of the unfavoured ones die, and then claim victory after the murders stop. But I worry I might be underestimating him, since a lot of my sources of information on the man are people that have sided against him." "This is why I hate College politics. Because of them, you're in a position where the Magister Patriarch of the Light Order being a good person would be a tricky complication." "Things were definitely simpler down south," you agree. "Normal contact procedures?" "Yes, and use the EIC if there's anything urgent but not sensitive." He nods. "See you in a fortnight," he says, and disappears. Over at the bar, his actual self smirks behind his disguise as he drains his drink. "What do I owe you?" he asks the barman. "A little more credit, for starters," comes your voice from the barman's mouth. --- The thing about rituals is that there are a lot of rituals, even when you're limited to the libraries of the Colleges of Magic. Many of them have never even been used, instead marking the point where a particular effort ended, either from interruption or from the ritual developing components or requirements that the creator was unwilling to pursue. Of those that have been tested and confirmed to work, most never see the outside of the creator's notes which are eventually inherited by their College. But you can dismiss this right away - you're not looking for a sanctioned, legal, wholesome ritual, you're looking for something ugly and evil. To even start asking questions on the matter would cause the asker to be on the receiving end of an investigation, but with rank comes privilege, and you're instead put in front of an extremely vetted librarian of the Grey Order whose job it is to be able to point in the right direction when someone has your kinds of questions, and the price they pay for that ability is that they are never to leave the grounds of the Grey College again, because the knowledge inside their head could catapult any petty Magus or Magicker into being a threat to the entire Empire. You ask your questions and are made to wait as in a locked and warded room, a lectern is prepared so that only a few pages of a specific book are accessible, and then under the placid yet watchful eye of a Perpetual Apprentice you read through those pages and take mental notes only. Then you leave the room, and a new book is prepared. This process takes much longer than you would like, and gives you plenty of time to dwell on the glimpses of those books you can get. Somehow, it's the ones made of normal materials with regular ink handwriting that unnerve you more than those made of all too identifiable vellum and parchment and written in blood. The idea of someone calmly researching, experimenting, and penning the results of violent and bloody rituals in a volume and a hand not that different to your own is more worrying than that of a cackling lunatic scrawling in blood under a green moon. When the Grey Order's books are exhausted you're made to wait once more, and in six other libraries careful copies are made of specific pages of certain books and, in dead of night and under heavy guard, taken through the streets of Altdorf into the Grey Order. These too are left to your examination, and as soon as you're done with them they're set aflame and the ashes carefully gathered. Through all of this notes are taken of every ritual you have witnessed, and if any of them are misused in the years to come, someone will be checking what you were up to at the time. And after reading the rituals, you entirely understand why. If this is just one very specific cross-section of the dark rituals available, it's a miracle the Empire is ever not swarming with Daemons and vengeful ghosts and everything in between. Over days of study, patterns start to emerge. There are all sorts of rituals that require violent human sacrifice, but most just use them in the same way that a fire uses wood. If you operate on the assumption that it is Alberich performing the murders, and that the timing and the relation between the victims is required instead of a bit of personal flair, then this is a ritual of dedication - Alberich is taking the circumstances of his fall to Chaos and reinforcing it. Most of those that come to Chaos can excuse themselves by telling of the tragedies that led them there - in Alberich's case, that his family was pursued by a murderous plot that left him desperate and alone. But by replicating this on another family, and amplifying it in both time and violence, he forever robs himself of all excuses. It is a message to the Chaos Gods: I blot out the circumstances that forced me to you, and forever reject the excuses I could make for my being here. But though this is a neat answer, it is built atop a set of assumptions: that it is Alberich, that the timing is required, and that the relation is required. You do need to make some assumptions at this point or you have nothing to work with, but you destine yourself for failure if you go ahead believing yourself to be correct on all counts. So what if you're only mostly correct? If it is not Alberich? Then it is a summoning. Whoever is doing it, they are attempting to summon either the Daemon that Alberich has become or the spirit that is all that remains of him by replicating the pivotal circumstance of his life, and presumably his ascension or death. Or they're misinformed and there is nothing to summon, or perhaps nothing with the power to respond, and if that is the case then the ritual would leave an opening for something else to step through from beyond. If the timing is not required? Then it is an empowerment, sacrificing eight members of a family to call upon the Violent to empower him - for eight is His holy number. The timing would be pageantry, either out of madness or a sense of drama, or perhaps to catch up the deaths of his family in the resonation as an extra sacrifice to his God. If the family is not required? Then it is a ritual of vengeance, attempting to curse those that killed his own family by replicating the timing of the acts he is calling for vengeance upon. Perhaps Alberich believes the Unfähigers to be responsible, and therefore considers it to be poetic vengeance to use their deaths to fuel a curse upon the rest of the conspiracy. If you were sure this was the case you might be tempted to step aside and let it happen, were it not for the fact that arguably you, Regimand, and Heidi could all be considered to be part of that conspiracy, and there are very few other members left for the power of a curse to focus upon. Dedication, summoning, empowerment, vengeance. A set of unpleasant options to be sure, but the field of possibilities does tend to get that way once human sacrifice enters the equation. You run over your mental notes once more, sign a set of papers acknowledging that you have accessed such unsavoury materials, thank the library staff for their time, and withdraw from the College to seek out some sunlight and cheery thoughts. --- Your arrival in Wurtbad feels a little uncanny, as the crowds part for your Shadowsteed and eyes turn towards you and a sea of murmurs fills your wake. You do your best to ignore it all as you make your way to Eagle Castle, and make your introductions to the guard at the gate and request an audience. The uncanny feeling grows stronger as you're taken inside and led through rooms you once called home to a conference room you once knew very well indeed. But a lot has changed, not least of which being that the conference table itself is gone, which you suppose makes sense, as to those that don't know the story behind it, the bloodstain it bears is merely unsanitary. Roswita herself is showing the passage of years too, for she must be at least partway into her thirties by now. And still unmarried, too, which is unusual for an Elector Countess. Or perhaps she has taken the same path as Abelhelm, and has secret heirs hidden away somewhere, ready to emerge when needed? You let this idle speculation occupy your attention as you make your way through the polite greetings to her and broach the topic at hand. "Ah yes, the matter of the Eastern Wing," she says. "Thirty-odd years left until it's unsealed." "Can you tell me any more about the details of what happened? I know that Abelhelm had Witch Hunters look into it, and I believe it may be related to matters elsewhere in the Empire." "How so?" she asks, her expression shifting, and for a moment you have an odd sense of nostalgia - Abelhelm had that same odd shift in intensity when switching from ruler to Witch Hunter. "Alberich got himself sucked into the warp, yes? Well, he either came back, or is being called back." "That could be very dangerous. Is it being seen to?" "Members of the Grey and Light Orders are working on it," you say truthfully. "Ah," she says, relaxing slightly. "I've seen the effect Light Wizards have on spirits, and I've heard they're just as potent against the denizens of the Chaos realms. I'm afraid that I didn't inherit the report on Alberich's demise, I only know part of the details from father's diary." "You read his diary?" you find yourself asking. "The parts covering his years here, yes. There was a great deal in motion that I had to suddenly be in charge of. For all of his predecessor's missteps, at least he left my father with a blank slate." "Could only have been blanker if he'd pulled apart the castle and sold the stones," you say faintly, trying not to speculate on the contents of those diaries, not sure if you're more worried if she found anything untoward or if there was nothing to find. It's strange, isn't it? A little over a decade since that chapter in your life ended, and most of the time it all feels like the distant past, and you've built a new life and now have something much realer than the handful of half-formed hopes you once had. But if something pokes at those memories just wrong they come to life once more, filling you with a nostalgic sadness and bringing all those if-onlys back to life... but this is far past the time and definitely not the place to lose yourself in those memories. "Would the Witch Hunters have the report, then?" you press on. "I requested it once before, but all they told me is how long to keep it sealed, and that was early on so I didn't feel I was in a position to throw my weight around. And since then, of course, all my focus has been east." She frowns. "But now that you bring it up, I don't like being reminded that I'm sleeping so close to something I know so little about. And I have built up some contacts within the Witch Hunters that know me as the Elector Countess of Stirland, rather than a former trainee. I think I'll have a word with some people. I take it that you'd like to be informed what I learn?" "I'd like that very much. You can contact me-" "Through the EIC. I know." She smiles, and you remember that it's been some time since she was the terrified girl who was so scared of a Wizard that she barely got through firing her without trembling, or the young woman so sure she would die that her soul swam with Shyish. Of course she would know the owners of the trade company that dominates her capital city. "Thank you," you say, simply and sincerely. --- Never one to leave all your eggs in one basket, you also drop in on the Hochlander and ask him to have a word with his own contacts within the Witch Hunters before you make your way back to Talabecland, and in the days to come you receive two messages through the EIC. Two near-identical copies of the same report might strike others as redundant, but to you it's an extremely useful corroboration. It's also interesting that the Hochlander was completely stonewalled until someone asked him if he was asking for you, and in a judgement call he'd answered in the affirmative, and only then had he received the document. Sections are redacted, but these are the sections that describe the exact sigils, glyphs, runes, and circles that would have been involved, and possibly any sacrifices or remains thereof. The relevant parts are found in the mundane remnants, or rather, a significant absence from them: the mortal remains of one Elector Count Alberich II Haupt-Anderssen. The summary of the report draws attention to this, as well as to part of the redacted section that you extrapolate to refer to part of the central circle that was removed, as well as the stone it was marked (or stained, or chalked, or daubed...) upon. The result of this ritual, intended or otherwise, was subtractive: it removed a portion of the material realm, drawing it into the Aethyr. And as you have experience with, portions of the material world drawn into the Aethyr don't like to stay in the Aethyr, so they would have been returned - and, evidently, they were not returned to the eastern wing of Eagle Castle. It is possible that wherever Alberich ended up, he was slain and consumed by the first Daemon that stumbled upon him. But intrusions into the Aethyr are very rarely a surprise to the beings that call it home, and unless Alberich was freakishly skilled or lucky or had somehow stumbled onto an extremely potent ritual, there would have been something of considerable power waiting for him, likely something that resonated with what was already within him. Very likely something that would see more value in having a catspaw in reality than it would one more soul to toy with in unreality. So it seems possible - likely, even - that when that bubble of air and stone returns to the world, it brings Alberich back with it - intact, but certainly not unaltered. After an unknown amount of time, after an unknown amount of changes, Alberich returns to a world that has already moved on from him. Most Daemons will seek to magnify that which is within a mortal, as it is much easier and more effective than creating it from scratch. But what was within Alberich? Was he full of fear and doubt, scrabbling in ignorance at tangled webs of conspiracy that ensnared him, and now seeks to eclipse them through the Changer? Did he despair at the fate of his family, call out to the Diseased, and now seeks to share that sensation with those who inflicted it upon him? Did he rage against those that killed his family, and now blood calls to blood with the approval of the Violent? Or did he act out of jealousy for his perilous position and call out to the Tempter, and now envy drives him to remove the competition for the title that he sees as his right? You might be about to find out. "Your tradecraft has improved," Regimand says from the rooftop beside you. "Didn't even see you until you popped up." "I have my ways," you say vaguely as you consider Krieglitz Manor. Most parts of Talabheim lack the casual defences that you find on even the smallest of homes elsewhere in the Empire, and most of the manors are no exception, favouring large windows and sprawling gardens instead of the miniature castles most nobles favour. Krieglitz Manor is a notable exception, as twenty feet of black basalt would present quite an obstacle to any mundane attacker. You and Regimand, however, are anything but. "Gatehouse?" you suggest. "Gatehouse," Regimand agrees, and a moment later the two of you are atop it. Within the walls are a jumble of different-size buildings around a central courtyard, at the center of which is a rather large fountain that would be quite impressive in daylight and with running water, but here and now the horns of whatever it depicts seem a lot more sinister than its designers would have intended. In between the buildings hedges have overgrown their shapes, turning the slender animals they once depicted into looming, shaggy beasts. "This might take a while," Regimand says. "We have a while," you remind him. "Five deaths, so first to find three wins." The words are barely out of your mouth before Regimand pops away, and you barely get a glimpse of him slipping a pick into a balcony door before he's disappearing inside. You have the Magesight, but he has the experience, and you're genuinely curious who will win. --- [Regimand vs Mathilde: 94 vs 4] You haven't been humbled this badly since you were an Apprentice. "The error of youth," Regimand says as you reach the fifth scene, only to find him reclining against the balustrade and considering a bottle of wine he apparently pilfered along the way, "is to believe that intelligence is a substitute for experience." "How long have you been working on that chestnut?" you ask, refusing to pant even though you started jogging after the second scene he beat you to. "You left me plenty of time for it," he says with a grin, tucking the bottle away in his robes. "I think this is the most recent one, too." "It's clearest to Magesight," you say after considering it. "Looks like they didn't even attempt to clean this one up, either." The fifth Haupt-Anderssen had 'tripped' while going down stairs, while the fifth Unfähiger had made that same fatal journey an amount of times that varied in the telling but was universally too large. Even with only faint moonlight to go by you can see the stains on the stairs, and you can smell the copper tang of old blood in the air. But you frown as you consider it; you'd said it was clearest to Magesight without really thinking about it, but now that you looked at it, what about it was clear is hard to pinpoint. There isn't really any Shyish in the air, but it has been a while since the body was cleared away. Nor any of the other Winds, though the traces left by the emotion of those involved would likewise be long gone. But there's a thinness to the air, an abrasion in the insulating layer between reality and unreality, the tingling itch of the Aethyr being a little closer than usual. "There's definitely something larger at play here," you conclude. "In a vacuum I'd say that maybe this is a trace of some sort of Daemon or spirit or something else at work, but it absolutely matches a groove worn by a ritual." "But wherever the in-progress ritual is localized, it's not here," Regimand says. "Nor was it at the other locations. Does that narrow down the possibilities?" You frown, thinking. "Not by much. It would either be centered on Alberich - well, on whoever's doing this - or on the family." "And this family has been living here less than sixty years," Regimand says. "So their metaphysical location would be on them instead of on their 'home', so it'd be either at the spa or at the lodge, or both." "If it is centered on the family, Alric would know which. But I don't think we can extrapolate which it is from how he's acting, since we don't know if he wants to take this on or let it pass by." "Could you tell by surveilling one or the other?" You consider that. "Not at a glance," you admit. "Not with how worked up they'd be. I'd have to spend a lot of time watching, get used to the Wind turbulence they'd have to be causing to spot what's in the background. It would be a lot easier to spot during the next murder. Even whether it starts getting rowdy in the lead-up to it or if it only perks up when the murder actually happens would tell me something. But if it is centered on the person doing the murders, it would be clearly visible. Even people without Magesight would be uncomfortable around them." Out of thoroughness you carefully inspect the other sites over the next few nights as well as using them to confirm which of the many conflicting rumours were true. The Haupt-Anderssen who'd died during the night of a weak heart had his counterpart's ripped out in bed, and the bed was stripped to the frame and still smelled of blood. The Haupt-Anderssen who'd fallen from a balcony was matched by an impact crater of considerable size below one of the Krieglitz balconies. The Haupt-Anderssen who'd simply keeled over dead midstep must have posed a tricky question for the reenactor, who had done their best to escalate the seemingly rootless death with a stiletto to every organ that left quite a set of stains in a corridor rug. And the Haupt-Anderssen who had seemingly accidentally shot himself while cleaning a gun was matched by the armoury on the grounds, which was emptied of its usual contents as half-hearted attempts to repair the many, many bullet-holes took place and were eventually abandoned. There's absolutely no doubt left in your mind that there's a connection between the Haupt-Anderssen deaths and the Unfähiger deaths. You also take some time to poke around the rest of the Manor while you're there, perhaps hoping you'll find a diary left behind by the family patriarch wherein he recounts his fiendish murders of the Haupt-Anderssens and then extremely detailed accounts of the eventual repercussions, but unfortunately if he kept any such records he's taken them with him. What you do find is a great deal of undeserved finery, including an entire linen closet filled with silk sheets that you give a long, envious glare to. There's also an entire library, and though your sojourn there evaluates it as the sort of thing one gets if you want a library to show off without actually caring what's in it, the sheer size of both it and the layers of dust it bears feels like a grave disservice to the written word. You also spot several voids in the layout of the main building that suggest hidden rooms of some sort, suggesting... well, all kinds of possibilities. Vaults? Forbidden shrines? Hidden dungeons? Secret laboratories? But you're here to observe, not to dismantle, and at least for now you intend to leave the Manor as you found it. --- Alys Schmidt meets once more with an equally-disguised Regimand, and Alys side-eyes her counterpart suspiciously as you very carefully don't look in the direction of Regimand's second illusion of a second disguised version of himself, and your Magesight scans the room for where the actual Regimand must be hiding. But that only has a sliver of your attention, because the rest of it goes to summarizing what you've discovered. Almost certainly a ritual, one of dedication, empowerment, or vengeance. Alberich was bodily taken into the Warp about eighteen years ago, and likely was returned in a different place, possibly in a different time, possibly in an altered form, and almost certainly with an altered soul. "We know one thing that Alric almost certainly doesn't," you say to one of the illusory Regimands. "Even if he does know the link between the Haupt-Anderssen murders and these ones, I'm almost sure he doesn't know that there wasn't an eighth murder. From how the Witch Hunters act it seems like only those with direct involvement in Eagle Castle are considered to have need to know, and the natural assumption for anyone else would be that he was an exceptionally gruesome eighth murder." "So if Alric thinks it's an empowerment, he might be taken by surprise by the seventh murder being the culmination," he says thoughtfully. "He might also believe that the eight is significant, being the number of the Violent. But if it is relevant in that way, it would be seven, that of the Unwell." "If it is Him, then that could take him off-guard. He thinks the seventh is just a stepping stone to an eighth to one God, but it's the culmination to a different one altogether, and one that could be a lot less direct about things and would be able to pollute the water he's relying on for protection." "You're sure it's not a summoning?" "Sure? No. It could be a random misinformed Cultist trying to summon someone that's actually just running around somewhere else. But someone once told me that you don't prepare against an idiot adversary, you prepare against the one that knows what they're doing." "I told you that," Regimand says with a smile. "So you did. If it's not that, then it's a dedication, and then there would be an eighth at the right timing - but it might not be a murder, it could be any act that proves his dedication to his new God or Gods." You frown. "Killing the Magister Patriarch of the Light Order would certainly qualify. That's another way it could blindside Alric - if he thinks he's the bodyguard instead of the target." "Or finally, if it's vengeance. That Alric would be prepared for - maybe thinking it's some other member of the family, since not all..." He frowns and trails off. "Surely not. It couldn't be the..." He looks around, and leans in. "The other one, could it? Your friend, seeking vengeance for her family?" "I'm absolutely sure it's not," you say. Because she's not a Haupt-Anderssen and you know for a fact which God she serves, but you're trying to avoid all that spilling out. He thinks for a while, and slowly nods. "Her role wouldn't really give her time to take a ship up the Talabec to do a spot of murdering every few weeks, would it? But Alric doesn't know that there's a better candidate out there." "He might think she's behind it," you conclude. Revealing that would absolutely catapult him back into influence. It would also tear the Empire apart, but the Magister Patriarch of the Light Order would be in a position to ride that chaos out. Or perhaps he intends to blackmail the Empress and wield her influence as his own. You'd thought it strange that he'd think the Unfähigers were his ticket back to influence, but you'd thought that maybe he couldn't find anything better and was hoping that he could just say 'saving an entire noble family' and skim right past the Unfähiger part. But perhaps he had inadvertently reached a twisted version of the truth, that the Empress was a secret cultist. "Okay, to lay it out: Possibility one. Ritual of Empowerment. Culminates at the seventh murder, Alric will be caught off-guard with his defences useless. Possibility two. Ritual of Dedication. Culminates at the eighth, which may not necessarily be an Unfähiger murder - Alric himself might be the target. Possibility three. Ritual of Vengeance. Culminates at the seventh, which will catch Alric off-guard but will not negate his defences, and this might lead Alric to think the Empress might be behind it. Well, it's a lot more to work with than we had." There are five weeks until the sixth murder. You are currently planning what to do for the next three weeks. Each of the below actions will take one week, so you have three actions. Voting will be in plan format. Your implied objective: Limit or prevent Alric getting credit for saving the Unfähigers. Your actual objective: Ensure this matter is resolved without revealing the Empress is not a Haupt-Anderssen, and without the Empress being implicated in a Chaos Ritual of Vengeance. [ ] Bring in the Empress She will bring with her a lot of influence, a lot of skill, a lot of attention, and a lot of questions. But she now has an even bigger vested interest in seeing this wrapped up quietly. [ ] Bring in Lord Magister Egrimm [ ] Bring in Lady Magister Elrisse [ ] Bring in Egrimm and Elrisse What better way to counter a Light Wizard than with one or two of your own? But they do know what you actually promised to Mira, and things could get awkward if they mention it to Regimand. [ ] Renegotiate with Mira If you're going to have to interfere with Alric anyway, you might as well see what Mira is willing to offer for you to do so, and clear the way to bring in your own Light Wizards. [ ] Bring in someone else: specify who You have all sorts of allies, contacts, and favours that you might call upon. [ ] Scour the city: specify who with If he is responsible, Alberich would have to be hiding somewhere nearby, and his time in the warp would have made him at the very least unsettling, and possibly visibly mutated him. A manhunt might find him, but you'd need to approach someone with the manpower or the authority to perform such a hunt. Some examples would be: the Elector Count of Talabecland, the Cult of Taal and Rhya, the Longshanks, the City Watch, the City Militia, the Taalbaston Guard. [ ] Approach Alric directly Working with him means splitting the credit, which would partly fulfil your implied objective and let you be on hand to perform your actual objective. But while refusing your assistance would put him in an uncomfortable position should he fail, it does mean he'd know you're involved, and he may work against you. [ ] Interrogate the spa Unfahigers Break in, interrogate, Mindhole, leave. Risky and difficult under Alric's nose, but they'd have the most information. [ ] Surveil the spa Unfahigers If the ritual is centred on them, enough observation will tell you what sort of ritual it is. [ ] Approach the hunting lodge Unfahigers They've been left to dry by Alric and the head of the family. If you offer help, they're all but certain to take it. [ ] Interrogate the hunting lodge Unfahigers Break in, interrogate, Mindhole, leave. They have no protection against the likes of you, and may know something useful. [ ] Surveil the hunting lodge Unfahigers If the ritual is centred on them, enough observation will tell you what sort of ritual it is. [ ] Plunder Krieglitz Manor It's unstaffed and unguarded, protected only by locked doors, boarded windows, and a sinister reputation. You've spent several days prowling its corridors without trouble and have a good idea where the squirreled-away riches of the Unfähigers might be found. [ ] Ransack Krieglitz Manor Tear open every secret nook and cranny and scour every inch of the Manor for anything relevant without any care for how much of a mess you leave in your wake, but without taking a single thing with you. [ ] Research: Alberich's life For all the time you spent cleaning up the mess he made, you never learned much about Alberich as a person. Find out what sort of ruler he was, and that might give you insight into whatever he is now. [ ] Research: Alberich's form Alberich would not have been unchanged from a trip to and return from the Chaos realm. Research what changes may have occurred to him that may help you locate him. [ ] Research: Underworld Turbulence 'A fair bit of activity from that lot lately' is not really actionable. See if anyone knows exactly what's got the Chaos cults of the Empire in a tizzy lately. [ ] Leave Chances are that this is already primed to blow up in Alric's face. Perhaps being a province away when it does would be for the best. [ ] Other: write in - There will be a three hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - The sections are separated only for legibility, you can take any combination of actions from any section. - If timing is particularly important, specify the order of what is done first/second/third in the plan. Otherwise I'll put it in what I judge to be the most advantageous order. - If the sixth murder occurs on schedule, there will be three weeks until the seventh, then four until the time Alberich disappeared.

Trouble in Talabheim, Part 4

Spoiler: Voting results [x] Plan: Ritual Centre -[x] Surveil the spa Unfahigers If the ritual is centred on them, enough observation will tell you what sort of ritual it is. -[x] Surveil the hunting lodge Unfahigers If the ritual is centred on them, enough observation will tell you what sort of ritual it is. -[x] Research: Alberich's life For all the time you spent cleaning up the mess he made, you never learned much about Alberich as a person. Find out what sort of ruler he was, and that might give you insight into whatever he is now. Tally "We've learned enough, fast enough, that we have the privilege of spending even more time to really nail down the corners," you say. "I'm going to surveil the Unfähigers, try to spot where the ritual is centered. If it's on one group or the other, then the ritual needs a specific target, and that would probably make it a Ritual of Dedication. If it's over both of them, then it's targeting the family in general and it's probably a Ritual of Vengeance. If it's not, then it would be on the person doing it, and so probably a Ritual of Empowerment. I also want to look more into Alberich himself, find out what kind of person he was and so what kind of new friends he might have made." Regimand nods. "I take it you've got contacts down south that would be able to tell you that?" "Yes, the Baron of Blutdorf is a friend, and through him I can get the impressions of the other rulers of Western Stirland." "Then I'll poke around Wurtbad for the perspectives of those below him. You only ever get half the picture of who someone is if you only know how they treat their equals." The two of you stare at each other for a while, each waiting for the other to vanish first. Then you both realize at about the same time that you'd both tried the same double bluff, actually coming to the table in person but wrapped in an Illusion to make it seem like you were an Illusion. Without speaking or making eye contact the two of you stand from the table and walk away. --- You spent some time weighing which branch of the family to surveil first, but in the end, it comes down to that after a week in the swamp you would really be able to use a week in a spa town. So Alys Schmidt decides to test her luck against the wildlife of Crater Marsh, and hires a room, a punt, and a flintlock fowler musket from the village of Sumpfrand, which likely exists solely to perform this exact service. She politely listens with half an ear as the publican speaks at length at the proper way to carve a sapling into an angling rod, and finally extricates herself from the conversation before the dawn fog burns completely off the marsh, and nobody is watching to notice how the fog doesn't part for Alys, but instead draws in thicker around her. Crater Marsh, you quickly find, is a far more welcoming set of wetlands than the Schadensumpf. Where that body has been cultivated by Elves over millennia to be as hostile to an interloper as possible, Crater Marsh has been cultivated by Taalites and Rhyans over millennia to not be actively unpleasant to live next to, and apart from the occasional mosquito your Aethyric Armour goes quite untested. The chirp of birds and the croak of frogs makes for quite a pleasant chorus, and while poling the punt does take some effort, it's much less than your sword drills do, and you make good time. Regimand had pinpointed the location of the hunting lodge on a map for you, and navigating by the morning sun leads you straight to it. With your punt half-aground on a small mound and shrouded in the mist that's too fond of you to burn away in the rising sun, you make yourself as comfortable as you can, make a mental note to bring a hat tomorrow, and focus your senses on the hunting lodge of the Unfähigers. One early complication is that there's far more coming and going than you expected, as you expected none at all. But your initial count of twelve humans and a dog has to be adjusted downwards as three of them depart shortly before noon, causing you to wonder if they're not as holed up as you thought they would be. But further comings and goings through the day shed some light on this, especially after a rowboat - small for a river but large for a marsh - propelled by a half-dozen burly armed men and carrying an older man with a sack of money arrives, and after a while inside the house these visitors depart minus the sack. Later in the day another rowboat drops off an assortment of sacks and crates and barrels. By the time the sun is starting to set once more and a new set of overnight visitors arrive, these ones in a state of artful deshabille instead of the genuine rumpledness of those departing in the morning, you realize what is happening here. You suppose it makes sense. There's only so long a person can maintain a state of mortal terror, and after weeks holed up without anything eventful happening boredom would rear its ugly head, and nobility like the Unfähigers aren't accustomed to keeping themselves quietly entertained. The controller of the family purse-strings may have cut this branch of the family tree off, but that doesn't mean they're without resources. Just as a peasant knows how to keep an eye out for Beastmen active in the area and how best to placate them, a noble knows when it's time to fill a pillowcase with the family jewels, and now those jewels are being sold off piecemeal to fund deliveries of food, drink, and entertainment. On the way back you use the last fading vestiges of daylight to gather what seems to you to be a reasonable result of a day on the Marsh. Fish don't have terribly much going on in their souls for your Magesight to see, but their passage through the ambient Ghyran of the Marsh is as visible as, well, as the wake of a fish through water. You were warned that these beasts were quite canny in their ability to nibble the bait off a hook, but they prove quite vulnerable to ropes of pure darkness delving into the water to strangle them unconscious, at which point you simply pluck them from the water. Your Marksdwarf pistol also plays a part, adding a brace of ducks to your day's tally at a range the fowler musket could only dream of. You quickly learn that you may have overestimated what a typical hunt results in, as the basket of fish in one hand and the brace of ducks in the other results in shock and then pride from the publican, who assumes the secret to your success was his own sage advice and purchases your catch off you for a fee that outweighs what you spent on equipment, room, and board. You suppose you're starting to see the appeal of this 'hunting' business. Over the rest of the week you accustom yourself to the auras of the Unfähigers during the day, the shifting morass of Shyish and Ulgu being kept at bay by a bulwark of Aqshy, and in doing so you are able to let it fade from your sight, as you do the busy Ghyran of the waters surrounding you. In doing so you discover the faint glow of divinity underlying the Ghyran that you take to be the blessing of Taal, which while spread thin is possibly enough to dissuade lesser Daemons from venturing through it. But you don't spot the lurking presence of a malign ritual, even after every other energy has faded. After five murders, there's no possibility of it being so minor that it would still be unspottable to you, not after a week of watching. You can say for sure that wherever the energies of the ritual are building, they're not here. --- Bad Dankerode is outside the crater of the Taalbaston and thus technically exposed to the horrors of the Great Forest, but with the undiluted holy waters of the Ostlichrand on one side, the sheer cliff of the Taalbaston on the other, and the guns of the Taalbaston's Eastern Bastion overhead, you can see why Alric chose this as his fortress. But while he and the Unfähigers have claimed the largest, most expensive, and best defended spa resort for their own, the rest of the village goes untouched by their influence, and you pick the rival resort that gives you the most unobstructed view of your target for Alys Schmidt to patronize. After a week of sitting on damp wood and trying to ignore the whine of insects as you focused, you're really in the mood to appreciate a more relaxed setting for your next surveillance. Places like this are quite used to dealing with the eccentricities of patrons, and when accompanied with a few coins your requirements are accepted without comment. A room with an adjoining private pool is set aside, lunch is to be covered and placed just inside the door for you to collect at your leisure, and you will not be requiring any professional company for the duration of your visit, nor will you be expecting visitors. You take some time to clean off the accumulated grime of a week in the marsh, then you make yourself a great deal more comfortable than you were capable of achieving in the marsh and turn your senses to the nearby building, where five Unfähigers, one Light Wizard, and an unknown number of servants reside. This close to the source the blessing of Taal is all the more evident in the waters, and you're sure it would be quite an advantage to a seasoned Abjurer on the defensive, but to you it is the first of the distractions you need to learn to filter out before you can find the answers you're looking for. The comings and goings of other patrons is next for you to ignore, but once you begin to filter them you start to be able to see Alric himself, shining like a lighthouse as he moves around the building and occasionally flaring as he makes some preparation or another. Once you've learned to tune out his illumination and gotten used to bracing your senses against his magics, the next layer of observation is picking out the Unfähigers from the servants, which is made easy by the emotions of these Unfähigers running just as hot as their less-favoured counterparts. Once you've honed in on those five you begin to make out what's lurking behind it. [Magesight: Learning, 79+29=108.] Hovering overhead like a gathering storm is a deep well of malign energies, with tendrils reaching out for one of the five Unfähigers in particular, inching closer by the day at a rate that will have him within striking range right on schedule, and growing stronger on their fear all the while. The Ritual knows its target and its timetable, and far above, a tendril of the ugly cloud vanishes into the distance somewhere to the northwest, where the creator of these energies waits for the proper time to come. This is a Ritual that mirrors the fates of the Haupt-Anderssens, and thus by your earlier research you can say with near certainty that this is a Ritual of Dedication, crafted as a piece of terrible art to be gifted to Alberich's new master or masters as a symbol of his devotion to them. You spend as long as you can bear studying the ongoing ritual in the hopes of gaining some insight into its intended audience, but until it is completed it possesses none of the nature of the Dark Gods, just the hideous energies of the death and terror that has been inflicted to create it. At last you turn your gaze away from it, letting reality rush back in and insulate you from it. Hopefully you'll be able to gather some insight of who Alberich was as a ruler that will tell you about who he may have chosen as his patron. The next morning you pack up your things, leave a few discarded and crumpled papers that match Alys' profession, and put some distance between you and Bad Dankerode - first by carriage, and once a safe distance away, you summon your Shadowsteed and turn your course southwards. --- As much fun as it is to appear unexpectedly, courtesy won out this time, and when you arrive in Blutdorf Anton is ready to welcome you. Apart from the usual greetings and gossip he has an important introduction to make to you: that of his first cousin twice removed and now adopted son, Anton. "The name was his idea," Anton says to you after the boy makes a formal and overawed greeting to you and is allowed to flee. "He's very earnest and serious about everything, I don't think he's capable of doing anything halfway. He was an ensign aboard a Wolfship in the Imperial First and doing quite well at it." "What made you decide to adopt?" "The rest of the family was starting to notice I hadn't married and beginning to fight amongst itself over who would inherit, and this was the best way to stop them." He shrugs with an easy and apparently genuine smile. "I just don't feel like there's an absence in my life that terribly needs filling with a wife. Reinhild and I enjoy each other's company, but it's not going to result in a marriage, nor in an heir if her amulet works the way the Jades say it does. And Blutdorf and Kirchham are happy to take every scrap of attention I can spare them. So why roll the dice with a new child when there's a perfectly good one ready to go?" You nod. "As long as you're happy, then that seems very sensible." "I thought so too. Da grumbles, but he likes Anton. Speaking of, you wanted to know about Alberich from him?" "If he's available." Anton hesitates a moment. "He's okay with day-to-day things, but his memory needs nudging for things that far back. So I did the nudging for you before you arrived. He gets embarrassed about it when it's in front of other people." "That's okay, I trust you to have found the salient details." Quite a lot of them, and carefully collated in written form, you quickly discover. Alberich only ruled for four years, but despite his youth he made quite a terror of himself to everyone around, proving as easy to slight as he was long to forget them. One common theme you gather from these recollections, which is reinforced as replies to the letters Anton sent off to his fellow nobles come trickling back in, is that above all else being overlooked infuriated him, and he appeared to spend more time nursing grudges against the elder Elector Counts of Talabecland and Averland than he did worrying about the fate of his predecessors. Prone to anger, but it was gnawing resentment, not the violent rage that characterized one of the four. Did not appear to be drawn into the web of intrigue that claimed his family, and only interacted on a surface level with the equally elaborate string of relationships between the nobility of the Empire. If he despaired he did not show it, nor did he seem inclined to give in to his fate. If anything points to a single being he may have fallen into the sway of, it was that he may have been ensnared by Paramountcy, the allure of power and command, one of the Six Deadly Seductions of the Tempter. It's a possibility, but as you compare notes with Regimand back in Talabheim, not the only one. Regimand managed to dredge from the memories of former servants of Eagle Castle that as a ruler Alberich did not seem to seek out adulation, instead being enraged at a lack of what he saw as the respect his rank deserved. This may fall under the heading of Paramountcy, but it also could signify a relationship with power in its rawest form, rather than the individual flavours of it wielded by the four. If he seeks power itself, why would he narrow down his options by ruling out three of the four Dark Gods? "Alberich," you summarize, "is performing a Ritual of Dedication to either the Tempter or to Chaos Undivided, with the next victim already selected and under Alric's guard, and Alric is certain to know who it is going to be. The penultimate victim is going to be likewise identifiable to Alric, but the culminating act of the Ritual would be a lot more freeform, which Alric is unlikely to be expecting - and that act might target Alric himself. Alberich himself is somewhere northwest of Bad Dankerode, so the most likely location would be hiding within the local population of Talabheim, with Talagaad as an unlikely but possible alternative - the only other possible locations in that direction within Talabecland are sacred to Taal." There are two weeks until the sixth murder. You are currently planning what to do for the next two weeks. Each of the below actions will take one week, so you have two actions. Voting will be in plan format. Your implied objective: Limit or prevent Alric getting credit for saving the Unfähigers. Your actual objective: Ensure this matter is resolved without revealing the Empress is not a Haupt-Anderssen, and without the Empress being implicated in a Chaos Ritual of Vengeance. [ ] Bring in the Empress She will bring with her a lot of influence, a lot of skill, a lot of attention, and a lot of questions. But she now has an even bigger vested interest in seeing this wrapped up quietly. [ ] Bring in Lord Magister Egrimm [ ] Bring in Lady Magister Elrisse [ ] Bring in Egrimm and Elrisse What better way to counter a Light Wizard than with one or two of your own? But they do know what you actually promised to Mira, and things could get awkward if they mention it to Regimand. [ ] Renegotiate with Mira If you're going to have to interfere with Alric anyway, you might as well see what Mira is willing to offer for you to do so, and clear the way to bring in your own Light Wizards. [ ] Bring in someone else: specify who You have all sorts of allies, contacts, and favours that you might call upon. [ ] Scour the city: specify who with You know that Alberich is somewhere northwest of Bad Dankerode, which means Talabheim or Talagaad, and his time in the warp would have made him at the very least unsettling, and possibly visibly mutated him. A manhunt might find him, but you'd need to approach someone with the manpower or the authority to perform such a hunt. Some examples would be: the Elector Count of Talabecland, the Cult of Taal and Rhya, the Longshanks, the City Watch, the City Militia, the Taalbaston Guard. [ ] Ready forces: specify what Bring a significant number of people to Bad Dankerode to be ready to move in on the night of the next murder, such as local military or Witch Hunters or mercenaries. Mathilde's rank means that her word will be sufficient if she says there's something bad about to happen that needs foiling. [ ] Approach Alric directly Working with him means splitting the credit, which would partly fulfil your implied objective and let you be on hand to perform your actual objective. But while refusing your assistance would put him in an uncomfortable position should he fail, it does mean he'd know you're involved, and he may work against you. [ ] Surveil Alric While surveiling the spa, you saw Alric wielding Hysh on a number of occassions, which indicates spells, wards, or short-term enchantments being set up. Study what these might be from a distance. [ ] Interrogate the spa Unfahigers Break in, interrogate, Mindhole, leave. Risky and difficult under Alric's nose, but they'd have the most information. [ ] Approach the hunting lodge Unfahigers They've been left to dry by Alric and the head of the family. If you offer help, they're all but certain to take it. [ ] Interrogate the hunting lodge Unfahigers Break in, interrogate, Mindhole, leave. They have no protection against the likes of you, and may know something useful. [ ] Plunder Krieglitz Manor It's unstaffed and unguarded, protected only by locked doors, boarded windows, and a sinister reputation. You've spent several days prowling its corridors without trouble and have a good idea where the squirreled-away riches of the Unfähigers might be found. [ ] Ransack Krieglitz Manor Tear open every secret nook and cranny and scour every inch of the Manor for anything relevant without any care for how much of a mess you leave in your wake, but without taking a single thing with you. [ ] Research: Alberich's form Alberich would not have been unchanged from a trip to and return from the Chaos realm. Research what changes may have occurred to him that may help you locate him. [ ] Research: Underworld Turbulence 'A fair bit of activity from that lot lately' is not really actionable. See if anyone knows exactly what's got the Chaos cults of the Empire in a tizzy lately. [ ] Leave Chances are that this is already primed to blow up in Alric's face. Perhaps being a province away when it does would be for the best. [ ] Other: write in - There will be a three hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - You cannot follow the ritual's trail all the way to Alberich in the time you have available - it takes days for you to be able to spot it at any given point, so it would take you several weeks to be able to follow it as far as Talabheim, and that's if he stays obligingly immobile for that entire duration. - There will be a final vote for what to do at the scheduled time of the murder. You don't need a readying action for Regimand or any other Wizards you might have recruited to be able to act on that night.

Trouble in Talabheim, Part 5

Spoiler: Voting results [X] Plan Close the Noose -[X] Scour the city: The Longshanks You know that Alberich is somewhere northwest of Bad Dankerode, which means Talabheim or Talagaad, and his time in the warp would have made him at the very least unsettling, and possibly visibly mutated him. A manhunt might find him, but you'd need to approach someone with the manpower or the authority to perform such a hunt. Some examples would be: the Elector Count of Talabecland, the Cult of Taal and Rhya, the Longshanks, the City Watch, the City Militia, the Taalbaston Guard. -[X] Research: Alberich's form Alberich would not have been unchanged from a trip to and return from the Chaos realm. Research what changes may have occurred to him that may help you locate him. Tally The Holy Order of the Templars of Sigmar have their headquarters in the Great Temple of Sigmar in Altdorf, not to be confused with the Great Cathedral of Sigmar. It is a large and imposing structure more resembling a castle than a traditional temple, and quite a number of those that are taken into it are never seen to emerge again. But while its labyrinthine network of subterranean gaol cells and crypts are the most infamous part of the structure, the above-ground portions of the Temple house the more prosaic elements of the Order, including the accumulated paperwork of every report made by the Templars since Magnus the Pious ordered their centralization and partial secularization. Somewhere in all of that is the unredacted report on the events in the Eastern Wing of Eagle Castle, and somewhere in that you hope to find a key detail that may lead to Alberich being found. You have to imagine that the Great Temple does not receive many unexpected visitors, and fewer still from the Colleges of Magic. But despite the tension and distrust between Templars and Wizards, the two were bound by Magnus to be allies in their defence of the Empire. Article 14 of the Articles Of Imperial Magic requires Wizards to render necessary aid to the Templars who are faced with malignancy beyond their capabilities, and Article 15 establishes that the primary concern and purpose of the Colleges is for Magisters to seek out and counter that which is beyond the means of the Templars. Despite this, when the novice Witch Hunter who is the day's doorkeeper responds to your knock and finds a Lady Magister in the signature hat of his Order, he seems quite lost for how to react. "I am Lady Magister Mathilde Weber of the Grey Order, and I would like to see someone in authority here on matters relating to my Article 15 obligations," you say to him. He stares at you for some time before answering. "I beg your indulgence whilst I fetch someone for you," he finally says, and the door swings shut once more. You wait patiently as he presumably finds his Master to ask what to do, who would then seek out his Captain, who would seek out a Chamberlain, and possibly further still. When he finally emerges once more, it is with the comforted air of someone who has sent a problem up the chain of command and had it replaced with a simple instruction. "If you would be so kind as to follow me, the Councillor is available to see you now." You are taken through bare stone corridors while you try not to look too on the lookout for any sign that your path is heading towards downward staircases, and eventually led to an unmarked office. The room is not made for meetings, consisting of a desk against one wall and many overstuffed bookshelves, but a second chair has been dragged in from somewhere. The man inside wears a black robe trimmed with yellow instead of the armour Witch Hunters favour while seeking their prey, and his face is dominated by a mass of twisted scar tissue peeking out from beneath a skull plate, an eye patch, and a prosthetic nose, telling of some past injury that must have almost claimed his life. It is customary among military men that eye patches bear the heraldry of their regiment, and instead of that of the Templars his bears a skull over two crossed cannons. You don't recognize it, but you'd guess a Nuln regiment. "Lady Magister," he says in a rasping voice. "I am Sir Philipp Freytag, Knight of the Inner Circle. I take it this is related to the Alberich business?" "It is," you say as you take a seat across from him. "You are familiar with it?" "As anyone can be who was not there. I reviewed the investigation after both the Elector Countess and your agent started asking after it, and redacted the reports that you ended up receiving." "That is the topic that brings me here today. I need some of the information that was left out of the copies of the report I read." His one eye narrows in suspicion. "The Templars are dedicated to expunging rituals like that from the world. We will not betray the purpose of this Order by spreading it further, particularly to one who has the skills to succeed where Alberich failed." Though he hasn't outright insulted you, he's come very close doing so. "I don't care to know how the ritual is performed. Keep to yourself the runes and incantations and the precise vocation and marital status of the sacrifices. What I need to know is what mark the ritual would have left upon he that performed it." The look of suspicion vanishes from the Templar's face, replaced with a look of calculation. "Alberich has returned," he realizes. "At minimum he has been returned for years, and now I find myself bound by Article 15 to act against one who has demonstrated himself beyond the means of Sigmar's Templars to counter. Will you stand in the way of me doing so?" [Rolling...] The Templar considers you for some time. "One of Alberich's accomplices was captured alive," he finally says, "and they had the Witchsight to witness the encounter between Alberich and his patron. The full testimony is long and repugnant and riddled with traps for the unwary mind, but it did include the physical changes Alberich underwent. His right arm swelled to several times its original size, and one of his eyes turned completely white. He also acquired a distinctive smell that the accomplice described positively, though considering the source that description should be taken as suspect." You smile thinly. "Thank you, Sir Freytag. That will be of great assistance." "Should you locate him, the Templars would, as ever, be standing ready to do their duty." You have a more suitable organization in mind, but you simply nod. "A good day to you." --- During Alberich's time as an Elector Count, he sat for a portrait that would have been displayed somewhere in Eagle Castle had he lost the position under less murky circumstances. But having spent time in Eagle Castle, you know for a fact that nothing ever gets thrown away there, just moved into an attic or cellar and forgotten about. Sure enough, Eagle Castle's staff were eventually able to uncover it. But a single picture is no good for a city-wide manhunt, and so you escort it back to Altdorf and into the University. Technically a Grey Wizard has no authority to make demands of the faculty of the University of Altdorf, but when all you demand is the time of some of their students of the Division of Arts, the bemused faculty apparently see no reason to resist. When you return to Talabheim several days later, it is with woodcuts of the more accurate depictions, both of how he appeared in the portrait and how he might appear if he had experienced the flow of time since then. The Templars of Taal known as Longshanks famously swear an oath to never spend more than a week in one place, but the necessity of bureaucracy means that those who rise to leadership amongst them are inducted into the Order of the Antler, the main order of Taal's priesthood, so they can remain in one place to oversee a specific area of Taal's domain. Their headquarters are within Talabheim's Temple of Taal, the only temple to Taal that is a building instead of a grove or stone circle. It is an odd place, as the wooden walls grow branches here and grass does the job of carpet. Here you seek the Hunter Lord of the Longshanks, and you seem to have little trouble doing so as none of the resident priesthood seem at all put off to see a Wizard among them. You do, however, have to wait for him to finish living up to his title and return from the Sacred Forest, and politely listen to him recounting exactly how large the stag that eluded him allegedly was. As soon as you tell him your reason for being here, Lord Goran Beyer sheds the joviality and transforms into the other form of hunter. By the end of the day, every Longshank present within the city has been given dispensation from the Wandering Vow, a copy of the portraits, and the authority to rally the Horned Hunters and the Knights of the Stag, with the former forming an invisible cordon around the city of Talabheim and the latter scouring the much smaller town of Talagaad. The next day, the Taalbaston Guard have added another requirement for passage through the crater wall on top of proof of citizenship or letter of passage: not looking like either of two pictures and subjecting themselves to examination of their right arm. And the average height of the city of Talabheim goes up a fraction of an inch as every auxiliary of the Tunnel Brigade finds themselves called up to watch every other way through the crater wall. And the day after that is Festag, and from the great Temple of Verena to the tiny shrine to Manann, there is a single unifying theme in every sermon: have you seen this man? Have you seen a person with a monstrously oversized right arm? At that point, all pretence of moving quietly is discarded. The Longshanks, reinforced by Taal's Chosen and the Kin of Taal, begin to kick in a great deal of doors that usually go unkicked by the City Watch, and very pointedly ignore the various petty crimes discovered thereby. The message penetrates through the underlayers of society: firstly that this isn't about them, so they've no reason to obstruct the search, and secondly that it's being taken very seriously indeed, so if anyone is sheltering the person in question they should probably rethink their choices. Though no faithful comes forward with a report on Alberich and he is not found behind any of the kicked-in doors, you find yourself not entirely dissatisfied. Alberich is somewhere within Talabheim, and as deep and well-hidden as his hidey-hole apparently is, the night is rapidly approaching where he needs to either emerge and slay an Unfähiger or see a ritual years in the making begin to fall apart at the seams. And to get to any Unfähiger he needs to travel through streets filled with people who know his face, and then through either the Tunnel Brigade on their home turf, or through the Horned Hunters of Taal through theirs. And you'll be waiting for him to do so. Where will Mathilde be on the night Alberich has to commit the next murder? [ ] With the Longshanks Patrol the streets of Talabheim with the Longshanks, waiting for Alberich's emergence. [ ] With the Tunnel Brigade Presume that Alberich is still going to attack his chosen quarry, and try to intercept him as he crosses the Taalbaston. [ ] With the Horned Hunters Presume that Alberich will give up on his chosen quarry and will instead seek to slay one of the Crater Marsh Unfähigers, and try to intercept him as he leaves the city towards them. [ ] With the Hunter Lord If any force encounters Alberich, it will be reported back to the Hunter Lord of the Longshanks. Stand ready to respond to that report. [ ] Outside Bad Dankerode However he gets out of Talabheim, he has to come to Bad Dankerode to complete the ritual. Be ready for him to do so. [ ] Outside the Hunting Cabin If he's rattled, he might resort to a less protected target. Be ready for him to do so. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Regimand will be with Mathilde if 'Longshanks' or 'Hunter Lord' is chosen, and covering the opposite possibility if 'Tunnel Brigade'/'Horned Hunters' or 'Bad Dankerode'/'Hunting Cabin' is chosen.

Trouble in Talabheim, Part 6

Spoiler: Voting results [*] With the Longshanks Patrol the streets of Talabheim with the Longshanks, waiting for Alberich's emergence. Tally Altdorf's nightlife has something of a reputation, but Talabheim proves easily its equal. Surrounded as it is by stone cliffs and holy forest one need not fear some unholy terror slipping through a crack in the more modest walls most cities are protected by. The streets at night are free of the fog that so often dominates Altdorf and patrolled by the fiercely dedicated and Ulrican City Watch, a holdover from the Ar-Ulric's interregnum in Talabheim who are too threatened with being subsumed by the Taalite Taalbaston Guard to decay into laziness and corruption like so many others. Though one can occasionally pick out the quiver and leathers that marks a hunter in the crowd, it would be very easy for just about anybody to fade into the crowds of those patronizing the nocturnal industries and slip unseen past the searchers. A clever quarry would not take this at face value, however. A clever quarry would eventually turn their eyes upwards, and if they have more than mundane senses to see they might spot the roving patch of Ulgu that scans the streets for a period, only to disappear completely and reappear somewhere else. But no matter how keen the senses of the watcher, they can only be in one place at a time, and one need only wait until the presumed architect of this manhunt moves on and then the way will be clear for them to pass unhindered. [Hunting Alberich: Intrigue, 61+27+10(Windsage)-10(crowds)=88 vs 37+32-10(arrogant)-10(visibly mutated)=49.] Or so they might think. While one Grey Wizard hunts from high above and using the signature magic of their Order, a second lurks among one particular crowded street, the only one you can reach from the slums of the Tallows and the warrens of the Ratholds beyond without passing through a Longshank cordon. Even the most suspicious of gazes slides right past her, clad though she is in elements of two groups anathema to the man she seeks, as she is shielded by a power older and greater than that of the Grey Order. None around her suspect that at any moment a Dwarven blade might manifest in her hand, ready to deliver justice to- Your idle internal monologue is interrupted by the enticingly sweet scent wafting out of the sedan chair passing by you, which turns cloying and sickly in your nose until you have to resist the urge to sneeze. These enclosed litters are quite popular amongst nobles who have business that takes them into streets too narrow for a carriages, and renting them is quite popular amongst nobles who can't afford to buy them but still wish people to think them capable of doing so. For this reason they have a set of hooks upon which their latest customer's heraldry can be hung, and though the hooks are currently bare, sketched onto the cart in charcoal is a skull above a hunting horn. You've heard a lot about the alleged self-destructive nature of Chaos, but someone putting their personal heraldry upon their hiding place while the subject of a manhunt is as pure a demonstration as you're likely to find. Truth be told, you'd have trailed this sedan chair even without that - it wouldn't even be the first conveyance of the night to draw your attention for an odd smell, though the previous example was merely a noblewoman who had over-perfumed to try to cover up just how many drinks she'd had at the theatre - but that charcoal sketch clinches it. You slip into the wake of the sedan chair and focus your senses until you're able to make out the deeply sullied soul within, and even the odd angle they're sitting at to accommodate their grossly oversized right arm. The porters, as far as you can tell, are not ensorcelled in any way, though it will be the Longshanks' job to determine how they were compelled into taking such a forbidden cargo. You could act now, though the crowds might make it tricky. Or you could wait, and hope that his course takes him somewhere more advantageous for you, instead of less. You don't know what his plan is to get out of Talabheim tonight, but it could very well involve accomplices. Kill him He is a Magus and Daemonologist. He has thoroughly earned death, and is too dangerous to let live. [ ] Kill: Branulhune Attack here and now, bisecting both sedan and Magus with a single swing. The crowds will complicate matters, but at least they are a known variable. [ ] Kill: Shadow Knives Shadow Knives can pass through armour, so the thin wood of a sedan chair's wall will pose no obstacle. Riddle Alberich with magical knives. If you do it from the right angle the porters might not even notice that their passenger has died. [ ] Kill: Dragonflask Wait for the sedan chair to leave the crowd, then subject it to Bright College artifice. [ ] Kill: Other (write in) Capture him Alive he will be the more impressive prize, and he could be convinced to reveal who taught him decades ago and who has sheltered him since. The Longshanks, like all Witch Hunters, have the accoutrements to render a magic-user helpless. [ ] Capture: Throttle If you walk alongside the sedan chair, it would be possible to ensnare Alberich with the spell Throttling and choke him unconscious. He might make a fuss while you do so, but the ropes would be very hard to spot in the shadowed street full of milling crowds. [ ] Capture: Mockery of Death Or more fully: Shroud of Invisibility, Substance of Shadow, then Mockery of Death. It might be challenging to manage all three spells at once, but done right it will take Alberich by complete surprise and render him completely helpless, and you'll be able to pluck him right out of the sedan chair and let it continue on without him. [ ] Capture: Reinforcements Thanks to Wolf, you can actually do a surprisingly convincing howl, which is the signal that will call in three militarized orders of the Cult of Taal. Four, if the Horned Hunters are within earshot. Bring them in and you'll have the numbers to handle any complications. [ ] Capture: Other (write in) [ ] Follow The night is still young. At the end of his current path lies a point at which he will be sandwiched between a Light Wizard and two Grey Wizards, a thoroughly unenviable position for any worshipper of Chaos. You might prefer the range of options you would find there. - There will be a one hour moratorium.

Trouble in Talabheim, Part 7

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Kill: Branulhune Attack here and now, bisecting both sedan and Magus with a single swing. The crowds will complicate matters, but at least they are a known variable. Tally For all the glory of taking him alive, for all the potential conspirators he might be able to lead you to, your main purpose here and now is simple: to ensure that the last Haupt-Anderssen does not cast doubt upon the legitimacy of the Empress. He stands mere feet away, completely unaware of you, and a thought away is a sword superior to all but twelve within the Empire. You match the pace of the sedan chair and recall the techniques of the Fellowship of the Shroud, to move from apparent repose to sudden violence as efficiently as possible. You wait until a relative ebb in the surrounding crowd, a pool of relative illumination in the darkness, and for the pace of the footmen to grow familiar to you, and then you act. By the time the concealment of the Night Prowler falls away from you, Branulhune is already in your hand and descending. The first sign visible to Alberich that his night's plans may be about to go awry is the shattering of the wood of the sedan chair's flimsy roof mere feet above his head, and he has the barest fraction of a second to react before that blade will do the same to his chest. No human could meaningfully react in the time available to him. [Rolling for patronage: 6, the Holy Number of Slaanesh] [Alberich dodge roll: 72. He manages to save 72% of his body.] But his humanity is just one of the things that Alberich has sacrificed to his unholy patron. Instead of ribs and organs Branulhune slices through bone and bicep, unnatural mutation proving no obstacle to Dwarven artifice as Alberich propels himself through the wall of the disintegrating sedan chair, leaving his most visible mutation behind as he dives into the screaming crowd. [Pursuing Alberich: Intrigue, 22+27+5(Windsage)+5(trail)=59 vs 31+32+10(patron)-15(badly injured)=58.] It takes no concentration at all from you for an eerily convincing wolf's howl to rip its way from your throat, as in Tor Lithanel the other half of your soul jolts several other Wizards awake as he leads you through example. Your concentration is focused on your quarry, and you dive through the wreckage of the sedan chair and into the part in the crowd left by the fleeing Magus as he pushes his way through, and you're almost distracted from keeping up with his flight as you realize he's continuing on the sedan chair's original course. Either he's arrogant enough to think that he can lose you and continue with his original plan - which from what you know of him, is definitely possible - or there are accomplices waiting for him that he's trying to lead you to. [Pursuing Alberich, round two: Intrigue, 44+27+5(Windsage)+5(trail)+6(???)=85 vs 89+32+15(patron)-15(badly injured)=121.] Time seems to slow as you push your way through the crowd, your senses growing sharper as you take in every dot of blood, every yell of fear or anger, every spike of emotion in the crowd ahead, but no matter how fit you are, you are bound by human limitations and Alberich is not. The blood you're following grows drier and the crowd around you calmer with every passing moment, and you growl with frustration as you shroud yourself in Ulgu and disappear from the streets, appearing on a nearby rooftop. If you were a lone wolf you would have failed on this hunt, but here and now you are not, and other hunters are converging in response to your howl. All you need to do... [Regimand interception: 33] [Longshank interception: 94] [Alberich vs Longshanks: Martial, 33+26+20(patron)-15(badly injured)=64 vs 68+20+2(???)=90.] ...is be ready. You're already running as the much poorer attempt at a howl rises above the noise of the crowd, thankful that Talabheim architecture favours terraces over the smooth and often loose tiles of Altdorf rooftops. Where Sigmarite Templars would be a din of metal on metal and demands to bow down to their patron, the only sound of the Longshanks pack as they close on Alberich is the faint whistle of their arrows splitting the air and the soft, wet thunk as one finds purchase in him. Where a Wizard causes surprise and alarm, the sight of the Longshanks on the hunt is one much more familiar to the citizens of Talabheim, and while most of the crowd parts for them, some of them draw knives of their own and fix their eyes on he who has made an enemy of the protectors of Taal's holy sites. [Alberich vs Longshanks: Martial, 61+26+25(patron)-20(heavily injured)=92 vs 31+20+5(crowd assist)+4(???)=60.] [Mathilde interrupt: Martial, 86+23+12(???)=121.] Seemingly heedless of his injuries, Alberich draws a bone dagger from his tunic with his remaining hand and throws himself forward, moving with sinuous and unnatural grace around the arrows loosed at him and closing on the lead Longshank, who has only his own knife to raise in defence of himself. The next few seconds might have gone very badly for the Longshanks and any in the crowd with the bravery to assist them, but Alberich's focus on the foe in front of him is all the opportunity you need. With a moment of concentration and a few muttered syllables you appear behind him, and Branulhune passes in a neat and perfect arc through Alberich's neck, sending a spray of blood over the Longshank who was heartbeats away from having his own spilled, and a head rolling across the cobblestones. "Thank you for your assistance, gentlemen," you say to the Longshanks as you allow Branulhune to disappear once more. --- Where thrilling adventure ends, hard work begins. The three chief fragments of the former Elector Count are gathered to be kept under close observation until they can be burned at dawn with the remains of his sedan chair, and Priests of Taal carefully wash his tainted blood from the cobblestones of Taal's city with holy water. The footmen are rounded up and interrogated and prove to know very little, and through close examination of them you confirm the lingering presence of a minor confoundment that would have prevented them from recognizing the mutated nature of their passenger. They are found innocent of knowingly consorting with Chaos, though their future will feature a fair bit of cleansing penance performed within the Taalgrunhaar Forest. Alberich's knife is examined and found to be mundane, except for the relative rarity of finding a knife made entirely of fish bone this far inland. There are still unanswered questions, of course. Though a number of groups that happened to be in the direction Alberich was headed are rounded up, they all prove to have innocent explanations for their presence, so if he had accomplices they've managed to escape and will now be laying very low indeed. You don't know where he was hiding out, and though it could have been simply a rented and flea-infested room at a tavern somewhere in the Ratholds, it could also have been something more elaborate, and if so is now one more hidden mystery among many to be found in the city's slums. And to the Longshanks, Alberich's identity remains a mystery. There's also the question of Alberich's empowerment. Despite his severe injuries, Alberich only grew faster in the few minutes between the beginning of your encounter and its climax, and for a man to move with the sinuous grace of a lesser Daemon of the Tempter implies more attention than you'd expect the Dark Gods to pay to matters like this. You are also very aware that you had more company than that of Ranald on this night's work, and you don't mean your colleagues among the Longshanks. Perhaps you should not have given a wolf's howl with sword in hand while pursuing a Slaaneshi Magus through the streets of a holy city. That is an uncomfortable density of resonances, and you feel uncomfortably watched from multiple angles right now. Still, Chaos thwarted, Empress safe, Alric upstaged. All in all, a good night's work. But when dawn does creep over the city of Talabheim, there's going to be a great deal of rumour about the dramatic events that unfolded on the city streets, and some sort of official story is going to be distributed by the city's bellmen to reassure the alarmed and intrigued populace. They won't get the full story, of course, but those with influence will get something closer to the truth. The question is what, exactly, that version is going to be. It is not at all unknown for the involvement of Grey Wizards to be left out of even the unofficial version of events, and that the worst a Longshank experienced through all this was being rather badly in need of a bath means you have more than enough goodwill with them to shape the story that will be distributed, and decide who will get the credit and attention for the culmination of this matter, for good and ill. Who will get the credit for the death of this unknown but powerful Magus? [ ] Yourself And why not? Nobody could possibly fault you for simply doing your duty to the Empire. Accept the accolades and the attention you have earned. [ ] The Order of Light Magister Matriarch- oops, you mean Lady Magister Mira of the Order of Light directed your attention here. Her getting the credit will shore up her position in the Light Order even more, and neatly extricate yourself from the matter. [ ] The Longshanks Allow the Longshanks to take sole credit for the killing of a dangerous Magus and the thwarting of a Chaos plot. This would provide a very solid foundation to working with them again in the future. [ ] The Templars of Sigmar The information they provided demonstrated the value of a good relationship with the Holy Order of the Templars of Sigmar, and them getting the credit means that any attempts by others to investigate the matter further will run into an unyielding wall. - There will be a two hour moratorium.

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] The Longshanks Allow the Longshanks to take sole credit for the killing of a dangerous Magus and the thwarting of a Chaos plot. This would provide a very solid foundation to working with them again in the future. Tally "Well, if you have to play politics, that's the way to play it," Regimand says to you the next morning, as he peruses a freshly-printed news-sheet. "All mention is of a Longshank victory over a mutant cultist after a prolonged search, with thanks to their coreligionists and the Taalbaston Guard. Alric would have to rub his own nose in his failure quite a bit to be able to get a whiff of your interference." "He might be able to make some hay out of having protected the Unfähigers until the Witch Hunters caught up with the murderer, but that is a long way from the triumph he needs. And beyond all that, having removed the man in question from the Empire is a job well done itself. I'm happy with how it all turned out." "So what's next for you? Back to the Elf city?" "No, there's a similar matter I've agreed to look into over in Bechafen for Paranoth. Something's stirring in the woods there, but whatever it is is straddling the river, so nobody with our skillset has been able to properly investigate." "Ah. Going to call on the friends you made during your adventures up north?" "Perhaps. Or perhaps the ones I made today, if I come at it from this side of the border. Haven't decided yet. I'll see if I can get a better idea of what's going on when I get there." "Travelling by Shadowsteed?" You nod. "I'll keep you company at least part of the way back, then." "Need a hand with your unfinished business in the east?" He shakes his head. "Honestly, even one Wizard is overkill. Only reason I haven't handed it off is because it'd take more time to properly brief someone else than it'd save me." He smiles. "I appreciate the offer, though. And it was nice to spend time with you. You've grown far beyond my expectations, and you've developed skills equal to your ambitions. None could ask more of their Apprentice." --- Bechafen is a compact and crowded city, with the dark wood it is constructed out of combining with the tall buildings choking out the sunlight to give it a gloomy aura it doesn't fully deserve. Beneath that haunted first impression is a prosperous city serving as a centre of trade and industry, with its location on the Upper Talabec and at the centre of Ostermark's road network allowing it to dominate trade with the eastern Empire and southern Kislev, and its maze of sawmills and boatyards by the waterfront constantly takes in freshly-felled timber and turns out some of the finest river vessels on the continent. It cannot compete with the great cities of the Empire like Altdorf and Nuln in the way that Mordheim once did, and perhaps it never will, but in comparison to the other lesser capitals of the Empire like Wurtbad and Salzenmund it is not without its charms. Johann is waiting to meet you in a tavern by the waterfront, and the ring of empty tables around his is a reminder of how he must appear to those who haven't grown accustomed to him. The golden robes of his Order would set him apart on their own, but the large golden staff, the inhuman golden claw, and the blank golden orbs of his blinded eyes set him even further apart. "Johann," you say in greeting as you sit. "Good trip?" "I've gotten too used to Dwarven vessels, coming up the Talabec with nothing but wood between me and the water was disturbing. But apart from that, tolerable enough." "Didn't leave you waiting too long, did I?" He shrugs. "Gave me time to get the lay of the land. There's definitely something up, but nobody can agree what it is. Hauntings, animal attacks, banditry, cult activity, and portents and omens galore. Plenty of smoke, but nobody can agree what the fire is." "That fits what Paranoth said. Apparently half the picture is on the other side of the border, so it might be that nobody at all has the whole picture right now. But at least there's no reason not to operate openly here." Johann nods. "So what's the plan?" You've been considering that since you left Talabheim. Between your rank, your reputation, and your contacts, there's quite a number of groups you could approach regarding this mystery that could make solving it a great deal easier. But any group you approach would expect you to work with them in solving whatever the problem ends up being, and might have cause to be put out if you solve it in a way not to their satisfaction. [ ] Elector Count Wolfram Hertwig Chancellor Wolfram Hertwig has a reputation for being sensible, and if anyone would know what's going on in Ostermark, it would be him. But approaching him openly would make your presence here very official, which might get in the way. [ ] League of Ostermark The trade league of Ostermark's nobility are likely to see you as a shareholder of the EIC first and a Grey Wizard second, but they more than anyone have a vested interest in peace and prosperity reigning over the Upper Talabec. [ ] Longshanks Gratitude expires quickly, so you might as well make use their good graces while you have them. In Ostermark they're primarily guardians of shrines and pilgrims rather than Witch Hunters, but they'd still have a good idea of what's going on deep in the forests. [ ] Morrite Witch Hunters While the citizens of every province of the Empire respect Morr, Ostermarkers revere him more than most, which means that Morrite organizations like the Order of the Shroud, the Dreamwalkers, and the Andanti fill the role of Witch Hunters in Ostermark where normally the Templars of Sigmar would hold sway. Get in touch with them and see what they might know. [ ] The Ostermark Hedgewise The Hedgewise of Ostermark are a matriarchal mystery cult with ties to the Hag Witches of Kislev, and many of them are part of Kurtis Krammovitch's extended family. They have eyes and ears in the odd nooks and crannies of Ostermark, and are likely to know more of what's going on here than anyone with official authority. But they are unsanctioned magic-users, and dealing with them might be problematic. [ ] Tsarevich Boris Bokha You've met him before, and he seems to have made it his business to solve problems that his more straightforward father can't or won't. Seek him out once more and see if he's interested in solving a source of unrest and disruption in the Southern Oblast. [ ] Ice Witches You worked well with them previously, and though their influence within Kislev is currently at a low ebb, they'd have jurisdiction to investigate goings-on on the Kislevite side of the river. [ ] From scratch It would not be easy to investigate the matter from scratch, but at least you'd be beholden to nobody. Better to investigate for yourself than to bind yourself to any other group before you have a good idea of what's going on here. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a one hour moratorium.

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Longshanks Gratitude expires quickly, so you might as well make use their good graces while you have them. In Ostermark they're primarily guardians of shrines and pilgrims rather than Witch Hunters, but they'd still have a good idea of what's going on deep in the forests. Tally Going to the Longshanks means going to the Taalites, and that means going to the heart of Taal worship in Ostermark: a stone circle just outside the town of Gross Selon, about fifty miles west of Bechafen. Though a path from the road is kept clear and the area inside the circle is hard-packed dirt, the vegetation has otherwise been allowed to grow wild, and most of the stone circle is coated in vines and shrouded in branches. But not all: the three primary obelisks, each twice as large as the rest of the circle, are clear of vegetation. Ancient runes in a language you don't recognize are proudly visible, glowing in a light invisible to mundane sight. "Lady Magister, Magister," greets a deeply tanned man in robes that mark him as one of the most powerful men within the Cult of Taal, who appears to have been waiting for you. "I am Dobromir, Taal's High Priest of the East. You have questions for the Cult of Taal?" "I have one question, your Grace. What's going on in Ostermark for it to be so riled up?" He nods, apparently having expected your question. "Many have asked this of the Cult of Taal recently, and I can only tell you what I have told all the others: whatever power is active here has the ability and the desire to keep their actions unseen." "These actions take place in Taal's domain." "And that they are still hidden is why so many are concerned." He nods to you. "You asked to see the Longshanks, and I can see why you would think they would help. But the hierarchy of the Longshanks makes that difficult - there has not been a Guardian of the Greifwald for generations, and ever since these woods have fallen under the authority of the Guardian of the Schattenwald, whose attentions are focused on Ostland. The Longshanks here are all but independent, and act according to their immediate concerns only." A fact that the Hochlander's reports highlighted for you, and it also included that High Priest Dobromir has been one of the loudest voices pushing for the Guardian of the Greifwald to be restored. These events are, perhaps, a good demonstration of why that should be the case, but that also means that he has a vested interest in ensuring that you find the local Longshanks to be of no help. "I appreciate that, your Grace, but nevertheless I would ask you use your authority to summon those who may have encountered the spoor of whoever or whatever is at work here, so that we of the Colleges may seek it out, as is our prime concern and purpose." He considers you for a long moment. Your citing of the Articles would be very easy to argue as improper for this specific scenario, as the Longshanks are neither a civil authority nor Sigmar's Templars, but it's a point the Taalites are loathe to make. The Templars of Sigmar have desecularized quite a bit since the time of Magnus and as such the other Cults have been pushing quite strenuously and for quite some time for their own Templars to be recognized as their equal. "The Cult of Taal always stands ready to support the Empire," he eventually says. "I will summon the Longshanks to you, that you may see for yourself what strangeness lurks in the corners of the Greifwald." You give him a grateful bow, and he nods to you and sweeps out of the stone circle to confer with his assistants. Johann sighs. "Politics. I thought the Taalites would be above all that." "Only the dead are free from politics," you say, "and even that needs a careful asterisk or two, with Sylvania just south of here." Johann nods, his head turning automatically to look southwards, towards one of the larger obelisks. [Mathilde's Magesight: Learning, 5+29+10(Windsage)=44.] [Johann's Magesight: Learning, 72+18+15(Magnetoreception)=105.] Then he frowns, and you step aside as he starts to very carefully orient himself until he stands at what you'd judge to be the centre of the stone circle. You follow Johann's gaze as he looks from one obelisk to another, and frown as you notice for yourself what must have grabbed his attention. "You can identify north, right?" He nods, and points in the direction exactly opposite to the southern obelisk, and exactly a right angle from the western obelisk. "What's west and south of here?" The first only takes a moment. "Talabheim is west," you say, "I'd have to check a map but I'm almost sure it would be. In fact, I'd bet that exactly west of you would be the Horn of Taal." You take a moment to focus your senses, and sure enough you can make out, deep below you, a dozen relative trickles of energy combining beneath Johann and being sent as one onwards to the west. "This is a Waystone nexus," you say. "Like the Horn of Taal and the Jade College. For some reason a lot of the Waystone network aligns with the cardinal and ordinal directions." "It makes sense that this would be one," Johann said. "If it was up to me to find them, going to the Taalites and saying 'take me to your biggest, fanciest rocks' would be my first resort." "But this is the end of the chain, there's only streams from individual Waystones coming here." That's why you didn't spot it until Johann brought your attention to it, you reason. "Then why's there three of the big glowy rocks? What's south?" You consult a mental map. "Some village, starts with K. South of that, Rhebulas, which is barely a town. And... oh. Mordheim. We're exactly north of Mordheim." The two of you stare at the southern obelisk, and you quickly conclude that it's probably for the best that there's no longer a torrent of incoming energy from that accursed ruin. "Okay, I don't like that. What about..." Johann frowns at the north-eastern one, "about half a point east of northeast from here?" "Not exactly northeast? Or east-northeast?" "Definitely not. About fifty degrees east of north." "Not Bechafen, then." You close your eyes as you try to dredge up maps you haven't closely studied recently. But Kislev being Kislev, there's not a huge amount of landmarks that it could be. "Kislev City." Johann frowns at you. "I thought they were on board with the waystones?" "So did I. The Tsarevich told me himself the Kislev City nexus, below the Bokha Palace, was active." "So why's there nothing coming in from Kislev?" "Good question." --- As intriguing as the stone circle may be, you're here for a reason and poking at waystones isn't it. It takes some coordination with the Cult of Taal, but over the next few days you travel with various Longshanks to points of interest in northern Ostermark. Near the border with Talabecland, you peruse an ancient structure too overgrown to identify that the Longshanks have chased cultists of the not-quite-forbidden but quite disreputable Goddess Dark Helgis out of several times in recent weeks. You walk through the subdued town of Biersalhof, where the worship of Biersal is under close scrutiny to determine whether it has yet again drifted from its accepted confines as an aspect of Taal. You consider Goblin bodies being fished out of the Talabec upstream of Bechafen, too battered and waterlogged to determine whether they are Forest or Night or regular Goblins and whether they originated in northeast Ostermark, southernmost Kislev, or in the World's Edge Mountains around Karak Ungor. You have an unnerving conversation with an uncharacteristically canny Ogre leading a group of his fellows in the employ of Ostermark, who appears surprisingly cooperative despite his sobriquet of 'Maneater' and tells you at length in heavily accented Reikspiel about the unusually large pack of giant wolves his Ogres had chased down, defeated, and consumed. And many more concerning oddities who would be too minor to even care about if it weren't for the overall pattern they form: that something is seriously out of balance in the untamed corners of northern Ostermark. By the end of it, you've travelled over every major road and through every town in northern Ostermark and acquainted yourself with everything that's currently going bump in the night loud enough to alarm a Taalite or Rhyan pilgrim. And individually, none of it justifies a fraction of the alarm and mobilization you're seeing all around you. You're tempted to write it off as mass hysteria just to be done with it, but these are Ostermarkers. They're a people used to life with Kislev and the Forest of Shadows on one side, Sylvania and Mordheim on another, and the World's Edge Mountains on a third. If they're worried, then there's probably a very good reason to be worried, and though you've yet to be able to connect the dots yourself, you're accumulating enough of them that you're pretty sure there are connections to be made. [Mathilde's insight: Learning, 2+29=31.] [Johann's insight: Learning, 57+18+10(Guest of Tor Lithanel)=85.] "These are supposed to be the creepy kind of woods, right?" Johann says to you one afternoon in a Bechafen tavern, as you nurse an overpriced mug of Karak Kadrin ale and glare moodily at your notes. "Supposed to be. I've been told they're considered part of the Forest of Shadows, which is about as creepy as it gets this side of Athel Loren." "So where's all the creepiness?" You wave a hand vaguely. "Out there somewhere. That's what we're chasing." "I get that, but even in the really tame parts of Laurelorn you're always being glared at either from a tree or by a tree. I have been looking for it and there's just nothing out there. No spites, no spirits, no wooden spirit-golems, no overgrown and overly clever animals." You consider that. "Talk about missing the forest for the trees," you sigh. "I've been so busy looking for the creepiness in the forest I never noticed there's no creepiness from the forest. Which would imply that either whatever it is that's active has scared the forest into passivity..." "Or it is the forest." "And by hiding what they're doing, they're also giving themselves away by hiding all the background creepiness of the forest." "That's why everything's so stirred up without any cause. It's like an invisible steam tank just rolled through town. Nobody saw the tank itself, but everyone's deafened by the clanking and coughing from the smoke." You nod. Forest Spirits, then. And not the arch and underdressed kind you get in Laurelorn, the kind that live in the darkest and deepest corners of the most sinister forests and water the roots of trees with the blood of men and beasts and plot vengeance upon anything that dares disturb what they see as the balance of nature. But... all this is supposition. Good supposition, but not the kind of thing you can drop in Paranoth's lap and call a job well done. You need to at least be able to attest that you've seen proof of that supposition, and you need to know what they're up to. Preferably before they actually achieve it. There's still quite a number of local sources of information you've yet to call on, but there's also an entire forest realm you've recently been getting to know who may be able to assist. Local Sources: [ ] Elector Count Wolfram Hertwig Chancellor Wolfram Hertwig has a reputation for being sensible, and if anyone would know what's going on in Ostermark, it would be him. But approaching him openly would make your presence here very official, which might get in the way. [ ] League of Ostermark The trade league of Ostermark's nobility are likely to see you as a shareholder of the EIC first and a Grey Wizard second, but they more than anyone have a vested interest in peace and prosperity reigning over the Upper Talabec. [ ] Morrite Witch Hunters While the citizens of every province of the Empire respect Morr, Ostermarkers revere him more than most, which means that Morrite organizations like the Order of the Shroud, the Dreamwalkers, and the Andanti fill the role of Witch Hunters in Ostermark where normally the Templars of Sigmar would hold sway. Get in touch with them and see what they might know. [ ] The Ostermark Hedgewise The Hedgewise of Ostermark are a matriarchal mystery cult with ties to the Hag Witches of Kislev, and many of them are part of Kurtis Krammovitch's extended family. They have eyes and ears in the odd nooks and crannies of Ostermark, and are likely to know more of what's going on here than anyone with official authority. But they are unsanctioned magic-users, and dealing with them might be problematic. [ ] Tsarevich Boris Bokha You've met him before, and he seems to have made it his business to solve problems that his more straightforward father can't or won't. Seek him out once more and see if he's interested in solving a source of unrest and disruption in the Southern Oblast. [ ] Ice Witches You worked well with them previously, and though their influence within Kislev is currently at a low ebb, they'd have jurisdiction to investigate goings-on on the Kislevite side of the river. [ ] From scratch It would not be easy to investigate the matter from scratch, but at least you'd be beholden to nobody. Better to investigate for yourself than to bind yourself to any other group before you have a good idea of what's going on here. [ ] Other local source (write in) Outside Assistance: [ ] Queen Marrisith's suggestion Go right to the top. More Elector Counts thinking kindly of Laurelorn would be very much in her favour, and though she wouldn't come herself, she'd be able to name someone who would be able to help and has the authority to tell them to go. [ ] Vicereine Cadaeth You're not entirely sure of her nature, but you're pretty sure that whaver she is, she has more insight into Forest Spirits than you do. [ ] Lady Kaia 'Stormwitch' Fanmaris The Warden of Storms advocates peaceful relations with foreign powers, and has spent much of an Elven lifetime fighting the products of corrupted forests. [ ] The Grey Lords You do not know of any beings with a superior track record at wrangling forest spirits than the Grey Lords. Ask for the most suitable of their number to assist. [ ] Other (write in) Laurelorn is full of people and beings that it would be useful to know more about, and this would be a great pretence for that. Name a House, Cult, or inhabitant of Laurelorn, and the Queen will send them to assist. - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Only one option can win overall, not one from each category. They're separated for legibility only. - It's up to you whether it's better to prioritize solving the mystery in front of you, or using this as an opportunity to get to know possible Waystone Project contributors.

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [X] The Ostermark Hedgewise The Hedgewise of Ostermark are a matriarchal mystery cult with ties to the Hag Witches of Kislev, and many of them are part of Kurtis Krammovitch's extended family. They have eyes and ears in the odd nooks and crannies of Ostermark, and are likely to know more of what's going on here than anyone with official authority. But they are unsanctioned magic-users, and dealing with them might be problematic. Tally About eighty miles upriver of Bechafen is the largely unremarkable village of Gerdouen. No road leads to it, and the only ferry that plies that section of the river is the Kislevite one between Ryazan and Rakhov. If you don't have a boat of your own, the only way to reach it is to either bribe or browbeat the supply galley to Fortenhaf to give you passage, or to make your way on foot through fifty miles of untamed forest. This would normally make for an extremely insular and suspicious population, but Gerdouen is a woodcutting town, and that means that they don't have the luxury of isolationism. Their living relies on lashing together hundreds of felled logs into massive and ungainly rafts to be carried downstream to be caught and pulled in by a boom at Bechafen, and then carrying the profits and the products of civilization that Gerdouen requires all the way home. This makes for a village of contradictions: an economy that is both intertwined with civilization but also as independent as they can make it, a population that is necessarily both gregarious and suspicious as they must be as able to find a buyer in Bechafen as they are to ward off a suspicious stranger on the way home, a population that is staunchly Ostermarker but for whom the vast majority of the outsiders they see are from the Kislevite ferry illegally anchoring there overnight. It is a nexus of borders and boundaries being crossed: land and water, wild and civilized, urban and rural, independent and interlinked, Ostermark and Kislev. And that makes it as steeped in the power of the Hedge as any of the Colleges are in their own form of power. You'd debated leaving Johann in Bechafen, but he's long since proven his trustworthiness and discretion, and besides that you're not entirely confident the villagers wouldn't react to the sudden appearance of a lone Grey Wizard in their midst with the swing of an axe. So the two of you make your way east along the southern bank of the river from Bechafen, you on Shadowsteed and Johann on foot, limbs of gold and shadow finding easy purchase where mere flesh would struggle. Despite that it's still relatively slow going, and though you left Bechafen at first light, the sun is high in the sky by the time you approach your destination. You finally emerge from the besieged border of the forest into a field of half-excavated stumps, and the rhythmic chopping you've been following stops immediately as the heads of those working nearby turn to you. Those who aren't carrying an axe wear a hatchet on their person, and most of those hatchets now have a hand edging closer to it. "I bring and seek no trouble here," you say, waving a greeting in a hand symbol of the Hedgewise that Kurtis Krammovitch taught you, which is eerily similar to a sign with the same meaning used in Ranaldian cant. "I simply wish to speak to a village elder." Eyes go to the guns on your waist and to Johann's golden claw, and you can see them weighing the odds. "That would be your right, Magisters," the eldest of them, a large, scarred woman with a wooden leg, eventually says. You resist the urge to correct her. A noble addressing you as merely Magister would be a deliberate insult, but on the fringes of the Empire 'Magister' is used interchangeably with 'Wizard'. You edge cautiously around the unmoving and heavily armed group of lumberjacks to follow the woman, the silence stretching as you and Johann are led through the field of stumps, between rows of crops, and towards the village proper. "Have you had any trouble with Beastmen recently?" you ask to break the silence. "We've not seen hide or hair of the tainted beasts for seasons." Strange. They'd normally be the first to be taking advantage of unrest in the forests. "No other disturbances?" "Not until today," she says shortly. Fair enough. You are taken to Baba Brzeginias, who is a wiry old woman with white hair and milky eyes that still appear disconcertingly sharp behind the haze, and she too has a hatchet on her hip. Her cottage is built right on the treeline and the inside is crowded with hanging herbs and cloves that threaten to knock your hat off. You don't hesitate to drop Kurtis' name, not entirely sure the woman is still able to make out the hand signs of the Hedgewise you are performing. "Tch," she says to the name. "Good family. Tragic, what happened to them. What was done to them." Her eyes flick to your hat, but after a tense moment she shrugs. "He is a good boy. If he says you are a friend, then you are at least not an enemy. What brings you here, to the edge of the east?" "Though it appears to have passed you by, there's a great deal of unrest in northern Ostermark of late, and nobody seems to know why. I want to fix that." "Why do the Greys care now? You have always left the Forest to us." "I'm here at the request of Magister Patriarch Paranoth, of the Jade Order." She snorts. "Them. They should stick to gardens and orchards. Their ilk might have uses back west, but here they have only ever got in the way." She considers you thoughtfully. "If you go back with no answers, he will send another." Though she didn't phrase it as a question, you nod. "I believe he would." "I do not know, because I have not needed to know. If it comes to Gerdouen, I cannot stop it. If it doesn't, I need not concern myself. But if it means keeping the tree-lovers from sending more questioners, we can stick our hands in the knothole and see what bites us." She rises onto steady feet and strides over to a window to peer up at the sky. "Tch. You've missed noon. Come back at dusk, and we shall see what we shall see." --- It seems that the entire village has been lurking just outside, half of them watching Johann and half of them the cottage, but most of them start to disperse after Baba Brzeginias tuts and flaps a hand at them. You summarize the exchange for Johann who frowns at you. "So, what, we just wait here for something like five hours?" You shrug. "There's always something that needs doing in a village. We might as well pitch in while we wait." After some awkward conversation with the nearest villagers, you and Johann break through their air of extreme caution with boasting and before long you've returned to the edge of the forest that the village is currently felling. It's been a while since Branulhune was put through its paces, and while a human smith would be greatly offended at a sword of theirs being used to fell a tree, Dwarves believe there should be no difference between a proper tool and a proper weapon. It is said that a Runefang can cut through a tree trunk so cleanly that the tree remains standing afterwards and still needs to be pushed over. Perhaps this illustrates the difference between even the greatest Runelord of the modern era and the legends of the distant past, because Branulhune hits with a deafening crack of thunder and a numbing judder sent up your arm, and it sends a swarm of wooden splinters flying in all directions, pinging off your Aethyric Armour and Johann's golden skin. But though it lacks the elegance of the Runefangs, the tree is nevertheless felled, and Johann lives up to his own boasting by sinking golden claws into the wood and dragging it across the ground without need of a sled. The villagers begin to look at you with calculating eyes, and you wonder if you might have erred. --- By the time dusk approaches, you're tired and bruised and will probably be picking splinters out of your plaits for days, but there are enough logs stacked at the riverbank that Bechafen is going to see an extra visit from the youth of Gerdouen this year and the locals no longer seem on the verge of drawing steel. You leave Johann with the villagers, many of whom have grown rather friendlier since he removed his shirt - a habit he seems to have picked up in Tor Lithanel - and once more enter the cottage of Baba Brzeginias. She looks up from the fire she is prodding with a poker, and holds out a bone for you that you really hope came from livestock. "Here. Don't drop it. If anything happens that shouldn't, break it over your knee." You gingerly take the bone, and you're as ready to flinch back with your mystic senses if you find anything untoward as your fingers are if they detect any scrap of remaining flesh. But though the bone thrums with energy, it's an energy you're unable to directly perceive. It seems like a faint star that seems clearly visible from the corner of your eye but disappears if you look directly at it. But despite its elusiveness there's a familiarity to its energies, one that would feel oddly comfortable to you if you weren't immediately suspicious of that feeling of comfort. "Ready?" she asks, and you turn your attention to her. "Will this be a ritual? What will it entail?" "Tch. Colleges." She reaches into a bowl on the mantle and pulls out a fistful of ash, which she throws at the northern wall. The timbers shudder and begin to part, but instead of the village that should be beyond you find yourself looking with mundane senses at something you have only ever seen with Magesight. The life of the river and the forest beyond unfolds before you in overlaid energies, the soft, faint slow-souls of the trees and the darting energies of animals twinkling like dying embers. But beyond all of the mundane energies of forest life and the occasional flaring oddity that seems to sense your attention and dart out of the way, is a blazing sun of shadowed energies. [Mathilde's Perception: Learning, 64+29=93.] [???'s Magesight: 16+??=??.] Far to the north, fury and Ulgu intertwine in a storm of bewitchment enfolding a mass of life, the sharpness of hungry beasts and the ireful fire of thinking beings on the warpath, and hovering overhead like vultures are slivers of attention from the Four who only ever bring ill - though you cannot tell if they had a hand in these events or are merely watching it for entertainment or opportunity. At the heart of it all the center of the storm finally turns, and you find yourself flinching back from a sense of bottomless wrongs, and you find the alien cadence of recited evils springing to your lips. Bone splinters beneath your fingers and suddenly you are back in the hut, left with nothing but the echoes of festered wrath and the smell of lilac. "Pfah," Baba Brzeginias says, and plucks a sprig from one of the dangling lines and throws it in the fire, and a heavy, earthy smell drowns out the lilac. She sits before the fire and looks thoughtfully at the wall that had just seemingly unfolded. "Have you ever seen the ocean?" "A time or two." "Deep waters, I hear, deeper than the mind can fathom, filled with enormous and terrible beasts. Our river here is so very small in comparison, and the creatures but minnows. If one of those ocean beasts found their way into these waters, they would find themselves constricted, suffocated and starved from waters too shallow to cover them and prey too tiny to nourish, and a time would arrive when they would surely die if they did not retreat back to where they came from. But oh, the terror they could wreak before that time arrived." You consider that. The Forest of Shadows would not be considered a metaphorical meander by any stretch of the imagination, so there are only two candidates for what could be considered a comparative ocean. And while Laurelorn is starting to look outside its borders, you're fairly confident they haven't quite reached the point where they're interfering with events four provinces away from them. That just leaves one other possibility, a possibility that has never been shy about unleashing terrors upon the rest of the continent: Athel Loren. An Asrai warhost or a murder of Dryads, and it would be difficult to say which would be the greater evil. "Things will be bad for my cousins across the border," she continues, "but they have withstood worse. And it means you can go back to your leaders and tell them that Ostermark need only ride out the ripples from the creature splashing about." --- Only the mad travel the Forest of Shadows at night if they do not need to, and you spend the night in murmured conversation with those whose turn it is to watch over the sleeping village, learning a little more of the community that has so thoroughly embraced the Hedgewise. Every axe of the village has runes carved in the haft by thorns cut when Mannsleib was in wane. Every man of the village wears a pouch of bat-leather filled with herbs to ward off misfortune and maladies, and every woman the wings of a dragonfly to ward off the attention of the dead and damned. And when the young and strong are away delivering the bounty of Gerdouen to the city, they do so believing that their mothers and aunts are watching over them from the other side of the Hedge - which must be as welcome for the journey to and back as it would be frustrating when presented with the many intriguing and expensive varieties of sin available in the city. And despite their relative isolation, the rare dalliances that the young women of the village are able to enjoy with Ostermark cityfolk and Kislevite sailors very reliably provide fresh branches to what could otherwise be very narrow and gnarled family trees. Speaking of which, you do not comment when Johann reappears the next morning, though it is impossible to completely resist the urge to indulge in some private speculation as to how and in what company he spent the night. As the two of you return to civilization, you use Johann as a sounding board for the matter at hand. You have more answers than you started with: a force from Athel Loren and shrouded in Ulgu is active in Kislev's Southern Oblast, and the direct effects on the Empire are likely to be no more than knock-on disruptions. Perhaps that is a sufficient answer for Paranoth. But there are still unanswered questions, and it could be argued that the order needing restoring represents either opportunity or obligation. The matter is: [ ] Concluded The disruptive force originated in Athel Loren and is active in the Southern Oblast, making it not the Empire's problem. This is enough information for Paranoth. Send him what you know and return to Tor Lithanel. [ ] Incomplete You cannot call your investigation complete when you do not know the composition or the objective of the force active in Kislev. Investigate further. [ ] Opportune There are individuals and organizations within Kislev you would benefit from a closer relationship with, and this presents an opportunity to forge those relationships. Offer your services to Kislev in restoring order to the region. [ ] Obliging The Empire is being disrupted by these events. The knowledge you have gathered here obliges you to do what you can to restore order to the region. Offer your services to Ostermark in holding back the worst of the disruptions and opportunists. - There will be a one hour moratorium. - You have some wiggle room left to resolve matters here before it begins to eat into the number of actions available next turn, but that amount of time is finite and getting entangled here might make you unable to neatly remove yourself from the situation if it threatens to drag on.

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 4

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Opportune There are individuals and organizations within Kislev you would benefit from a closer relationship with, and this presents an opportunity to forge those relationships. Offer your services to Kislev in restoring order to the region. Tally There was a knock on the door, and a familiar voice reached Captain Loza. "Kovnik?" "Yes, Bedrich?" Captain Loza replied, not looking up from his paperwork. Bedrich was the kind of underling he prized above all others: large, strong, and dim, but the kind of dim who knew they were dim, and so could be counted on to follow the instructions they are given exactly and to come and get him when they were confused by something. In his experience, a steady stream of small concerns from a self-aware idiot was much better than an occasional complete disaster that could only come from a slightly clever person who thought they were a very clever person. "There is a professor from a school in Alt-dorf here, but their papers do not look like what the book says Alt-dorf school papers are supposed to look like." "Have you arrested them?" "They also say they are a noble, and their bodyguard has metal claws." Loza looked up at that, frowning. If the bodyguard was a mutant Bedrich would already have called in reinforcements, so he must mean... "Oh, Indic fist-knives. Some Imperinyi druzhina with an exotic bodyguard, who thinks they are too important to have proper papers?" Loza rose from his seat, grinning at the opportunity to ruin the day of some petty foreign noble. --- You'd expected it to take some time crossing the border into Kislev. Though you've been to Kislev multiple times before, this time you do so as a passenger of the Fortenhaf ferry arriving at the docks of Rakhov, rather than flying far above in a gyrocarriage or crossing as part of a Dwarven steam-wagon convoy. As such you are subject to the border bureaucracy of Kislev. The letters patent of the Colleges seemed to confuse the border guard you presented then to, and you did your best to explain it to him as best you can through his very shaky grasp of Reikspiel and your very modest smattering of Kislevarin. You'd expected him to finally reach his limit and escalate the matter to a superior; you'd not expected said superior to arrive with a look of eager anticipation, nor for said expression to shift to shock and alarm as soon as he set eyes on the two of you, before settling into a mask of professionalism. You explain the matter all over again, and the Kovnik studied your papers closely before disappearing. "Are you sure this is a good idea?" Johann asks again. "I could head back to Tor Lithanel if this is about me." "It isn't. I know everyone says Kislev has a problem with male Wizards, but it's a bit more complicated than that. The Ice Witches have a major problem with anyone male trying to use Ice Magic, so they only recruit women, and any men of Kislev who can't or won't stop trying to use magic are killed or banished or Pacified. But one look at you would be enough to tell any magic user that you're as spoken for as any Wizard could possibly be. And besides, the Ice Witches are out of favour at the moment, so they wouldn't be dictating border policies." "So what's the problem, then?" "It's possible they've literally never had a Wizard try to cross the border here. Most Empire visitors to Kislev would go through Erengrad or just get a ferry right up the Urskoy. Even from Bechafen it would be quicker and easier to get a ferry to Zavstra. The only reason we're here instead of one of those is we started from Gerdouen." He still looks troubled, but doesn't object further. "So what's our plan?" "I'm still deciding that. This is an opportunity to make friends, but who with? The first possibility is the Tsarevich, who wanted to host the Waystone Project in the first place because he didn't think he'd see any benefits from it unless he did so. This could be a way to demonstrate that I'd be a good friend for him to have even if I wasn't living in his back pocket. "Second is the Ice Witches. They're on the outs with the Tzar, but the Boyars still hold them in high esteem, which means that they'd be the ones the local Boyar would be relying on to make sense of the troubles in the Shirokij Forest. I've worked with them before, and I've been thinking of trying to bring them into the Waystone Project. "Third is the local leaders of the settlements actually within the Shirokij. Even more than most Kislevite stanitsas, the forest stanitsas are very reliant on Hag Witches to placate the local spirits, and they're right in the middle of all of this. Hag Witches are said to know a great deal about pacifying the spirits of the land and cleansing the taint of Chaos. If that involves Waystones, great, and if it doesn't, then they're somehow able to do the same thing that Waystones do." "Wouldn't it make the most sense to go right to the top? Better the Emperor as your friend than some local baron, right?" "In theory yes, but in Kislev City, the Shirokij trouble would just be one more regional concern among dozens, so it'd only make sense to go there if my objective is to get close to the Tsarevich himself. The Boyar of Rakhov would be a lot more concerned with the Shirokij he lives on the outskirts of than Kislev City would be, so working with him would give me a lot more sway with the Ice Witches than the Tsarevich would. And the atamans within the Shirokij could very easily be facing an existential threat, so I'd be able to win a lot of gratitude from the local Hag Witches if I help them ride this out. So it comes down to who would be the most useful to me, rather than simply who's got the biggest title." You and Johann debate the issue for a while, and by the time the Kovnik returns you've settled on an answer. He is carrying a dusty and yellowed piece of parchment to compare against your papers, and spends quite some time in quiet scrutiny. "Your papers are in order," he eventually says, sounding half relieved, half disappointed. "Where are you traveling to from here, and what is your business there?" [ ] Tsarevich Boris Bokha You are travelling to Kislev City to offer your services to the Tsarevich himself. [ ] Ice Witches You are staying right here in Rakhov, to offer your services to the local Boyar and to work alongside the Ice Witches. [ ] Hag Witches You are travelling deeper into the Shirokij Forest, to offer your services to the local atamans and their resident Hag Witches. - There will be a one hour moratorium.

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 5

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Ice Witches You are staying right here in Rakhov, to offer your services to the local Boyar and to work alongside the Ice Witches. Tally "My destination is here in Rakhov, to see the Boyar about the trouble in the Shirokij," you reply. "Can you take me to him?" You see the worry in the Kovnik's eyes grow as he realizes that you are going to be a part of his life for more than the next few minutes. "The Boyar is currently meeting with the Hromada Ledyanoy Ved'ma," he says, and pauses there, clearly hoping this will dissuade you. "Good," you say, dashing his hopes. "I had hoped to work with my northern colleagues on this matter." He looks even more haunted. "Very well. Follow me." --- The Boyar's fortress mostly consists of a set of walls and towers with a mustering ground within, and the fact that most of the towers give a clear view of the river's most fordable point harkens back to an age when Kislev and the Empire weren't quite as allied as they are today. The modest structure tucked into one corner is something that only diplomacy would lead you to label a proper keep, as it would struggle to measure up to the structure you built at the heart of your own fief. You have to remind yourself not to underestimate Kislev - these defences might be called wildly inadequate by the poorest of Hochland Barons, but each member of the rota this village would be able to muster would be the match of a Knight of the Empire. [Rolling...] The Kovnik leads you inside the hall, and within the central hall is a bearded man wearing the tall fur hat of a boyar and the golden sun medallion of the Cult of Dazh, and it is hard to tell through his layers of clothing whether he is well-muscled, well-fed, or both. Deep in conversation with him is an equally large and slightly familiar middle-aged woman who pays no attention to your entry, though the hawk on her shoulder turns immediately to fix you with a suspicious glare. You dig through your memories of your previous trip to Kislev, glad that you went over your notes recently to refresh your memory. "Dzień dobry Boyar Kirill, Ved'ma Milica. Greetings on behalf of the Empire." The two of them turn to you and Johann and the Boyar looks you up and down, his brow furrowing. "Greetings to you... Lord Magister?" He looks to the Kovnik, who nods and says what you take to be confirmation that he's checked your papers. "What brings the Colleges of Magic to Rakhov?" You resist the urge to breathe a sigh of relief that at least one of them speaks Reikspiel. "The disruption in the Shirokij threatens to spill across the Talabec, and besides that, the whole Old World is safer when Kislev is strong. I have come to lend my aid alongside the Hromada in this matter." Milica groans and asks something that sounds rather strained, and the Boyar nods and replies in Kislevarin, and the Boyar looks even more concerned at her next words. "She says it is like if you hoped the Tzar would send an extra rota, and then three pulks and the Kreml Guard arrive. Do you know something that Kislev does not?" Ljiljana must have really talked you up to her fellows. "The force moving through the Shirokij is using magic to shield itself from direct observation, but I have been able to pierce it for long enough to identify their origin. It is a warhost from Athel Loren." The Boyar has no response to that, but from her grimace Milica recognizes 'Athel Loren'. She mutters something to him and recognition flares in his eyes. "The forest of Daemon-Elves and maddened spirits in the land of horses in bunting?" Perhaps one could find a few technical faults with that description, but that phrase does capture the essence of the children of Athel Loren. "The very same." "What purpose could they have in Kislev?" "They are unpredictable. When they have appeared in the Empire, it has always been to bring destruction. Sometimes to us, sometimes to some threat within our borders we were not yet aware of." The Boyar confers with Milica, who grunts and says a few short words. "Kovnik, send riders to Fort Jakova and to Gerslev and the oblast krugs, we muster at Resvynhaf. A boat to Zavstra, too. Milica," he says a few words in Kislevarin, and she nods and walks towards the doors, muttering to her hawk. "That will take word to the city. Did you and your man bring horses, Chief Witch?" Johann bristles beside you at the title, which is a lot less respectful to Imperial ears than to Kislevite ones, but looks to you and calms at your lack of reaction. "We can keep pace." "Then let us race Dazh, and see what sort of welcome we must bring to these far-travelled visitors." --- In the Empire it can be a process of weeks to raise even a local militia, which is why in modern times the provinces rely more on their standing army in all but the direst of circumstances. Outside of the major cities Kislev has no standing army and relies entirely on its mounted levies, which many take to be a sign of poverty and primitiveness. As horns blow, riders muster, and the Boyar comments to you that the rota of Rakhov could have made Vitevo before dawn were they not giving time for word to reach Fort Jakova, you begin to realize the truth of the matter: that the people of Kislev are already a standing army. The next morning the quiet of dawn is broken by the eerie howl given off by the 'wings' of the Winged Lancers of the Gospodar: a banner of feathers attached to the rear of their saddle that gives off an ululation that ripples through the air and the Winds alike, which rather piques your interest. Everyone that has spoken or written of Kislev at war mentions the howl of the Winged Lancers, and you can see why. At first you suspect enchantment, but as careful a study as one can make on the march later you realize that it is an enchantment only in the most technical of senses, in the same way that a lever is a machine. The product of centuries of tradition and bloodshed have created something that simply exists as much in the ethereal realm as it does in the physical, and when dragged through the ethereal at great speed and in great numbers creates a reverberation that is as unsettling to the soul as the howl of the wings is to the ears. You spend the rest of the day trying and failing to find a way to expand that single sentence into something that justifies an entire paper on the subject, and eventually conclude that you might be able to accomplish it if you're able to personally witness the effect the charge has on sufficiently varied foes. When the day's ride concludes at Vitevo, which proves to be a walled compound similar to many within Kislev with one key difference: the towers are on the outside. The salt mine within is where the convicted criminals of Kislev City are sent and from which many never emerge, and the small village clustered around its walls is apparently almost as dangerous as the barracks inside. Under normal circumstances, anyway. With a rota from Fort Jakova starting to arrive and several Ungol 'krugs' - nomadic Ungol communities from the oblasts - having already set up their camps and now loudly deriding the Gospodars for how long it took for them to get here, you doubt there'll be much trouble from the locals. The next morning the rota of Voltsara and another krug have arrived, and nobody insults them by asking them if they're ready to start riding immediately. In another day the force arrives at the small town of Resvynhaf, notable for being where the spring of the Shirokij River emerges from the ground as well as where felled trees from throughout the Shirokij Forest are taken to be processed in its sawmills and sent on to Kislev. It is also, after generations of feeding Kislev City's appetite for lumber and firewood, several miles from the treeline. "Boyar Kalashinivik - the Boyar of here in Resvynhaf and of the Shirokij villages - is said to be visiting Praag," Boyar Kirill says to you as he assembles a makeshift council of war. "And the Boyar of Fort Jakova has remained in Fort Jakova - unrest in the mountains, he says. So this remains my sole command." He grins at that. "Three pulks led by one Boyar. If nothing else, that will make the Tzar come." "The Tzar comes, but the city boyars drag their feet," a nervous-looking Kovnik Loza translates for Milica. "His son leads the Kreml Guard here with as much speed as they can manage." "Which is none," Kirill says with a snort. "Yha. Gerslev will be here before Tsarevich." "The ataman says that the Shirokij villages are besieged by some unknown force, it kills any that try to venture outside the walls, some have been killed in their beds. Only by sending multiple messengers at once was Ryazan able to get word through." "On horseback?" "Nie, on foot. Shirokij villages only have horses for pulling carts." The Boyar is almost able to keep the derision from his voice. You'd be suspicious of that if you only knew the reputation of Athel Loren, but after having seen the control their more civilized cousins have over the woods, there's no doubt in your mind. "That has to be deliberate. No man on foot could avoid an Athel Loren picket in a forest. And isn't Ryazan on the river?" "Yha, where the Shirokij River reaches the Talabec." "They get word through a hundred miles of forest on foot, but can't get word twenty miles downriver to Bechafen?" Kirill and Milica exchange looks, and Milica says a single word. "Trap," Loza translates. "They might terrorize a village on their way through to doing something else," you reason, "but for them to be so inefficiently murderous... they are trying to draw someone in. Someone that would not know that Athel Loren is in their woods, and would simply think it is one more terror of the Shirokij." "If Boyar Kalashinivik was here, honour would have demanded that he lead the rota in himself," Kirill says. "But he is gone, and the ataman had simply sent word to Praag to ask him what is to be done." "Is that normal?" you ask. He shrugs. "Some would call it deference, others cowardice. He sent word six days ago. Praag is..." he thinks, and confers with Loza in Kislevarin. "Five days, with remounts. Boyar Kalashinivik should arrive in four days." Milica speaks again. "It is a trap," Loza translates, "but it is a trap for a mouse, and a bear is about to step in it." Kirill nods. "When the Tzar gets here, every mustered man will be led into that forest to kill whatever he finds." "How long will that take?" you ask. "One day after the city boyars finally assemble their rotas. When that will be, I cannot say. Tomorrow? Next month? When the world freezes?" There's a series of Kislevarin comments from all three of them, and you catch enough of it to guess that what is being said is rather uncomplimentary about city-folk. "So whoever arrives first of the Tzar and the Boyar will lead a force into the forest?" Kirill nods. "Would it be the whole force?" "Even if it is Boyar Kalashinivik and I refuse to join my pulk to his, in the absence of their own Boyars, the other forces could choose to follow him instead of me. And they would. Enemies march on Kislev's soil." "They'd lead an all-cavalry force into a forest?" After Loza translates that, Milica begins to speak with even more firmness in her tone than usual. "This is not the Empire," Loza relays. "We do not have islands of civilization in an ocean of trees and beasts. We do not accept entire realms of enemies within what we call our borders. This is our land. All of it, our land. They must die for stepping upon it." "And the Tzar has never backed down from a fight in his life," Kirill says, pride and exasperation warring in his tone. "So yes. There will be a red day before this week is out." Boyar Kalashinivik will arrive in four days and Tzar Vladimir will arrive in two days at the soonest. The first to arrive will lead the gathered forces into the Shirokij. Each of the following preparations will take one day, and the two with the most votes will be chosen. You may or may not have the opportunity to perform further preparations after that point. [ ] Bring in the Kreml Guard Tsarevich Boris is leading the Kreml Guard, but they are travelling on foot on a dirt road and may not arrive in time for the battle. Kislev's forces actually having infantry would be helpful for a battle in a forest. Use Rite of Way to speed their journey. [ ] Bring in Ice Witches Currently, the only Ice Witch that is likely to be present for the battle is Milica. If you travel to Kislev City, you could bring in additional Ice Witches on Shadowsteeds. Milica says there are at least two and perhaps as many as five Ice Witches in Kislev City that would be able to respond and could meaningfully contribute to a battle. [ ] Bring in the Tzar Tzar Vladimir is on his way and bringing the very many rotas of Kislev City with him. It might be preferable for him to get here first, and would definitely be preferable for him to get here knowing who his enemy is going to be. Travel to Kislev City, tell him all you know, and tell him he needs to get moving or he'll miss the fight. [ ] Find the Boyar For some reason, the Athel Loren forces seem to be trying to lure in Boyar Kalashinivik and his rota. Boyar Kalashinivik should be somewhere on the road between Praag and Kislev. Intercept him and see if you can figure out what this is all about. [ ] Investigate the missing leyline The Waystone Nexus in Gross Selon seems to be set up to receive energy from Kislev City, but currently nothing is coming through. Investigate where the leyline should be between Resvynhaf and Kislev City to see if it is still flowing out of Kislev City, because if it is, then it is being intercepted somewhere in the Shirokij. [ ] Scout the Shirokij Of the forces here, only you would have any chance of moving unseen through the Shirokij. Use this to try to scout the enemy. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - If anyone is playing along at home, I'm mostly using the map of Kislev from Realm of the Ice Queen, but with a few extra settlements on the border from one of the fan-made maps. - Yes, it's Tzar with a Z and Tsarevich with an S. Blame GW.

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 6

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Bring in the Kreml Guard Tsarevich Boris is leading the Kreml Guard, but they are travelling on foot on a dirt road and may not arrive in time for the battle. Kislev's forces actually having infantry would be helpful for a battle in a forest. Use Rite of Way to speed their journey. [*] Investigate the missing leyline The Waystone Nexus in Gross Selon seems to be set up to receive energy from Kislev City, but currently nothing is coming through. Investigate where the leyline should be between Resvynhaf and Kislev City to see if it is still flowing out of Kislev City, because if it is, then it is being intercepted somewhere in the Shirokij. Tally The Kreml Guard and the leylines, you decide. If there's to be a battle inside a forest, you want to have at least some dedicated infantry on your side, and having a sensible and skilled general in the form of Tsarevich Boris around would also be an advantage. And while you're heading in that direction you can also investigate the matter of the missing leyline you noticed at Gross Selon, as if those energies are still flowing from Kislev but are being intercepted partway by the enemy within the Shirokij Forest, that's something you're going to want to know about in advance. Normally you would hesitate to leave a male Imperial magic-user with no knowledge of Kislevarin unattended in Kislev, but close proximity to an obviously unperturbed Ice Witch has demonstrated to the gathered pulks that Johann is benign and keeping up with cavalry on the march for days while on foot has made him intriguing, especially to the young men and women of the nomadic Ungol krugs. So while a chaperone might be called for, he's at least in no immediate danger from the Kislevite taboo on male magic-users - or at least in less danger than he would be if he got caught sniffing around the leylines with you. With the stated intention of speeding the Kreml Guard along their journey you carefully scrutinize every map the gathered pulks can produce and depart from the muster at Resvynhaf and once you're out of sight you veer northwards, towards the headwaters of a tributary to the Urskoy that the leyline should pass underneath. If you follow the river from its source to its mouth, you should be guaranteed to cross the direct line between Kislev City and Gross Selon. --- Two hours later you're starting to develop a headache from straining to look downwards with your Magesight while keeping your eyes fixed on the path ahead. While the Shadowsteed has many advantages over flesh-and-blood horses, its willingness to gallop at full speed into a tree or river can be quite a downside. And through it all, not a single glimpse of a leyline. While that might be enough to quell your concerns of Kislev's army marching unawares into a superpowered Athel Loren Battle Wizard, it does nothing to sate your curiosity. So instead of turning back, you use Smoke and Mirrors to hop across the Urskoy near the village of Iranasgrad and start to follow the river upstream towards Kislev City. --- Two hours later, as you approach the village of Sava northwest of Kislev, you finally pick up a leyline, and one strong enough that you likely would have noticed it even if you weren't actively looking for it. Judging from its direction, you're certain that it is coming from Erengrad. That makes sense, as it is one of the three major cities of Kislev, and though you're not sure if it was ever an Elven settlement, the mouth of the Lynsk would have been a natural place for them to have erected a Waystone nexus even if they hadn't lived there. So energy is flowing into Kislev, but as far as you've seen so far, it isn't flowing out. You start to construct possible explanations for this in your mind, from the mysterious to the catastrophic, but you shake yourself out of it. You're going to be completing a circuit of Kislev City anyway in order to reach the Kreml Guard, so building theories now when much fuller data is only a few hours away would be a waste of effort. --- About an hour later, halfway between Kislev City and the village of Ardkha, you halt your Shadowsteed in consternation at the leyline you've discovered. As you might have guessed, there was a leyline between Kislev City and Praag, Kislev's third major city. What you hadn't guessed was that the leyline would be flowing northwards, taking power from Kislev to Praag. While you're relieved that all that power isn't gathering and curdling under Bokha Palace, it makes as little sense as water flowing uphill. The Waystone Network exists to gather magical energy from across the world and deliver it to the Great Vortex of Ulthuan, and while you do know that there are other, smaller networks, that Gross Selon is built to take in energy from Kislev City, and that Kislev City was originally founded as the Elven trade settlement of Athel Numiel for trade with Karak Ungor, both indicate that Kislev City would have once been part of the main Waystone Network. So something had to have changed for it to be flowing north from Kislev City instead of south. Your first instinct is to suspect some Chaos plot, as it's very easy to remember your own visit to Praag and suspect some deep wellspring of corruption that might be to blame. But on further thought that doesn't make sense to you. Praag is in a dire state, but it is less so than it was in the direct aftermath of the Great War Against Chaos. It may be recovering with heartbreaking slowness, but it is recovering. And it wouldn't be if the Waystones of half of Kislev or more were draining Dhar into Praag. So the energies must either be expended in Praag, or be flowing onwards onto some other unknown destination. You glare up the Kislev-Praag road, very conscious of the time ticking by. You're already going to be cutting it fine to reach the Kreml Guard in time to get sufficient sleep before a day of speeding them on their way with Rite of Way. There's no way to squeeze the four days it would take you to ride to Praag and back into this already very constricted timetable. You sigh and mentally add it to the very long list of unanswered questions you've accumulated on the subject of Waystones and turn your Shadowsteed southwards. --- Thankfully, it proves rather straightforward to find the Kreml Guard. Even if they weren't the only infantry column making their way down the narrow and rutted dirt road between Kislev City and Resvynhaf, their signature armament of a light bow and a heavy axe is hard to miss. You slow to a trot as you approach the column, as anyone approaching at what could be perceived as a charge seems very likely to have a bad time of it, and by the time you reach the column you see that part of it has already split off and is watching your approach, and by the size of the centremost figure and the aura of frost surrounding his glaive, you're fairly sure you've found the Tsarevich. Probably not the welcome every passer-by gets when approaching the column, but not every passer-by would be riding a horse made of shadows. "Atamanka Ved'ma Weber!" Boris calls out at your approach. "Heard you were in Kislev once more. Did your Elves tell you about these Elves?" "No, Laurelorn is as far removed from Athel Loren as the Elf Quarter of Erengrad is. I was looking into the trouble they caused on the Ostermark side of the border when I picked up their trail." "Many of your colleagues would have called the matter done when they realized it was Kislev's problem." "Before Khan-Queen Miska arrived in Kislev, Ostermark's capital was as far as it could physically get from the border, even though that meant being across the river from Sylvania. Now it prospers just across the river from Ryazan. It is in the Empire's interest for Kislev to be strong." "If only more realized it. Why have you come to me? Though we march to war, my father will ride to it, and will not wait for anything once he smells blood on air." "I know, and I was hoping to change that. There's a spell that should let you reach Resvynhaf in time-" "Wait, I read about this. Is this with boots and coins and blood and sometimes troops just disappear?" "No, I'd need a number of other Wizards for that. This is a spell of my own invention, one I used to good effect on the Karag Dum Expedition. All it does is make a flat, even surface out of just about any terrain." Boris looks at the churned remnants of the rutted path the Kreml Guard has left in its wake. "But not slippery, yha? Like proper Dwarf road?" You nod. "And you can do this all day?" You nod again. Boris considers that, before turning to the man next to him and rattling off a series of instructions. "My Kossars do not drink before a battle," he says, turning back to you as orders are shouted at the marching men who by now are some distance down the road, "but you are welcome to share our fire and food and koumiss." --- It takes shockingly little time for a small village of round Ungol tents to be erected and a meal of porridge and dumplings to be boiled, and once that is done the Kreml Guard gather around the fire in an air of easy camaraderie that Boris seems entirely at home in. You don't have nearly enough Kislevarin to immerse yourself, but that does give you the opportunity to observe, and you have enough to say thank you when the skins of koumiss circulating are handed to you. Koumiss has a reputation of being shockingly potent, but that's because unsuspecting visitors to Kislev take one taste of fermented mare's milk and stick to vodka for the rest of the night, which looks and tastes deceptively mild but hits like a runaway bull, and they blame the resultant blackout and hangover on the horse milk instead of the stuff that seemed like water. You find the koumiss to be surprisingly charming, like a mix of soured cream and Bretonnian bubble-wine. Once everyone has eaten their fill, there's a great deal of dancing, sparring, and wrestling, and it's often difficult to tell which is which. Despite their heavy arms and armour the Kreml Guard prove to be incredibly agile, and after watching some of the axe spars and being watched in turn by Boris, he asks you if you know your way around a blade. Branulhune's appearance in your hand supplies your answer for you, and an accepted challenge later you find yourself ringed by Kossars as you weigh up Boris, who's an intimidating sight even with the icy glow of his glaive muffled by a cloth wrapping. The two of you put on a decent showing for the audience, but you can tell that Boris is growing as frustrated by having to keep from unleashing the full power of his weapon as you are, and the two of you call it quits while you still can with good grace. You observe to him that there'll be plenty of opportunity to have a proper fight soon enough, and Boris claps you on the back. The next morning finds you atop your Shadowsteed in the morning mist, trying to ignore several hundred pairs of eyes watching you with cautious expectation. It's been a while since you've had cause to use Rite of Way, but the Praestantia syllables you'd constructed it with leap to your tongue as though it had been yesterday and Ulgu leaps to your command. You brace yourself for the initial jerk of draining energy as the path ahead of you disappears under a field of impenetrable fog, and then the draw lessens almost as sharply as you urge your Shadowsteed forward at a fraction of its possible speed. You let the chorus of the spell slip from your tongue to your internal monologue, then to the back of your mind. Behind you the foremost of the Kreml Guard cautiously wades into the fog, peering downward in confusion at the flat and solid surface that has somehow appeared where moments ago there had been rutted dirt, and then he is nudged by the man behind him and starts to walk. You increase your pace once and then again as the Kossars become familiar with the terrain you have supplied and threaten to overtake you until you're at as rapid a pace as infantry can maintain without breaking into a jog. Behind you a marching song begins in a tongue that sounds halfway between Kurgan and Kislevarin, Boris' voice loudest of all among them. [Casting Rite of Way: Learning, 72+29+10(favourable conditions)=111.] --- It's still several hours from dusk when you arrive at Resvynhaf, and it takes you a moment to remember how to stop casting the spell so you can step to the side and allow Boris and the Kreml Guard to make an impression upon the gathered pulks. Despite a day's hard march they stand tall and proud, Boris foremost among them, and he shouts a greeting to Boyar Kirill as he nears. After arrangements are made for food and drink for the Kossars, they, you, and Milica convene to discuss the latest happenings. [Rolling...] The Tzar, you hear via Milica's familiar, has finally gathered together the city rotas and is ready to leave the city tomorrow at dawn, which should have them arriving at Resvynhaf that evening. It is generally agreed that the Tzar is likely to order an attack on the intruders in the Shirokij the morning after that - or rather, considering how little is known of the intruders, to push into the Shirokij in the direction of the besieged villages and see what happens. That gives you a single day before everything is violence and confusion, and leaves you with the difficult question of how best to spend it. And having the heir to Kislev's throne present does open up new possibilities. [ ] Bring in Ice Witches Currently, the only Ice Witch that is likely to be present for the battle is Milica. If you travel to Kislev City, you could bring in additional Ice Witches on Shadowsteeds. Milica says there are at least two and perhaps as many as five Ice Witches in Kislev City that would be able to respond and could meaningfully contribute to a battle. [ ] Find the Boyar For some reason, the Athel Loren forces seem to be trying to lure in Boyar Kalashinivik and his rota. Boyar Kalashinivik should be somewhere on the road between Praag and Kislev. Intercept him and see if you can figure out what this is all about. [ ] Scout the Shirokij Of the forces here, only you would have any chance of moving unseen through the Shirokij. Use this to try to scout the enemy. [ ] Urge an attack From what little you know of Tzar Vladimir, it does seem like it might be preferable for the attack to be made under the command of Tsarevich Boris instead. Argue for the attack to begin before the Tzar arrives, while the gathered pulks are under Boris' authority. [ ] Attempt a parlay The Tsarevich can grant you the authority to negotiate with these intruders in the name of Kislev, though that's easier said than done. Attempt to make that happen without endangering yourself too much. [ ] Contact Ostermark The Tsarevich can grant you the authority to reach out to Ostermark to request their aid on behalf of Kislev, and their military is already mustered at Bechafen. Ride there and request Elector Count Hertwig pushes into the Shirokij from the south as Kislev's forces do so from the north. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a one hour moratorium

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 7

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Bring in Ice Witches Currently, the only Ice Witch that is likely to be present for the battle is Milica. If you travel to Kislev City, you could bring in additional Ice Witches on Shadowsteeds. Milica says there are at least two and perhaps as many as five Ice Witches in Kislev City that would be able to respond and could meaningfully contribute to a battle. Tally From their reputation, you suspect that the greatest strategic assets of an Athel Loren warhost are mobility and stealth, and tactically it's hard to look past the Elven capacity to spend centuries mastering their weapon of choice. But to a more typical point of view, the strange magics and terrible spirits that they are able to call on are rather flashy, and if given free reign to perform they'd be entirely capable of stealing the show. So you will ensure they do not have the opportunity to perform their magics unobstructed. If they want to bring strange magics and terrible spirits to Kislev, they can bloody well learn that Kislev is no slouch in the strange magics and terrible spirits department. "I am going to ride to Kislev City," you say to Boris in private. "I have magics that could allow even a middling rider to reach here before tomorrow's battle, and I intend to offer that service to the Ice Witches there, allowing them to answer the request for help from Boyar Kirill and the Ataman of Resvynhaf. But it seems to me that they would be more likely to respond if I am able to call on them in the name of the Tsarevich." Boris considers that for some time. "It is complicated situation you are stumbling into," he finally says. "My father does not like the Ice Witches, he says he has seen where putting faith in pale women with cold skin and strange magics leads. The Boyars respect them too much for him to act against them, but he will not call upon them. Thinks horse and steel will solve all problems." "Do you agree with that?" you ask carefully. It takes a while for him to respond. "In daydream world, Teclis listened to Tzar Alexis. Stayed here, built here. Then Kislev could have Witches like you, bound by oath and law to serve Tzar and Kislev. But in this world, Fire Spire was ruined and never rebuilt. In this world, every true servant of the Bear and the Flame and the Thunder died in Praag, and now thieves and cowards choke their temples." He looks over to his glaive, glistening with cold magic. "In this world, when horse and steel is not enough, Winter is all we have left." He nods to himself as he reaches a decision. "Tell the Ice Court that Tsarevich Boris Bokha calls on them to defend the land they claim to serve." --- [Rolling...] During the times of the rule of Khan-Queens, the Ice Court is a physical location within the wing of the royal palace made of glistening ice. The rest of the time it's a bit more conceptual. Luckily you have a guide in the form of Milica's hawk, who leads you through the streets of Kislev City until you reach the noble quarter, where the hawk leads you on a winding path through the least defensible noble quarter you've ever seen. Stepping over a knee-high fence into a courtyard with a mostly-frozen fountain centrepiece, you're delighted to see a familiar face. "Nie," Ljiljana says as you approach, not looking up from where the ice has been partially sculpted into a small army of miniature Winged Lancers. "Glad to see you haven't joined the winter," you say with a smile. She shrugs without looking up. "Too busy to die." "Busy making ice sculptures?" "No friends in palace, so need friends in boyarin. Boyar-wives having party here tomorrow." "Ah. And if some of those little lancers don't come home..." "They can look at all this work and wonder, why was this Ljiljana not at battle, saving my husband? Then they go yell at Tzar. Also, Boyar-wife pays well for fancy party. Their chickens do not peck at money." "Milica is down there." "Milica went down there when it was Boyar problem. Now stuck there." She waves a hand at the hawk, who is pecking at one of the tiny ice horses. "Follow bird to others. Zlata is somewhere, young enough to go running off into battle." "What if someone else called on the Ice Witches for help?" She looks up from her work. "Boyar Kalashinivik beat Tzar there?" "No. The Tsarevich did. And he calls on the Ved'ma to defend Kislev." "He left behind his pets?" You shake your head, smiling. "Ah. Your fog trick." She considers that for a moment, then sighs and swears. "Fine. South gate, thirty minutes." --- "This is my former Apprentice, Nadezhda," Ljiljana says, gesturing at a woman of about thirty who is loaded with a heavy-looking knapsack. She greets you in Kislevarin while looking you over with open curiosity. "She never learned Reikspiel so she can't stop me from telling you that only reason she wants to come is she wants to ride Boris. Summon your shadow horse for her." With a thought and a gesture you do so, and Nadezhda awkwardly clambers atop it, reflexively reaching for reigns that aren't there. "And for you as well?" you say, and then recoil back as you turn back to Ljiljana and instead find what looks something like a pure white Vargheist, and only the smugness of its expression and Nadezhda's lack of reaction that stops you from summoning Branulhune on the spot. "Okay, apparently not," you say faintly. You recall reading that Ice Witches could turn into terrible blizzard monsters, but you'd assumed it was poetic license. Performing Rite of Way at a gallop is a lot more challenging than at a march, but this time you're only doing it for a single person, so it's easy to slip into the rhythm and let the miles disappear underhoof as Nadezhda adapts to Ulgu horseback, while overhead a localized blizzard centres around the transformed form of Ljiljana as she flies above you. About three quarters of the way back you overtake the galloping rotas of the city boyars, who appear equally confused and outraged at being overtaken by the three of you. This also gives you enough time to get back to Boris and Milica, and after Boris formally and stiffly thanks a once more human Ljiljana for her response while Nadezhda stares raptly at him, you begin to plan for the Tzar's imminent arrival and thus for the push into the Shirokij that's bound to begin tomorrow. As Boris explains, due to the rather strained relations between the Tzar and the Ice Witches, the Tzar is likely to ignore the presence of the Ice Witches unless someone forces him to acknowledge them, giving you freedom to deploy wherever you think you'd be most needed. But if forced - by, say, you worming your way into the planning session for the upcoming battle - then you would be made officially part of the chain of command and will have to submit to the Tzar's decision on what part you and the Ice Witches will play. You essentially have to decide between you having some input for and control over the upcoming battle's overall strategy, or you and the Ice Witches having full control over the deployment of magical forces. [ ] War Council Have input into the planning for the upcoming battle. [ ] Witch Council Have freedom to decide what part you, Johann, and the Ice Witches will play in the upcoming battle. - There will be a one hour moratorium.

Unrest in Ostermark, Part 8

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Witch Council Have freedom to decide what part you, Johann, and the Ice Witches will play in the upcoming battle. Tally As the Tsarevich, Boyars, and Rotamasters confer with the Tzar, you and Johann hold your own little conference off to one side with the Ice Witches, with Ljiljana translating for Milica and Nadezhda. Ljiljana and Milica are both capable of the Ice Witch equivalent of Battle Magics, summoning blizzards to freeze a few or to hinder many, and freezing the river to make it easier to cross or to severely inconvenience anyone midway through fording it. And while Nadezhda isn't yet fully comfortable with all but the least of Battle Magics, this battle taking place in a forest gives her an unexpected advantage: a tree rapidly frozen will explode, potentially causing all kinds of damage with wooden shrapnel and falling branches, thus allowing her to have battlefield-scale effects with more reliable magics. And, of course, Ljiljana has the ability to turn into some sort of... giant ice bat? Which certainly looked like it could do some damage in a fight. Unfortunately, it seems like an encore of her performance at the Kul camp is not a possibility. You share the most relevant of the capabilities of Johann and yourself, and spark a brief and confusing debate over whether the Mystifying Miasma actually interferes with the flow of time or just mortal perception of it, which then evolves into an even more abstract argument over whether there is a meaningful distinction between the two. Ljiljana looks quite relieved when the debate she'd had to translate every word of is interrupted by the approach of Kovnik Loza, who is doing a fair job of masking how intimidated he is. "The path to Ryazan is a narrow cart-path along the Shirokij River," he relays to you. "The Kreml Guard and the rotas of Resvynhaf, Rakhov, Volstara, and Resov will clear-cut the trees alongside it to enlarge the path, and will use the logs to build fortified positions along it. The krugs will scout in force through the forest within horn's blow of the path. The other rotas will patrol the expanded path and stand ready to respond to any contact with the enemy along it." You nod to yourself as you consider that. Strategically, it reshapes the would-be battlefield into a form more suited to the Kislevites and less for the enemy, and puts the enemy in a position where the longer they hang back, the stronger Kislev's position becomes. If they refuse to engage at all, then the Shirokij will soon be cut in half by a fortified and enlarged road all the way to Ryazan, at which point the enemy must either engage or lift their siege of the village and withdraw to one half of the Shirokij or the other. And in terms of morale, responding to a warband from Athel Loren by cutting a swath through the heart of a forest is likely to make them want to react. It's a strategy that will either provoke a quick reaction or punish the lack of one, and either scenario is a win for Tzar Vladimir. It also plays to the individual strengths and avoids the most prominent weaknesses of the involved forces. Resvynhaf, Rakhov, Volstara and Resov are all woodcutting stanitsas, so they would have a familiarity with forests that the other rotas would lack, so they would be the ones most able and equipped to act as lumberjacks and the ones most likely to be able to deal with any reaction their clear-cutting might provoke. The krugs of the southern oblast are likewise used to the forests that hem in their lands, and would have honed their ability to be able to negotiate the forest on horseback while hunting in them. And the rotas from the city and from the unforested stanitsas are, like most Kislevites, largely ignorant of acting in forests, so they will be patrolling the cleared path and otherwise being kept in reserve until battle is joined, at which point they can travel along the path most of the way and dismount and engage the enemy on foot. For a strategy formed with little information about the enemy and for terrain so far removed from what the average Kislevite is used to, it's certainly sound. The only remaining question is what part you and the Ice Witches will play in it. You begin to discuss it with them, and though they don't come right out and say so, it quickly becomes apparent that the Ice Witches are holding off on making any decision until you give your own perspective. Considering the enemy and the terrain, you suppose that makes sense - if you were about to go into a battle against Norscans on the steppes and had an Ice Witch on hand to advise you, you'd definitely listen. Mathilde [ ] [GREY] Scouting the forest with the krugs [ ] [GREY] Guarding the forest rotas as they expand and fortify the path [ ] [GREY] Patrolling the path with the city rotas [ ] [GREY] Standing ready to respond with the Tzar and Boyars [ ] [GREY] Investigate Boyar Kalashinivik [ ] [GREY] Other (write in) Johann [ ] [GOLD] Scouting the forest with the krugs [ ] [GOLD] Guarding the forest rotas as they expand and fortify the path [ ] [GOLD] Patrolling the path with the city rotas [ ] [GOLD] Standing ready to respond with the Tzar and Boyars [ ] [GOLD] Other (write in) Ice Witches [ ] [ICE] Scouting the forest with the krugs [ ] [ICE] Guarding the forest rotas as they expand and fortify the path [ ] [ICE] Patrolling the path with the city rotas [ ] [ICE] Standing ready to respond with the Tzar and Boyars [ ] [ICE] Other (write in) - There will be a twelve hour moratorium - to consider the new information, to allow for any write-in strategies to develop, and to give people enough time to look up from Total Warhammer and notice an update has happened. - The possibilities I've given only allow for supplementing part of the forces according to the Tzar's plan. Anything more creative will be the domain of write-ins.

Battle of the Shirokij, Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [GREY] Scouting the forest with the krugs [*] [GOLD] Patrolling the path with the city rotas [*] [ICE] Guarding the forest rotas as they expand and fortify the path Tally The decision is fairly straightforward: the Tzar has a distrust of magical women and the Ice Witches aren't especially mobile (except for Ljiljana, but her transformation into what she calls a 'Morozvolich' is likely to spook the horses of the Ungols), so it makes the most sense for them to work with the forest rotas - and with Boris, which Nadezhda seems nervously enthusiastic about. You want to leave at least one Wizard with the main body of the force and close to leadership, and if the Tzar has a problem with magic-using women, then he should find Johann refreshingly masculine - plus Johann would have trouble being an effective scout, and honestly his blindness is far from the biggest issue. More prominent than that is how very visible he fundamentally is. From the soul up he has been shaped by his desire to be seen, and everything he is rejects the entire concept of stealth. For that reason, you find yourself among the krugs: the mostly Ungol nomadic communities of Kislev's oblasts. They do not maintain a distinct force that is sent off to battle as needed, as instead they go to war in almost their entirety, leaving only their oldest and youngest behind to watch over their herds. This far south the krugs speak a dialect of Gospodarinyi with only light influences from the Ungol tongue, so you're able to use your smattering of the language to find an ataman who knows fairly good Reikspiel, probably because of smuggling. There would be a fair bit of profit to be made in taking goods overland between the upper Talabec and Kislev City, and no exciseman would have a chance of successfully intercepting a krug on their own oblast. Though you haven't made as much of an impression as Johann, your proven ability to summon an inexhaustible horse from thin air means you have no need to prove yourself, and no objection is made as you attach yourself to the scouts that will be penetrating deepest into the forest. --- [Fey scouting Kislev's forces outside forest: 14.] [Scouting inside forest, Fey vs Krugs: 5 vs 55.] In a shadowed copse, a spirit of spite and malice thinks and plots. It is far from the forests it knows, so it knows not what to expect of these manlings that are to be its prey. Are they Elf-puppets who have their weakest forces on foot and their elites on horseback and encased in metal? Or are they Dwarf-puppets who fight mostly on foot with the steel and gunpowder of their masters? Information from scouting flows in, and only compounds the confusion as it tries to make sense of it all. The Household was finally responding to the torment of their southern neighbour, and they creep down the riverside path with axe and bow, tearing at the trees as they go. The axe is to be expected of those that dare harvest the forest, but the bow suggests these are Elf-puppets. But the scouts say that the few horses they ride are bare. So perhaps these are Dwarf-puppets? But the scouts see no sign of Dwarf-weapons, nor any sniff of the unnatural powders that fuel them. Doubt rises, but is brushed aside by impatience. Of course these manlings are ill-equipped, they are the Glade Guard of a single House. Does it matter whether they are particularly weak Elf-puppets or particularly weak Dwarf-puppets? They will feed the forest all the same. Finally the last piece of the puzzle falls into place as the one who must be the local Highborn is identified by the armoured troops that surround it. The whiff of alien magic about its spear confirms it: this could only be the augured target of the hunt, the bearer of two intermingled royal bloodlines: one of the northern snow, one of the southern sands. A grin forms as forces begin to rally. Though the trees of this strange place are too deadened by the local magics to call for vengeance, they will still have it, and then one more tool of deliverance will be at hand. --- Most Wizards would have overlooked the first signs of trouble, but most Wizards had not spent months in the heart of Laurelorn. When the first of the tiny nature-spirits began to hover through the branches, you pointed out the soft glow and told the ataman that it was a spy for the enemy. She does not hesitate, and a few murmured orders has the entire band draw bow and arrow from the holster and quiver on opposite hips, and a moment later a sheaf of arrows are sent whistling through the air to rattle through the boughs nearest to the spite. You cautiously advance and inspect the site, and from the bloom of scattered energies you're sure the spirit was at least injured by an arrow, if not entirely decorporealized. Messengers are sent off to warn the other scouts of what to look for as you consider the matter. If the enemy had used any kind of more traditional scouts, you'd be tempted to try to sneak up on one and incapacitate them for interrogation. But spites? Laurelorn only trusted spites because they were bound by the magics of the Grey Lords. The only beings that would trust the scouting of an untamed spite would be other forest spirits. Word reaches you throughout the day of a number of similar encounters, both from the krugs and from the Kreml Guard. All of them end similarly: with the spirit watchers being chased off by the expert aim of Ungol warriors. You wonder if that would dissuade the enemy, but you suppose by Asrai standards their aim would be rather mediocre. In any case, you're not just preventing proper scouting but also bleeding the enemy of scouts they can't replace, as Loren Arhain is no friend to Athel Loren. You're just starting to wonder where that thought came from when the horns begin to blow. You and the krug turn, and the Ungols quickly fall behind as the Shadowsteed easily outstrips the cautious trot of horses who need to be careful of their footing. As the trees thin out and eventually give way entirely to a field of felled trunks, you catch sight of the enemy immediately: a disorderly mob of vaguely humanoid beings of thorns and twisted wood, glowing with lilac energies, entangled in a melee with the Kislevite woodsmen. From what you can see their numbers are about even, and axe seems to bite into wood just as easily and often as talons do into flesh. Neither side shows any sign of being dissuaded, one as outraged by the felling of trees as the other is by enemies on their soil. In amongst them is Milica, a sword of ice in one hand and a swarm of frozen shards being fired from the other. By the river a knot of resistance has formed with the Kreml Guard split in half, one hacking at any of the Dryads that get near with their own axes and the other firing volley after volley into the river, which has been frozen solid with still more of the Dryads encased within, making easy targets. As you take in the battlefield with experienced eyes, you spot several problems. In the river, one much larger being has torn itself loose of the ice and advances at a slow but unstoppable pace towards the Tsarevich: an entire ambulatory tree, perhaps thirty feet tall or more, with a rainbow of glowing spites warring with its lilac inner glow. Ljiljana stands among the Kreml Guard staring it down, and the energies of winter are beginning to grow within her. You catch a glimpse of Boris himself among the Kreml Guard, and to your surprise he's not in the thick of battle, instead staring upward with spear in hand and a look of concentration on his face. You follow his gaze and see why: overhead is the hovering form of a Manticore, Chaos' mockery of the noble Griffon. It seems to be returning Boris' gaze, and seems about to swoop. Nadezhda is by his side, but her attention is on keeping the river in winter's grip, and may be unable to help. On the path, a trio of the Dryads have not charged with their fellows, and Ghyran flows through them as they attempt to bend the forest to their will. When the scouts begin to return those three could prove easy prey for them, but to those without Windsight, they might seem a much lesser priority than the Dryads currently engaged - and if left unopposed, they could turn the tide of battle. Milica is closest to them, but is currently engaged with the Dryads in melee. And above the din of battle and the whirling of magics and emotions, there are two undertones that are equally easy and impossible to ignore: the faint but growing sound of approaching horns from the rest of the Kislevite forces, and the dissonant note in the native energies of the forest. There is a wisp of Ulgu here that is very much not of the namesake of the forest, and the forest is resisting all attempts of it to blend in to its shadows, giving you tiny glimpses of it out of the corner of your soul. Somewhere out there, the source of today's violence is watching. There is only one of you, and there are several places where you might make all the difference. Where will you lend your assistance? [ ] Treeman Face down the approaching Treeman with Ljiljana. [ ] Manticore Engage the swooping Manticore with Boris. [ ] Spellcasters Disrupt the trio of Dryad spellcasters before they can force the local trees to aid them. [ ] Leader Seek and engage the hidden watcher. [ ] Reinforcements Leave the battle to reach the approaching reinforcements, and use Rite of Way to speed their vanguard. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - If you wish, the exact way that Mathilde engages a particular enemy can be written in. By default Mathilde will use my best judgement, but the creativity of the thread has worked wonders in the past. - Part of this update was originally posted here.

Battle of the Shirokij, Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Leader Seek and engage the hidden watcher. Tally To an outside perspective, between one second and another the Wizard and her steed simply vanished. To an outside perspective familiar with Grey Magic, now would be a good time for everyone opposed to that Wizard to start checking over their shoulder. Enveloped within Shroud of Invisibility, you do your best to tune out the din of battle and try to focus on the discordance in the shadows, as to leave the leader of this host to their own devices could be disastrous. [Mathilde spotting Drycha: Intrigue, 24+27+10(Windsage)=61 vs 69+25+10(Trait: Hidden Watcher)-20(Rejected by the Forest)=84.] [Drycha spotting Mathilde: Intrigue, 27+25+10(Trait: Hidden Watcher)=62 vs 21+27+10(Invisibility)=58.] [How is Drycha hiding?: Learning, 10+29+5(Diplomacy: Eonir)=44.] As you move through the forest, you quickly grasp what you're not looking for. You're familiar enough with how the Winds move during battle to be able to spot a whorl of Ulgu where there shouldn't be one, and the absence of any indicates that your target is hidden in some other way. You turn your eyes to the trees themselves, both to the branches a watcher might be perched upon or the trunks that a Forest Spirit might lurk within, but you see nothing that might be your opponent. [Woodsmen vs Dryads - Martial, 72+15+10(Milica)+10(Kreml Guard support fire)=107 vs 14+20+10(outnumber)=44.] With a sliver of your attention you're unable to completely tear away, you note that the Dryads on the road are being brutalized by the foresters they face, in no small part thanks to Milica in the fray and the support fire of the Kreml Guard. [Mathilde spotting Drycha: Intrigue, 48+27+10(Windsage)=85 vs 20+25+10(Trait: Hidden Watcher)-20(Rejected by the Forest)=35.] [Drycha spotting Mathilde: Intrigue, 35+25+10(Trait: Hidden Watcher)=70 vs 41+27+10(Invisibility)=78.] You almost kick yourself when you see it. You spent your formative years in a liminal realm, checking for one here should have been the first thing you thought of, especially after having seen Laurelorn's in action so recently. The Dreaming Wood, Queen Marrisith had called it, as close as a thought and writhing with indignation at the being within it. With careful steps you approach the ripple in the surface of reality that signifies something of significant metaphysical size moving on the other side, shadowing it as it approaches the battle. [Woodsmen vs Dryads: Martial, 100+15+10(Milica)+10(Kreml Guard support fire)+5(outnumber)=140 vs 45+20=65.] [Boris vs Manticore: Martial, 83+20+10(Shard Blade)=113 vs 48+25+5(Frenzy)=78.] [Ljiljana vs Treeman: 80, 92.] [Kreml Guard firing on river Dryads: Martial, 91+20=111.] [Rolling...] And what a battle it is proving to be, as the Dryads fall as readily as the trees they protect, battle cries springing from the lips of the woodsmen as they practice their trade. Behind them the Manticore has attempted to dive upon the Tsarevich and impaled itself upon his readied glaive, and in the river a wave of ice has crept up the legs of the approaching Treeman as Ljiljana adds her strength to Nadezhda. With a series of hollow, echoing cracks craters open in the Treeman's body as the freezing sap expands within its body, and arrows begin to punch into these craters as the Kreml Guard turn their attention from the few remaining Dryads in the river to the Treeman. The ripple seems to react to this, moving faster and with purpose, and as soon as you extrapolate its course and confirm its intentions you teleport over to Ljiljana intercept it. [Mathilde counterambush: Martial, 24+23+10(surprise)+10(invisible)=67 vs 74+20-20(Rejected by the Forest)=74.] [Ljiljana reaction: 81.] Within the fallen trunk of a dying tree, the writhing fabric of reality is slit open and an avatar of embittered wrath wriggles forth, ephemeral spirit solidifying into the substance of the tree that allowed it entrance into the world. Glowing eye sockets lock onto Ljiljana as the being silently wrestles itself free of the trunk, and then it leaps with outstretched talons, flying right into- Right over your blade. With inhuman speed it twists in mid-air to avoid the swing of Branulhune, and what would have been a fatal swoop turns into an ungainly tumble as it skids through mud and leaf litter. Ljiljana turns with a fistful of ice, redirecting her stream of frost at this new foe, and it is forced to skitter backwards on all fours to avoid it. Heads turn and a cry goes up as the Kreml Guard notice this unexpected intruder behind their lines. [Mathilde interception: Martial, 85+23+10(invisible)=118 vs 38+20=58.] To its credit, the being only takes a second to react to this change in circumstances, managing to leap to its feet without losing its momentum away from Ljiljana and starting to run back to the trunk that gave it form, where reality is still torn open and bleeding. Her speed is inhuman and her course was perfectly calculated despite the fact you are still invisible to mundane senses - the momentum of your swing has your blade too far away to react before she's past you. Against any ordinary swordsman, she would escape. You are no ordinary swordsman, and Branulhune is no ordinary sword. With a thought Branulhune vanishes from your hands and takes its momentum with it, and you swing empty hands towards the Dryad as it sprints past you, Branulhune reappearing with a painful jolt in time to catch it across the waist. Gromril tears through bark and wood and out the other side, sending two halves of the being flying, splinters and sap and malign energies filling the air. The top half hits the ground and then arrests its sprawl with talons dug into soil. It twists to look at you, glowing eyes locking onto yours as they glow even brighter with hatred and outrage. For a moment you think it is going to try to throw itself at you, but then the eyes dim slightly as Ulgu shivers through the air. You recognize teleportation cantrips starting to form, and have only a moment to act before it will be gone. [ ] Counter Attempt to disrupt the magic that the Dryad is performing, with the intention of forcing it to stay and fight. [ ] Attack Charge and attack the Dryad before it can complete its magic. [ ] Dragonflask Dragonflask. [ ] Pursue Pursue the being into the realm it is trying to retreat to. [ ] Disengage Let it retreat, and help mop up the remaining enemies. [ ] Bind You do know a range of techniques for binding Apparitions, and a Forest Spirit is metaphysically similar enough that it may be possible to bind this being to you. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Dice rolls: Round 1, Round 2, Round 3, Round 4. - The 'Bind' option was suggested by @pucflek here and its inclusion in the above list of options is not a statement on my part as to how reasonable an idea it may be.

Battle of the Shirokij, Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Dragonflask Tally For a brief moment you're overwhelmed with the heady hubris of the idea of trying to apply the Apparition-binding techniques you learned from the Gold Order to the being in front of you, but good sense and your desire to finally test the Dragonflask in combat conditions prevail. You draw the flask from within your robes and swig down the mouthful of spirits it contains, wincing at the unnatural burning sensation as the Dwarven whiskey evaporates and unleashes its payload of Aqshy within your sinuses. Knowing what to expect, you're able to expel the fireball in a controlled cough rather than a sneeze, and the world turns white and ringing as the flash and roar of the magic drowns out your senses. [Magesight: Learning, 39+29+10(Windsage)-20(Blinded by Aqshy)=58.] When your vision returns a moment later, you take in a smoking crater where the top half of a Dryad had been. There's plenty of smouldering splinters that may or may not have been part of your target, but nothing large enough for you to be sure it came from them instead of the detritus of the forest floor. When you try to focus your Magesight through the ripples of so much Aqshy being unleashed in an instant, you're able to catch a glimpse of the splintered remains of what had been an attempt to weave Ulgu into a teleportation spell, now quite thoroughly disrupted. You exhale in relief at that - you don't know enough about Dryads to say for sure whether that's the end of this particular being or not, but at the very least their part in this battle is done. [Kreml Guard vs Treeman: Martial, 84+20+10(outnumber)=114 vs 18+30-15(heavily wounded)=33.] [Boris: Martial, 86+20+10(Shard Blade)=116.] [Nadezhda: Learning, 63+15=78.] You return Ljiljana's thoughtful look with a smile - your invisibility having been shattered by the use of the Dragonflask - and turn your attention to the rest of the battlefield. Nearby, the Treeman appears to have reached the bank by clawing its way across the ice, and though several of the Kreml Guard lie dead and dying around it, the rest are swarming it with axes swinging. As you watch, Nadezhda turns the flow of ice from the river to the Treeman, slowing its actions for long enough for Boris' flying leap to thrust the blade of his glaive into the Treeman's face, the lilac glow dimming and the spites scattering as the being finally succumbs to its many injuries. [Horse Archer vs Branchwraiths: Martial vs Learning, 99+20=119 vs 64+25=89.] Behind you, the woodsmen had finished off most of the Dryads and had begin to charge the magic-users, but before they could reach them or the Dryads could finish their spell, arrows slamming into the Dryads announces the arrival of the Ungol horsemen that had been scouting the forest. One of them topples and the magic is disrupted long enough for the woodsmen to reach the two that remain, and they fall under a series of axe blows, refusing to the last to turn their attention from the spell they had been trying to cast. The last of the lilac glow finally fades from the battlefield, leaving the remains of the fallen enemies difficult to distinguish from the felled trees their bodies lie among. Boris pulls his glaive from the Treeman and thrusts it skywards. "Slava Kislev!" he cries, and it is repeated by all present, Kossar and Gospodar and Ungol alike. --- Tzar Vladimir arrives soon after, and his disappointment at having missed the battle lasts only as long as it takes him to catch sight of the fallen Manticore. After that point his attention goes towards organizing a cart for the trophy and having a messenger sent to warn his personal taxidermist to be ready as he examines the teeth and claws of the beast. All other details are left to be taken care of by others, who seem unsurprised by this turn of events. Over the next few hours, you and Johann watch the battlefield be restored to something resembling order. The wounded are carted off, pyres are built for the dead, and some of the rotas are dismissed to return home. Boris speaks personally to each of the woodsmen who fought so well against the Dryads, and most of them end up accepting his offer to join the Kreml Guard. The Ice Witches gather up every scrap of Dryad they can identify and fill several carts with now-inanimate wood, debating back and forth over what that they're going to do with it all. You've already claimed the lower half of the being you destroyed as your own trophy, and are considering whether you should use the credit for this day's work to claim some more. And once the most urgent tasks are complete, you meet with Boris and Ljiljana among the debris to discuss the day's work. "An easy battle is a good battle," Boris says. "And we owe it to you, Atamanka Ved'ma Weber. The rota of Boyar Kalashinivik would have been helpless against this force." "I am glad to have been able to assist the Empire's ally," you reply. "But still I ask, why? What brought them here?" "Athel Loren's actions are hard to understand, but when they have come to the Empire, it has been with specific targets in mind. And in this case, it seems to have been the local Boyar." "The Praag Kalashiniviks were loyalists to Tzarina Kattarin," Ljiljana notes. "The Resvynhaf Kalashiniviks managed to avoid the purges of Tzar Pavel, but perhaps that was a mistake. Perhaps they were meddling with something that drew the attention of the Forest Spirits. If you wish it, Tsarevich, the Ice Court could investigate them." He considers her for a moment before nodding. "Do it. If anyone is trying to thaw out that monster, they need to be found and killed." Ljiljana smiles. The Ice Witches have been on the outs with the Tzar, and you think you just saw them get their in with his heir. "The Widow will see it done." You tune out their discussing of the specifics as you consider the battlefield. Both Kislev and the Ice Witches have benefited from today, and there's a number of ways you can ask for that debt to be repaid. The Waystone Project which brought you here in the first place comes to mind, but so too does your nascent library back in Karak Eight Peaks. A word from the Tsarevich could grant an army of scribes access to a number of different libraries and institutions within Kislev. [Magical component gained: The lower half of an Ulgu-wielding Branchwraith] Mathilde will claim the one choice from each of the below two categories that get the most votes. Gratitude of Kislev: [ ] [KISLEV] Waystone Project: Kislev A formal partnership with Kislev itself will mean you will have easy access to its lands for study and experimentation in the later stages of the Waystone Project. [ ] [KISLEV] Waystone Project: Hag Witches Boris has a strong relationship with his Ungol subjects, and would be able to arrange Hag Witch cooperation for the Waystone Project if you ask for it. [ ] [KISLEV] Library: Bokha Palace After almost a thousand years of Kislev's often-tumultuous succession, it's anyone's guess what sort of books might have accumulated within the Palace Gospodarin, and what might have survived its near-destruction in the Great War. [ ] [KISLEV] Library: University of Kislev Significantly more modest than many equivalent institutions of the Empire but renowned in certain circles for the study of beasts and spirits, as the lines between the two are often blurred in Kislev. [ ] [KISLEV] Library: Magnus Gardens of Praag A surprising oasis of art and learning within the cursed city, the institutions of the Magnus Gardens produce some of the finest artists, musicians, and astrologers in the Old World. [ ] [KISLEV] Library: Writer's Rooms of Kislev The headquarters of the government-funded scribes for a mostly-illiterate country, Writer's Rooms boast over eight hundred years of the transcribed history and culture of Kislev. [ ] [KISLEV] EIC Foothold Though it's far from any of the EIC's current outposts, a nod from the Tsarevich could open up a market that it is usually very difficult for Empire traders to get into. [ ] [KISLEV] Manticore If you have some use in mind for Manticore parts, the taxidermist could be made to hand over to you everything he removes from the beast. [ ] [KISLEV] Boon Leave the favour unpaid. One day he will be a Tzar, and a favour from a Tzar can be a great thing to have. Gratitude of the Widow: [ ] [WIDOW] Waystone Project: Ice Witches You've worked well with the Ice Witches multiple times now. Seek to continue that trend by bringing them in to the Waystone Project. [ ] [WIDOW] Library: Ice Court If asked to contribute to your Library the Ice Witches are likely to carefully excise anything that might give insight into their own magic, but they would still have centuries of accumulated observations on the other magical phenomena of the Old World. [ ] [WIDOW] Treeman wood The most difficult of the trees felled this day, wood and spirit entwined is sure to make for useful materials that could be of use for either Collegiate or Dwarven artifice. [ ] [WIDOW] Dryad wood Less dense in power than the wood of a Treeman but greater in total mass, the large amount of spirit-manifested wood left behind by the defeated Dryads could be used to make something of considerable size or number. [ ] [WIDOW] Boon Leave the favour unpaid. You never know when Ice Witch assistance might come in handy. - There will be a six hour moratorium to give other suggestions time to be suggested. - While today was good work, it didn't save an entire Kingdom. Suggestions should be on the scale of a single skilled specialist or a single conversation the Tsarevich would need to have with someone. - Before anyone asks: Mathilde doesn't know enough about Dryads to say whether or not this was a permakill, and didn't roll well enough on her Magesight to identify the trajectory of any departing soul or spirit. - Dice rolls: here.

Turn 37 Results - 2488 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [KISLEV] Waystone Project: Hag Witches [*] [WIDOW] Waystone Project: Ice Witches Tally As the planning for drilling into the secrets of the unfortunate local Boyar wraps up, you re-enter the conversation. "The Waystone Project has built up quite a roster of Magisters, Mages, and a Runelord," you say. "The magical traditions of Kislev would be more than welcome to join it." Boris and Ljiljana exchange thoughtful looks. "Your Colleges are built on Elf secrets," Boris says to you. "Perhaps can squeeze some more out of them." "Me and Nadezhda will be busy with Boyar," Ljiljana says. "Milita only speaks Gospodarinyi, Věnceslava would get herself into trouble... Zlata can go. Good with languages, good with new people, thirst to prove herself." "I think I will send word to Boyar Yevschenko. Baba Niedzwenka knows Elf and Imperinyi, and he will be happy for break from her." Ljiljana frowns at that, but doesn't comment. "We will be happy to have them," you say. "I'll send word to our Embassy in Kislev City to do up papers for them. If they make their way to Aarnau or Middenheim, I can arrange an escort to Tor Lithanel." "I didn't think I'd see you again after you decided to go chasing Elves," Boris says frankly. "But if you give us something we can use to push back the Za on top of all you have already done, you will have proven the value of the partnership between Kislev and the Empire." "I'll do my best to live up to the examples of Magnus and Teclis," you say firmly. --- You return to the Empire in high spirits, passing through Bechafen on the way to send word to the Chancellor of what the problem was and that it has been taken care of. They won't immediately stand down the army on the word of a single person, but they'll be pointed in the right direction for confirming things for themselves and able to start quashing the wilder rumours. You also have reports of your investigations sent off to those that sent you on them. There are, you note, significant gaps regarding the matters you were supposed to look into, but you doubt anyone will mind since you made it so that they were no longer a problem that needs investigating. Having spread word everywhere you were required to, instead of heading west back to Tor Lithanel, you continue southwards towards a destination just beyond Stirland. There is, you're aware, a problem with your library. Karak Eight Peaks is quite some distance away from the Empire - though that distance will seem shorter once the Black Water canal is completed - and with its shelves bare of all but your personal collection, it would be difficult to convince most people why they should have any interest in it. This could trap you in a nasty little circle of being unable to expand your library without the prestige of already having a large library. But there's one group in the Empire that has already bought in to Karak Eight Peaks - the Halflings of the Moot. And though the Mootland Genealogical Library in Eicheschatten might not be the most famous of libraries in the Old World, the millennia of accumulated history and culture it contains would go a long way to giving your library a bit more substance. The Genealogical Library is run by the Cult of Quinsberry, the Halfling God of knowledge, ancestry, and tradition. The position of Head Librarian is intertwined with that of High Priest, and the current incumbent is a man with substantial sideburns and an unlit pipe never far from his mouth, and he nibbles on the stem thoughtfully as you explain your proposition. "And in providing a space for our books, you thereby increase the size and prestige of this library o'yourn." You nod, unabashed. "If yer willing t'take what yer given, might be an arrangement t'be made. Could always use more space, but there's nothing here that's entirely a waste of it. If ye can guarantee that we'll still have access..." "Elder Hluodwica has secured rights of free passage for all citizens of the Moot in Karak Eight Peaks," you confirm, "and Barak Varr has ships serving as ferries from the Skull River to Ulrikadrin." "And soon that canal upriver. Well, as for the bloodline records, those've travelled to the Karak will've been wanting copies at some point. And those't go there or come here to marry will mean that sooner'r later, there'll be need for copies of every extant bloodline. Long's yer able to wait, ye'll accumulate the lot." "I have no problem with that. It's intended to be a long-term project." "And ye'll cover transport, I take it?" "Just let the local EIC branch know and they'll take it from there." "The one with the mark of three swords?" You nod. "Alright then. It seems we have an agreement." You smile as you shake the Halfling's hand. That went surprisingly smoothly, but you suppose it's a natural enough partnership. The Cult of Quinsberry is religiously bound to preserve an enormous amount of information, even though the passage of centuries has rendered a great deal of it nearly useless. It may be stricturally required to preserve the complete family trees of the Halfling Clan that was wiped out by Waaagh Gorbad in the 1700s, and once in a very long while it might be necessary to consult a single one of those very many tomes over some manner of lineage or inheritance, but the space and effort and expense it takes to store and preserve entire roomfuls of books would weigh heavily on any library. You've come out of nowhere and offered to take on all of that burden at your own expense, and the only downside is it will now take someone a fairly long boat ride on the rare occasions one of those tomes is needed. And considering the amount of regular traffic back and forth between the Moot and the Karak once the canal is completed, it probably won't even be that big a bother for someone already heading to the Karak to bring a request for a specific tome or set of tomes, and for someone already heading to the Moot to take those books with them. And while you're not very likely to ever need any of that information, this does get you a foot in the door to make copies of their other materials. Which... is easier said than done, admittedly. As you experienced for yourself in Stirland, there's only so many literate workers available at any given time. You'll need to think about some sort of method to secure a large number of reliable scribes. Perhaps an arrangement with the Cult of Scripsisti, or perhaps getting the EIC to begin recruiting from everywhere they have a presence, or perhaps a school in Karak Eight Peaks to teach and recruit citizens of Karag Nar who don't wish to become Undumgi... there's a number of possible approaches, and choosing between them all is a matter for another time. For now, you can consider this a good day's work - the first official partner library of the Kron-Azril-Ungol, and soon an influx of tomes that will go some way to filling those empty, echoing halls. --- Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The five with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Laurelorn [ ] Max The entire time you've known Maximilian, he has been pursuing his own goal of true transmutation via magically-enhanced blacksmithing. Check in to see how he's going with that. [ ] Thorek See what inroads Thorek has made with the Major Houses of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Cadaeth You've had unanswered questions about Dryads for some time, and your encounter with them in the Shirokij gives you a good pretext to ask them. [ ] Magister Tochter Grunfeld Get to know Tochter Grunfeld, ritualist, traditionalist, and veteran of the Sylvanian Campaign. [ ] Baba Niedzwenka Get to know the Erengrad Hag Witch that Tsarevich Boris has sent to contribute to the Waystone Project. [ ] Zlata Get to know the young woman who is the Ice Witch contribution to the Waystone Project. [ ] Panoramia - Tor Lithanel Now that you're somewhat familiar with it, introduce Panoramia to the people and sights of the city. [ ] Panoramia - Laurelorn Now that you're somewhat familiar with it, introduce Panoramia to the beings and biomes of the forest. Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Gretel She's apparently getting involved in the Karaz Ankor's ambitions in the Border Princes. [ ] The We See how their self-guided societal evolution is going. [ ] Okri The new Loremaster of Karak Eight Peaks is Okri Drakkisson of Clan Bronzebeard, formerly of Karak Norn. Meet your replacement and gauge what kind of person he is. [ ] Kazrik and Edda They are to be wed. Attend their nuptials. Foreign Relations [ ] Stirland See for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. [ ] Middenland See how the Ulricans are going with their new Eonir coreligionists. [ ] Karaz-a-Karak To investigate their preparations for the Mount Silverspear campaign. [ ] The Black Water Canal Pay another visit to the canal project, and see if there's any further signs of sabotage. Friends Abroad [ ] Roswita Get a sense for who will control Sylvania after you turned down the position. [ ] Kasmir See how his partnership with Sylvania's native faith has been going. Following Up [ ] Mira Give an in-person report on the events in Talabheim, and find out how Alric reacted to them. [ ] Alric Or you could cut out the middleman and ask Alric himself about current events. [ ] Paranoth Give an in-person report on the events in the Shirokij, and see if he knows anything about the being you defeated. [ ] Amber College Check in on the salamanders. [ ] Gold College See what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Organ Vat Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Skull River Ambush Look into the investigation of the mining of the Skull River, and any consequences of it. [ ] The Weber Estate Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Which witch dicerolls. - Thanks to everyone that provided ideas to replenish the pool of possible social actions.

Turn 37 Social - 2488 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Kazrik and Edda [*] Baba Niedzwenka [*] Panoramia - Laurelorn [*] Cadaeth [*] Paranoth [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else Tally Making its leisurely way up the river is a sailing pinnace, crewed solely by a plump old woman in a black frock with short white hair, one hand on the tiller and the other holding the mainsheet. Without context, this is an entirely mundane scene that could be found in any number of places within the Empire. That the pinnace has sailed through the Sea of Claws and is now making its way up the Schaukel towards Tor Lithanel is one set of key details that recontextualizes the scene; another is that it is making its way determinedly south in defiance of both wind and current. Even if you had not warned Laurelorn's defenders to be on the lookout for this invited guest, there's enough red flags that they'd still react with extreme caution to this foreign visitor. "Ahoy, it's a hoy," she calls in a deep, rich voice as she approaches the dock of Tor Lithanel you've been watching from, just a trace of accent breaking through the Reikspiel. "Nice to finally lay eyes on a watcher with enough politeness to show themself." "Baba Niedzwenka, I presume?" you ask, glancing up at the blue-on-black Erengrad pennant flying from the mast. "And likewise I presume you to be Lady Magister Mathilde Weber, the ambition behind this endeavour." She waves and a tendril of ephemeral motion grips a rope and snakes out to a bollard on the dock, weaving the rope around it in an unsettlingly serpentine motion. As the boat approaches the foaming water around its hull forms into the shape of a old man's face, who gives a bubbling, agonized moan. "Pay no attention to him," she says with an airy gesture that dunks the spirit back into the water. "He has taken too many innocent lives to fairly claim to be a victim." "How was your journey?" "As peaceful as one could hope for. The Sea of Claws is an old friend, and this river is much too tame to attack without order." She grips a rope and pulls herself to her feet with some effort, a series of clicks and pops coming from her joints. Somewhat stiffly she steps up from her boat to the wharf, and you take the opportunity to study her with your Windsight. To your surprise she seems to have no inherent magical ability of her own, or at least nothing she has used recently. What she does have is a spiderweb of ephemeral attachments sprouting off her, some connecting to the boat and others to what seems to be items concealed on her person. "So this is the Eleventh Kingdom," she says musingly, staring up at the walls of Tor Lithanel. "Where'd they get all the marble?" "Most of it was traded from the Dwarves back when they were allies. Apparently Master Runelord Thorek is discussing the possibility of resuming those shipments." "Interesting. It's quite the roster you've gathered here. You think you stand a chance of unpicking the mysteries of the past?" "I can only hope. Kislev knows more than most that the status quo cannot be sustained indefinitely." She nods. "And I will not shy away from reminding everyone present of that fact. Even the Ice Witch, if need be. Ever since they arrived, the Ice Court has jealously guarded the nexuses on behalf of their mistress. Even the Sea Elves could not pry them loose from it, not with all the bribes and threats they could muster. Do you know who they have sent?" "Ice Maiden Zlata, I understand." "A maiden?" She gives a sinister chuckle. "Oh, a mere maiden can be twisted around any number of fingers. Though only if necessary, of course." You refrain from commenting on that. "I had the impression that, erm, your kind of magic-user..." "Koldunja." "Koldunja," you repeat, thankful. 'Hag Witch' might be the literal translation of their Kislevarin name, but it does come across as rather disrespectful in Reikspiel. "That you didn't travel well, as the spirits you draw power from tend to be sessile." She smiles. "They prefer to be, but over the years I have taught many that it is also preferable to stay on my good side. Fear not, should it prove necessary to our endeavour, I will still be able to call on a wide range of my abilities." Once more you swallow your initial response, and instead add to a growing mental tally of concerns. "Glad to hear it. Allow me to guide you to the residence of the Project, where you may have your choice of quarters to claim for your own..." Once Baba Niedzwenka gets moving her joints appear to stop protesting, and before long she's striding through the streets with the self-assurance of a queen, running a thoughtful eye over the buildings and people of Tor Lithanel. "You know, none of the Sea Elves of Erengrad liked to speak of this place." "Why is that?" "Laurelorn does not recognize either claimant for the Phoenix Throne. From what I managed to winkle out of the Sea Elves, I can't say I particularly blame them. The first Caledor abandoned them, the second Caledor denied their autonomy, and Caradryel stripped them of citizenship. After all that, I could see an argument that the wrong fellow got the throne after Bel Shanaar to be quite convincing to those who've never had their shores visited by a Black Ark." "There are those in the Empire who might agree," you say carefully, making the sounds of agreement without actually agreeing. "The Druchii are very much a blight on the coastlines, but at least they've never lent military support to secessionists." "The Asur ultimately serve only themselves," she agrees. "And they have the sheer arrogance to claim otherwise with a straight face, not thinking the 'lesser races' are capable of seeing through their bold-faced lies." "Happily, it seems the Eonir have not inherited that tendency. They are aware that while they could defeat a single province, the united Empire could crush them, which has forced them to address us as equals to be negotiated with, rather than inferiors to dictate terms to." "Glad to hear it. While that's always an enjoyable lesson to teach, it would take a great deal of time and effort that would be better spent elsewhere." --- On your latest visit to Oldenlitz there was more than a single Mischief standing watch for visitors. When you arrive Cadaeth was quite prepared for your arrival, and is once more dressed in bark and leathers. As you accompany her on her rounds of the glimmering trees that are the citizens of her village, you ask her of the beings you recently fought against. "Hmm," she hums, thinking. "Do you know what a Dreaming Wood is?" "The liminal realm of a magical forest." "Mm. It has been called the soul of a forest, and the poetry of that has resisted countless attempts to correct it on technical grounds. An individual tree's soul is typically simpler and more ponderous than that of most beings of flesh and blood, but they live a very long time and can absorb a great deal of ambient magical energy over the years. Put enough trees and enough magic together for long enough and a Dreaming Wood arises, and then nature spirits begin to emerge from it. Spites first, then the Naiads and Oreads and Limniads, and finally the Dryads." "Are you speaking generally?" you ask, frowning. "Not a lot of Dryads left around the place, are there? What I described is the primordial form of the forest, undisturbed by the encroachment of fleshy beings. There are no forests I know of that still retain that status. Here in Laurelorn, the Grey Lords colonized and tamed the Dreaming Wood, binding some spirits and forming accords with others, and in modern times the distinction between Faniour Elf and Laurelorn Dryad has practically disappeared. As for other forests - well, I can only guess based on what I have heard from the outside world, but none have remained unchanged by the passage of years. The Drakwald has fallen entirely to the Beastmen, the Bogathingaz and Dukhlys to Goblins. The Schattenwald has been twisted by an eternal war against the beings that live in its depths, and many say it is as fallen as the Drakwald. The Reikwald lies dormant, the magic that once sustained it disappeared. The Grossewald has adapted to the humans that live within it, and many spirits seem to have found niches within your pantheon. The Forêt de Châlons belongs to a local Goddess, and the Forêt de Arden is a war between man and beast and Orc in the absence of the Beastman Daemon that once ruled it. "But Athel Loren? Athel Loren was the most magical forest of all, and there the Dryads gave rise to a new form of being. The most ambitious of them permanently intertwined their spirits with one carefully-chosen tree, literally rooting themselves in the forest that they emerged from, and in doing so claimed rulership over it and the Dryads who lacked the courage or strength to do the same. When our kin first came to Athel Loren three of the very first Treemen remained: Adanhu the Wise, Coeddil the Protector, and Durthu the Benevolent. During the War of Vengeance it is they that those that would become the Asrai entered into an accord with. And by the colouration of the Dryads you described, I believe they were servants of Coeddil, so I can only guess that there was some threat to Athel Loren within the Shirokij that the Dryads sought to combat." "They did seem to be hunting the local Boyar, who may be affiliated with Vampires." "Well, much of the problems of the Schattenwald can be blamed on Vampires. Perhaps they foresee some threat from them that they seek to avert." "But the Schattenwald seemed to be actively rejecting the Dryad leader. If they were there to oppose Vampires, wouldn't it have cooperated with them?" She shrugs. "I can only speak for Laurelorn, for everywhere else I can only speculate. Perhaps the Schattenwald is maddened beyond rational thought, perhaps it is opposed to Athel Loren for its own reasons, perhaps the Vampires the Dryads were opposing were in turn opposed to the Vampires within the Schattenwald. Perhaps some other combination of factors I cannot even guess." You nod, mentally adding this new information to the conversation you're going to have with Paranoth later. "Would destroying a Dryad's physical form permanently kill them?" "No, that's what makes the Treeman incarnation such a gamble, because it binds a Dryad to a single body that can perish. When a Dryad moves from a Dreaming Wood to the physical realm it borrows substance from the tree it uses as a bridge, and if they shed it or it is destroyed within the bounds of a forest the spirit can return to the Dreaming Wood. But being wrenched from a body by its destruction can grievously wound the Dryad, and it will need to return to the forest it originated from to heal." "Wouldn't that be a dangerous journey for a wounded spirit?" "Not if they can reach the Worldroots, though I don't know how far the living sections of them still extend in that part of the world." "Presumably they reach at least to Ostermark, the Warhost stirred up the locals while physically travelling through the province." "So it, and all the other Dryads that fell in battle there, would have needed to travel through a significant stretch of the hostile Schattenwald Dreaming Wood while wounded. I don't know those woods so I can only guess, but it does seem like it would be a deeply unpleasant journey." You nod. "Hopefully any survivors have learned a lesson on sticking their noses where they aren't welcome. By the way, I took the lower half of the leader Dryad, thinking that it would make a good material for enchanting - she was an Ulgu wielder, after all. Would that be correct?" "It would have only existed since the Dryad manifested so it wouldn't have the centuries or millennia of being steeped in a Wind that makes things like dragon bones so useful, but it would have been created with the conscious intent of creating wood that would be extremely amenable to the flow of their Wind. It would be better suited to fine control than raw power." There are, you reflect, two distinct facets to Cadaeth - that of the diplomat, and that of the expert. Her diplomatic guise is a bludgeon of fey coyness that undoubtedly serves her very well in Middenheim, but as superficially charming as that can be, you find you enjoy her company a lot more as she is now, dressed sensibly and expounding on a topic she knows well. You find it reminds you a fair bit of Panoramia, and you make a mental note to introduce the two when you get a chance.

Turn 37 Social - 2488 - Part 2

Your work in the northern parts of the continent keeps you away from Karak Eight Peaks for the majority of your time, but you return there fairly regularly to consult your personal library, to make decisions regarding the construction of your much larger one, and, of course, to spend time with Panoramia. Now, with the Jade Order officially a party to the Waystone Project, there's no barrier save her busy schedule keeping her from visiting you in Laurelorn, with the side-benefit of it giving her the opportunity to explore the most magical and benign forest within the Empire's borders. So with a packed lunch and a satchel full of tools and sample containers the two of you set off into the forest to see how the long habitation of the Eonir has shaped it. "A forest is a forest, isn't it?" you ask of her as the two of you make your way into the trees. She smiles at you, seeing right through your play of ignorance, but responds anyway. "In about the same way that a Karak is a mountain. At first glance it might be the same, but if you look close you start to see the small external changes that hint at how much has changed underneath. For instance, look at this." She walks over to a nearby tree with a large vine wrapped around the trunk. "A rooted scandent vine, possibly hemiparastic, possibly just a liana, there's debate about whether that's commensalist or even symbiotic. But look, the climbing pattern is unnaturally uniform. See there?" She points upwards into the canopy. "Though the trunk narrows higher up, the distance between bands remains the same." She gives the vine an experimental tug, then without hesitation she starts clambering upwards. You watch her progress until you're satisfied she's not going to slip and fall, and then use Smoke and Mirrors to appear on the branch she's heading towards. "Do you have to do the smoke every time?" she observes wryly as she pulls herself up onto the branch. "Actually, yes. The spell is actually simpler if broken into cantrips and interwoven with another piece of magic, so I use an Illusion of some smoke. It's the only spell powerful enough while also being benign and not dependent on specific circumstances." "Ooh, commensalist magic. I wonder, does that indicate an inefficiency in the base design that the interweaving manages to bypass, or is it a cunning use of harmonious design? Anyway, the reason we're up here." She looks at where the vine finishes its climb by wrapping itself around a fork in the branches, creating an almost completely flat platform. She puts a foot onto it experimentally, then fully steps onto it. "It's a firing platform," she says. "Look, there's even less branches directly below here than on the other sides of the tree, and if you look there," she points, "you can see where the climbing vine has strangled out a branch that would have obstructed the view from here, but it worked around the ones on the other sides of the tree." "So in the same way human tamed wolves into dogs, the Elves have tamed plants to do jobs for them?" "We tamed plants too, you should see the wild ancestors of the plants we farm. But that's so much easier a job, just pick the largest seed or friendliest puppy to breed more of. To create something this specific must have taken either a much deeper understanding of selective breeding, or the use of magic to completely rebuild the organism for a specific purpose." "Cadaeth did imply that the lornalim weren't entirely natural. I'd figured that she meant that each plant was carefully sculpted as it grew for a specific purpose, but if they custom-make entire species for specific jobs..." "Isn't that what their mythology says about them? That the Elves were custom-made as guardians of Ulthuan by Asuryan and Lileath?" "It does contrast with what the Teutogens and Taleutens said, that they were the Chosen of Ulric and Taal respectively. That implies a selection from a pre-existing population, rather than them being made from scratch." "Perhaps they inherited some of those techniques, and the Eonir have used them to shape the forest. A forest where no matter where you were, you could look around and find an easy climb to a concealed firing position with a great field of fire..." She looks down, and then kneels to inspect the underside of the platform. "With provisions too, judging by the fruit." "Or a convenient source of poison for their arrows." Panoramia withdraws her hand from where she'd been about to pluck one. "That would be a possibility too," she says, opening her satchel and fishing through it for gloves and a glass jar. After Panoramia finishes collecting samples and observations from the vine, the two of you move on in your meander through the sculpted forest and come across several other oddities of interest. There is a tree that she theorizes accumulates trace minerals from the soil and concentrated them in nodules along its trunk, and in the hollows left by previously-extracted nodules spites have made their nests, and some glare menacingly out and chatter litanies of improbable threats. There are dense thickets of bushes with broad fronds that would provide excellent cover to the light-footed, and the habit the fronds have of folding in on themselves and revealing stems covered in long, hooked thorns mean that anyone with too heavy a tread will find no shelter among them. And the natural-looking paths through the trees that make wandering through Laurelorn so easy are fringed with coiled roots that, with some experimentation, Panoramia is able to provoke into uncoiling and choking a stretch of the path, turning it into an uneven and treacherous surface that would slow any march to a crawl. "There's an awareness to the trees," Panoramia says thoughtfully as the two of you enjoy your lunch in an excessively picturesque grove. "Which isn't unusual in itself, trees pay more attention than most people think, but it's usually only interoceptory unless something gets their attention. These trees are watching, and they're curious." "The curiosity of a domesticated beast, or the curiosity of a confused sentry?" "Good question." She mulls it over. "I don't think they're sentries, exactly. Their thoughts are too slow to make a decision quickly enough for that to be practical. But their attention being piqued would leave a trail in the wake of anyone with good Magesight and a familiarity with them." You run your eyes over the surrounding trees. "Firing platforms and metal farms and spite nests and caltrops and watchdogs, all in one. The entire forest has been sculpted into the ideal terrain for skirmish and attrition, a hundred miles of it in every direction around Tor Lithanel and the Wishing Woods and the Rainbow Falls." "And then Nordland started peeling it away." You nod grimly. "Schlaghugel is maybe sixty miles from Tor Lithanel, and their loggers would have been following the river upstream so it could carry the logs back to the village for processing. If they bypassed the hilly terrain immediately upriver of them, they could have been logging less than forty miles from Tor Lithanel's walls." Panoramia grimaces. "That puts a new face on matters. I'd thought the matter was a match for the reputation of the Asrai, killing at the slightest provocation, over just a few felled trees and a few tiny villages on the wrong side of a river. But to lose half of their buffer zone..." You nod. "And at a pace too slow for any one Nordlander to be meaningfully responsible. It's been eight hundred years of very slow encroachment." She sighs. "What a mess." The rest of the day passes similarly, and you find yourself quite happy to follow Panoramia and listen to her expound on a topic of such interest to her, both out of personal curiosity and out of enjoying listening to her speak with such passion and delight. By the time the sun starts to dip and the two of you return to the city her satchel is bulging with specimens, which gives you a perfect opportunity to introduce her to a laboratory filled with the finest Eonir artisanry that money can buy. Perhaps it hasn't been the most conventionally romantic day, but you wouldn't change anything about it. - I normally prefer longer updates, but the weather's been playing up here and I'll feel better knowing there's no chance of losing this if my computer ends up floating out to sea.

The Marriage of Prince Kazrik and Princess Edda, Part 1

Spoiler: Unfinished business [*] Kazrik and Edda [*] Paranoth [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else In the Karaz Ankor, the marriage of a prince and a princess is not quite as uncommon now as it was before Kazador's many children were unleashed. But a marriage between the heir apparent of an Old Hold and a very well-respected princess of a Young Hold would be some of the biggest news of the decade even before their involvement in the story of Karak Eight Peaks is factored in. Compounding that even further is that between the two of them they have had dealings with just about every Dwarven King and Elector Count in the Old World and made generally positive impressions across the board in the process. As the guest list starts to swell and Hammerers and Greatswords across the continent begin to plan a trip to its southern edge, Karak Eight Peaks and Barak Varr begin to turn their eyes to security precautions to avoid a repeat of the attack on the Okral. Death Pass swarms with Undumgi, Blood River with Winter Wolves, Skull River with Rangers, and Black Fire Pass with patrols from Averland and Karak Angazhar. The Karaz Ankor is determined for this to be a joyous celebration, tinged as little as possible with the violence and tragedy that is too often the theme of Dwarven history. Zhufbar finds itself barraged with enquiries as to the state of the Black Waters canal, and though they must report that they are not yet ready to allow passage between the Reik and Black Gulf basins, their Steward takes the opportunity to personalize a reply to each inquiry to inform exactly how much time the project would save on a trip between their location and Karak Eight Peaks once it is completed, guaranteeing it as a common topic at the wedding among those that had to travel via Black Fire Pass. Also taking advantage of the opportunity is Barak Varr's Slotchokri, the Riverine Shipwrights Guild, who have the lead ship of the newly-invented Waterfall-class passenger monitors run ragged taking passengers from Black Fire Pass to Ulrikadrin, showing off its speed and comfort to the many prominent individuals taking the trip. There are two significant days in Dwarven courtship: the Barazdeg, Day of Promise, and the Harazdeg, Day of Joining. The typical Barazdeg consists of a day of festivities which culminates in pre-approved suitors presenting gifts to the maiden and her Clan for them to evaluate their worthiness, and the length of time between it and the Harazdeg can tell you a lot about the circumstances of the marriage. In this case, the Harazdeg takes place the day after the Barazdeg, which is a strong indication that the groom has already been selected and there is no need for the engaged couple to get to know each other. That or the bride's clan is utterly desperate for money or allies and needs to seal the agreement as hastily as possible, but that there's only one suitor that will be allowed to present gifts at this Barazdeg makes the circumstances of this marriage clear to all, even those who have not heard the gossip of the Prince and Princess getting a headstart on their nuptial duties and ending up with a strict and undelayable biological deadline for their marriage. There was a time millennia ago when this would be a scandal, but one of the many changes the Time of Woes made to Dwarven society is that it has become entirely willing to turn a blind eye to even the most heavily pregnant bride. As the many guests gather in Karag Rhyn on the Barazdeg, you find a conveniently shadowed niche from which to monitor the many guests as they enter the Grimbrow Clan Hall. There's someone from just about every Dwarfhold there is, of course, including innumerable representatives from the many Valley Kings of the Vaults. Just about every Elector Count has sent at least a representative and a few are here in person, most of them traveling with an Elder from the local Imperial Dwarf population. Ostland is the only exception, likely because they're too far from any populated mountains to have any involvement in the affairs of the Karaz Ankor. Kislev has sent a diplomat who has travelled the considerable distance with the nervous-looking delegation from Karak Vlag, the unnatural-seeming leanness of whom is even more pronounced when there are so many other Dwarves to compare against. The Royarch of Bretonnia has sent a representative, as have the Dukes of Carcassonne, Parravon, Montfort, and Gisoreux, and their ceremonial armour stands out less in a Dwarven crowd than in most human ones. Most of the Tilean city-states have sent someone, as once it become known that Tobaro and Miragliano would be sending someone nobody wanted to be left out. Nobody from Estalia, which isn't really surprising as they're too far west to get involved with the affairs of any Dwarfhold but Barak Varr. And at first you didn't think anyone had been sent from Marienburg, but then you spot a Dwarf in the red and blue of House Fooger, the only Dwarven family on Marienburg's Directorate. But states aren't the only ones who have sent someone, and you spot among the growing crowd someone that would otherwise be rather difficult to nail down a meeting with and make a beeline towards them as they sip thoughtfully from a flagon of ale. "Magister Patriarch," you greet him. "Have you received the report I sent to your Order?" He smiles at you. "Lady Magister, a very brief summary only. The staff at the College always have so very much they wish to report, and the kestrel they use only has so much carrying capacity. They relayed that the issue was an Athel Loren warhost, which was defeated in some manner." "Broadly correct. It was a Dryad warweald aligned with Coeddil." He coughs into his flagon and only just manages to keep from propelling some of it across the crowd. "Drycha?" "Who?" He blinks at you as he wipes his mouth. "Was it led by an Ulgu Branchwraith?" "Yes, but I didn't get her name before I cut her in half." He stares at you for a while, and sighs when he realizes you're serious. "I think we need more kestrels. Can you tell me the full report?" You give him the full story, from your investigations in Gryphon's Wood to your dealings with Kislev to the showdown in the Shirokij. Paranoth nods along, asking the occasional question to clarify matters. "Whether the Schattenwald is itself evil or merely full of it is a matter of much debate," he says as you wrap up, "but it's a distinction lost on most. It is the nature of a society built on farming to be opposed to the forest, so there's no benefit of the doubt to be found for the Schattenwald. But those evils, whether they be native or invading, are largely focused in Ostland, so Ostermark likes to pretend they don't have to worry about it. Do you know much about the Boyar that Drycha was hunting?" "Boyar Kalashinivik of Resvynhaf. The Praag branch of that family was aligned with the Tzarina Kattarin the Bloody and were purged, but the Resvynhaf branch was spared. The Tsarevich and the Ice Witches are going to be investigating him to decide whether that was a mistake." "It probably was if Drycha's after him. Either he has something that he shouldn't, or he has blood in him that he shouldn't. Royal blood is always potent, and magic doesn't care if it's human or vampire, Kislevite or Nehekharan." "You think Drycha has her own agenda, rather than operating for Athel Loren as a whole?" He gives you a strange look. "Of course, the same agenda she's always had." "And what is that?" He looks baffled. "How do you know Coeddil's name, but not- oh, did Laurelorn tell you about him?" You nod. "It makes sense that they would be a bit behind on things. Of its Treeman Elders, Athel Loren only has Durthu left, as Adanhu was killed and Coeddil corrupted by the endless battles against Morghur." He frowns. "Well, apparently endless. Are you sure it was him you saw up at Karag Dum?" "I am, and so are the very many people that were also credited with my paper on the subject." "Mm. By all accounts he's impossible to mistake for anything else. I do wish you'd been able to get some hard answers about what that was all about." You manage to keep from bristling. "So do I, but my duty was to the Expedition, rather than my curiosity." He nods. "Of course. No criticism intended. What was I getting at?" "Coeddil and Drycha?" "That's right. Coeddil attempted regicide, and was imprisoned somewhere within Athel Loren. Drycha has been scouring the continent for magical power ever since, in what we assume is an effort to free him. Many shrines and temples in Bretonnia and the Empire have been looted by her forces over the centuries, and the Amber Brotherhood have fended off several attacks by her on the Amber Hills. She fails more than she succeeds, sometimes by the efforts of defenders, sometimes due to being pursued by Athel Loren loyalists. But just like the one that corrupted her master, her nature grants her the privilege of coming back no matter how many times she is struck down, and every success takes her closer to her eventual goal." "Well, that's worrying." He shrugs. "If Drycha succeeds, it would probably be bad for a lot of people in the short term, but it might also bring Athel Loren to the negotiating table with their neighbours. They'd need help, and we want them to stop going on rampages every spring. In the trail of every conflagration is new growth that was impossible before." He smiles, and then looks into his now-empty flagon. "Best of luck to you and Grunfeld," he says as he moves away, making a beeline towards the many barrels forming a formidable wall on one side of the hall. You return your gaze to the crowd, and spot one part of it has already noticed that you're now unentangled and is coming towards you with as much determination as Paranoth was to the ale. "Mathilde, darling," Empress Heidi says as she swoops upon you, giving you a brief courtly hug. "It's always such a pleasure. Can we talk somewhere private? Very private, for preference?" As the attendants catch up and begin to buzz with unasked-for comments on this, you spot one of the many Princes whose name begins with 'Kaz' and after racking your mind for the rest of it you get permission from them to borrow their Clan Hall, which would be currently empty but still heavily guarded. You lead the way for the Empress, discarding her courtiers in the hall and her Greatswords outside the Clan Hall to mingle with the Hammerers. "Such an abrupt departure is the sort of thing that starts rumours," you observe as the doors swing shut and you run your Magesight over the room, confirming it's as empty as it seems. She waves a hand dismissively. "Those rumours exist for every Empress, doubly so for the attractive ones. At least with you there's no way for it to cast doubt on Mandred's legitimacy." With a mental shrug you accept that. You've never been one to care too much about gossip, and there's so much worse that can be and often is said about any given Wizard. "What is it you wanted to talk about?" "This," she says, producing a familiar wooden horse from nowhere in particular with a gentle spark of Ranaldian energy. "Has it stopped working?" you ask, taking it from her and frowning down at it. The Ulgu within does look... degraded? No, more eroded, gradually shifted from constant pressure that shouldn't exist. "Quite the opposite, and that's what worries me." You neigh at it, and it gives a rather vigorous whinny in response, far louder and more lively than the one you had weaved into it years ago. "Ah," you say faintly. "Mandred's interested in knights these days, and he'd have one of his dolls atop that and having it defeat all kinds of enemies. He used to complain that it wasn't 'bold' enough. Then it started getting louder and longer." "And I take it there haven't been any visits from Grey Order enchanters." She shakes her head. "Didn't think so. This is entirely instinctive work. It bothered him, and the Ulgu in it responded to his will. Just a little bit, but over time that's enough for such a simple change. Has he been drawing in any energy?" "No, thankfully. I'd have brought him with me if he was." "Then I think you already know what this means." "I know. I'm not here to talk to my Grey Wizard friend, I'm here to talk to Mandred's Godmother. You're..." She looks at you, considering. "Deceiver and Protector by nature, right?" You consider that. "I suppose so. Night Prowler situationally, Gambler when I need to and when I want to get His attention." "Right. You're sort of balanced, you have a relationship with all of Him. But my relationship is entirely with the Gambler. Even when I deceive, I'm... well, look at me. The stakes don't get higher than this, do they? That's the Ranald I know. I take risks, the boldest and most stylish ones I can find, and He's right there alongside me and together we ride out the aftermath and pick the pockets of those who couldn't. And I think that's why Mandred is the way he is now. Just as he shaped that horse, I shaped him." "Or it could be purely inherited. Just as you are a magic-user, so is he. Or environmental, we get a lot of Apprentices out of Altdorf and some think it's something to do with the city itself, not just because the locals are familiar with us or because we're there to spot them." Or it could be you. There's only two children you've been involved in the lives of, and now both of them have turned out to have the potential to be Wizards. What are the odds that that's sheer coincidence? She considers that, chewing on her lip. "Well, even if that's true, it doesn't change that I need your input. I've been thinking about this ever since I noticed it, and it's not fretting about it I've been doing. I've been looking forward to it. I should be worried for my son, and don't get me wrong, I am, but more than that I'm looking forward to what might happen. And I'll roll those dice again and again until they all come up ones and I go to meet the father-in-law of our mutual friend, but for Mandred? For my son?" She grimaces. "Part of me keeps saying that he's not a chip I should be anteing, but another part of me keeps saying that he's already in the game and this just gives him one more tool to play it with. He's got the wrong father to live a safe life no matter what I do, so maybe I should see to it that he's as well-armed as possible. And even if it comes out in the worst way and it ruins any chance of him being Emperor, he's still going to be the next Grand Prince of Reikland, and we've had a hundred Emperors and thousands of Elector Counts but never a Wizard Elector, and that could do so much. The Empire would still have Marienburg if we trusted Wizards more, and Mandred could fix that. You're his godmother, you're a Wizard, and you have a more well-rounded relationship with our God than I do. And you're the only one, apart from Him, that I can talk to about this. Please, give me your advice." You take a deep breath and do your best to think. Your first instinct is that Mandred being a Wizard wouldn't work because that would almost certainly make it impossible for him to be Emperor, so he should be fitted with magic dampeners now so that he never develops the ability to call on the Winds at all. Having been discovered so early, it would be possible to completely stamp out the capability in him before he even realizes it's there, which would mean he wouldn't be tempted to remove the dampeners and dabble with the ability. But the idea of taking someone who has the chance to see and touch the beauty of the Winds and smothering that gift in them is one you would feel great horror at recommending. You would rather lose your eyes and hands than your capacity for magic, so how could you justify crippling your godchild? And besides that, it would be far from the end of the world if someone else became Emperor. Grand Duke Feuerbach of Talabecland is the most likely candidate now, but he's also a decade older than Luitpold and unlikely to outlive him. Given time for the younger Elector Counts to build a legend for themselves... Emperor Boris of Middenland, the man who made friendship with Laurelorn possible? Emperor Wolfram of Ostermark, who is responsible for the push for Dwarven infrastructure that is on the verge of revolutionizing travel in the Old World? Empress Roswita of Stirland, even? Who's to say that any of these would be worse than Emperor Mandred II? The boy is seven, it's far too early to have any idea of how good an Emperor he could be. And Heidi's not wrong about what a Wizard Elector Count could accomplish. Every Wizard lives with the knowledge that their right to exist is based solely on the Articles of Imperial Magic, and if that is withdrawn - as all Emperors have the power to do, as one Emperor has done - then the life of every Wizard is forfeit. It has been less than a lifetime since the Colleges suffered a fifteen-year siege as a result of their tenuous legal protections being withdrawn. But Grand Prince Mandred of Reikland, a Magister of the Colleges? He could lay down legal protections that could prevent the Colleges from ever having to depend on walls and enchantments to survive again. Or there's a third path, the same path as his mother walks. He could be taught to wield the divine magic of Ranald, and cement even further the influence that your God will have over the potential future Emperor. But this might be the riskiest option of all, as while the Empress might be able to pass unnoticed as a worshipper of Ranald, a potential future Emperor himself would be under far greater scrutiny, possibly that of Sigmar Himself. Mandred as an anointed of Ranald would need to inherit every scrap of cunning from his mother to have any hope of passing unnoticed. And being outed as a worshipper of Ranald - more than that, as someone so favoured by Ranald as to be granted the power to wield miracles - would be at least as bad as being a Wizard for his chances of becoming Emperor, and could even damage his claim to inheriting the title of Grand Prince of Reikland. You turn the horse over in your hands as you try to reach a decision. [ ] Nullify Mandred should add a few subtle magic dampeners to the regalia of a Prince to smother his potential to use magic before it has a chance to bloom, and you and Heidi will have to learn to live with the crippling of a child on your consciences. [ ] Wizard When Mandred starts to interact with ambient Winds, he should be trained as a Wizard. For the son of the Emperor, all sorts of allowances could be made to keep the disruption to his life as minimal as possible. [ ] Ranald Mandred should be fully inducted into the Cult of Ranald and taught to wield His power, and taught to keep anyone else from finding out he has the capacity to do so. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Heidi will take Mathilde's input on this matter very seriously, but is not guaranteed to follow her advice. - "Oh come on, first Eike, now Mandred?" Yeah, I know. I'm still struggling to believe it myself. The dice, it seems, have no obligation to plausibility. - The wedding will continue next update, which will bring chances to mingle with some other guests.

The Marriage of Prince Kazrik and Princess Edda, Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Wizard Tally "When someone is fitted with suppressors, if it's their decision then it's their decision, and if it's something their parents have forced on them then they can still remove them and come to the Colleges and be accepted. But this is a decision that's normally being made when someone has first channelled and shaped magic. As young as Mandred is, as undeveloped as his magical ability is, fitting him with suppressors would likely completely smother any ability he will ever have to see and touch magic. And I couldn't recommend that for anyone. If I was given a choice between keeping my eyes and keeping my magic I wouldn't even hesitate to choose magic. "And in all honesty, if he never becomes Emperor, so what? Plenty of people never become Emperor. I'm sure Mandred will grow up to be a wonderful leader, but the Empire would do just fine under Todbringer or Hertwig or Van Hal. Grand Prince Mandred will still have plenty of power and responsibility, and you're right that as a Wizard he could do so much good for the Colleges and for Wizards. In the minds of the masses he could do more simply by existing than people like me could do in a century of good deeds, and he could lay down legal protections that will stop us from being a single document away from being besieged by the Witch Hunters once more. "You're looking at this as a gamble and then beating yourself up for seeing it as a gamble, but the decisions that led to this have already been made and it's too late to start second-guessing them. The only way to walk away from this hand is to abandon your son. If you don't, then it's your duty as his mother to accept who he is and help him grow into a good person." Heidi nods, slightly at first and then with more confidence. "You're right. If he's a Wizard, he's a Wizard. I can handle that, and so can Luitpold." "And from a Ranaldian perspective, aren't you the one that says you don't go for the big elaborate plan? If you were the grand plan type you never would have been in Nachthafen for me to meet you, right?" She considers that and nods. "So pivot the caper. A Grand Prince can do almost as much and with much less oversight. Remember the Black College business, when everything Luitpold tried to do was shaped by having to tiptoe around the Elector Counts? Maybe Mandred could get more done for Ranald if he was the one getting tiptoed around. Help the Dealer spread up the Reik, maybe." "That's a point, if he didn't have the Grand Theogonist breathing down his neck he'd have a lot more freedom to act..." Heidi's face creases in thought. "Especially if the new Emperor tries to shift the location of the Grand Conclave, and has to do some favour-trading to make it happen since it's been in Altdorf for so long..." "See? There's always opportunities for mischief and profit, even when you're doing the right thing." She smiles at you. "The Cult would be a lot more accepted if everyone went about worshipping Him the way you do." She looks around the empty Hall while you try to decide how to respond to that. "We should probably get back to the festivities before the gossip reaches a fever pitch." You nod. "Don't want to miss the Barazdeg itself." "What's up with that? From how it was explained it seems like some sort of wife auction?" "Well, the thing about that is..." As the two of you head back to the Grimbrow Clan Hall, you explain the finer points of Dwarven culture and the unspoken understandings and behind-the-scenes negotiations that underpin the ancient rituals. When the two of you arrive she's quickly swallowed back up by her swarm of attendants and you position yourself once more to scan the crowd. There's not enough time left before the presentation to have any serious conversations, but once the presentation is made the family will withdraw to consider the gifts, and though everyone knows the result is a foregone conclusion they need to spend enough time in consideration to pay proper respect to whatever Kazrik's gift might be. When the time comes, there are no ritual words to be spoken as the work is supposed to encompass all that needs saying about the suitor's wealth and skill. Kazrik steps forward in silence and places his offering upon the table: an abacus of steel and gemstones that he places upright, and with a finger he nudges up one of the jewels. At his touch all of the stones begin to softly glow with an inner light, and the jewel he moved stays resolutely in place, ignoring the call of gravity. A wave of appreciative nods spreads through the audience as they take in this gift, and you find yourself joining them. The jewels quite obviously demonstrate wealth, and the display of Runesmithing may not be up to the standards of Kragg or Thorek but is impressive for someone who had to work around their duties as heir of Karak Azul and diplomat of Karak Eight Peaks. But more than that, the gift itself is a thoughtful one that Edda would be able to get a lot of use out of, since Klinkarhun numerals are incredibly ungainly to do any sort of calculations with. It shows an understanding and appreciation of Edda's skills and knowledge, and that will undoubtedly be extremely useful for the future King of Karak Azul to have in his Queen. Edda and her kinfolk take the abacus and retire to give the proper show of consideration, and King Kazador walks up to his son and claps him on the shoulder in pride. Normally this period of a Barazdeg is as much a spectacle as the presentation of gifts, but without any other suitors to potentially clash with Kazrik the crowd returns to the buzz of conversation as all sorts of affairs of state are discussed by the gathered personages. It would be gauche to actually sign any treaties or make any deals at an occasion like this, but it's places like this that the unofficial groundwork is laid for future, more formal arrangements, and you consider the conversations you wish to have while this many important people are in one place. Every Elector Count except Ostland and every Dwarven King of the Karaz Ankor is either here in person or has sent a delegate, as have the Tzar of Kislev, the Royarch of Bretonnia, the Dukes of Carcassonne, Parravon, Montfort, and Gisoreux, and the many rulers of Tilean city-states. There are also an assortment of lesser figures representing innumerable minor powers from throughout the Old World. Just about any dialogue you might wish to have with the institutions of the Old World can be had here. Write in any topics you wish to discuss with, questions you wish to ask of, or messages you wish to send to, the states, organizations, institutions, and cults of the Old World. No formal agreements will be reached here, so use this as an opportunity to send messages, sound people out, lay foundations for further talks, fish for headpats, or satisfy any curiosities you may have. Mathilde will pursue as many topics as she can before the Barazdeg comes to a close, prioritizing based on which get the most votes. Example votes: [-] The Rangers Guild about teaching Dwarven War Yodelling to humans [-] Stirland about whether Wurtbad needs a Dwarven War Yodelling academy [-] The Cult of Myrmidia about whether Dwarven War Yodelling would fall under Myrmidia's authority - There will be a six hour moratorium. - For the sake of my sanity, please refrain from asking about whether any specific individual or institution is present. Whatever conversation Mathilde wants to have, you can assume there will be someone here who is at least familiar enough with it to give Mathilde some sort of answer. If there's a conversation you need to have with a specific individual and can't be had with anyone else, this probably isn't the place to have it.

The Marriage of Prince Kazrik and Princess Edda, Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Talk to a Priest that was present during the Emergency Conclave and ask what's up with being declared a "Dwarf". [*] Carcassonne/Bretonnia to inquire about their willingness to join the waystone project [*] House Fooger, for their view on the canal project and Marienburg situation [*] Cult of Verena about the possibility of entering into an agreement with our library [*] Middenland about how the Eonir-Ulric partnership is going [*] Stirland about the state of the war and who has become Markgräfin [*] Okri: The new Loremaster of Karak Eight Peaks is Okri Drakkisson of Clan Bronzebeard, formerly of Karak Norn. Meet your replacement and gauge what kind of person he is. [*] Follow up on the newfound partnership between the Light Order and the Cult of Gazul Tally Gunnars sighs when you ask him about the Conclave's declaration of you as having a Dwarven soul, and guides you to a part of the crowd where the only people close enough to eavesdrop on a hushed conversation are those who don't speak Khazalid. "It's plausible on two levels," he says. "On one level, there's the level that most Dwarves understand - that upon death a soul is either directed towards the Underearth to join the Ancestors by the proper rites, or it fails to get those rites and returns to the Aethyr, eventually returning as another Dwarf and having another chance to end up where it should. Given that framework, it's plausible that a soul that was once a Dwarf and would have been returning to be one once more could be redirected into a human body. But I'm sure you spot the part that'll make most Dwarves uncomfortable if you pick at it." "There's a big leap between the departing and returning." "Right. The other death Gods all claim to have an answer, but Gazul can only speak for those that go to the Underearth. If some or all souls are those that have walked the world before returning for another go, there's no metaphysical maker's mark that anyone's been able to find that proves they keep coming back the same species. So yes, maybe you were a Dwarf before, and maybe your Ranald is responsible for you being a human now. But it's just as plausible that any other human was a Dwarf before. Maybe any bird or goat or Goblin was. That's the part that no Dwarf wants to think about too hard - that someone not given the proper rites might come back as something other than Dwarven. We like to think of ourselves as a species apart from the world, and the world does a lot to reinforce that, but one way in which we're exactly the same is that the origin of our souls is as unknown to us as it is to you." "I can see why Dwarves wouldn't be comfortable with that. But the announcement the conclave gave was a lot more than just saying it was plausible. What takes it from 'it's technically possible' to them being sure enough to announce it to the world?" "More than the need to assuage the guilt and shame of a Karaz Ankor that had given up on Karak Vlag? Well, I speculate, but if they were able to communicate with your Ranald and put the question to Him, would He have given them a straight answer?" You consider that. "Ah." --- It took some waiting for her conversation with Soizic to finish, but you manage to ensnare the Damsel that had come with the Bretonnian delegates in conversation. "We are, in the abstract, not uninterested," she says with a coy smile once you broach the subject of the Waystone Project. "And had you accepted our invitation to pursue your research in Carcassone, we would already be working hand in hand with you. But you chose otherwise, and while our hearts can recover from being snubbed so, those you did choose are ones with whom entangling ourselves could be problematic - both in regards to their distant kinship with our own, sometimes-troublesome neighbours, and in regards to baser matters of conflict and trade." "As far as I am aware, there is no conflict between Athel Loren and Laurelorn-" "As far as you are aware," she echoes. "As far as I am aware, too. But we would have to become much further aware for that to be a safe endeavour. And the effort of becoming so much further aware is effort that could be spent elsewhere - such as, for example, the Iron Orcs of the Irrana Mountains. But if you were to come to us with something more tangible than dreams, then perhaps we might be tempted." She gives you a parting smile and a little wave before she disappears back into the crowd. --- "So now you'll be able to row from Black Water to the Aver, so what?" Arkat Fooger, head of House Fooger and the only Dwarf on Marienburg's ruling council, says to you. "Marienburg isn't built on a single accident of geography. Idiots think Marienburg has a stranglehold on the Empire, but what difference does it really make that all sea trade goes through us? Bretonnian trade can as easily go through Helmgart as through us, Tilean trade already has the River of Echoes, the Karaz Ankor is half built on the Empire's borders and the rest could go through Black Fire Pass. If some idiot has bet their shirt on something like supplying Arabyan coffee to Averheim then they're sunk, but if that's the foundation of a family then they're already underwater. No, what this means is that for a few years a bunch of amateurs and dilettantes are going to try to undercut Marienburg by going through Barak Varr, and apart from a handful of goods from Estalia and Araby they'll find that Marienburg has more going for it than the Reik and most of the routes will be back through us in ten years." "Not everyone from Marienburg seems to agree." "Pfah, it's because they're manlings. Right and proper they put their elders in charge, but their elders have maybe a decade of living left in them, and they go whenever they go instead of when they're at peace with going. They feel Morr's breath on their neck, and it makes them as hasty as a beardling in a brothel. Things going back to normal ten years from now might as well be never for them, because it means that they'll be less rich for the rest of their lives. So they fret and moan and rattle their sabres until they do something stupid enough to get their hands slapped and remember they've got a lot more to lose than to gain." "Stupid things such as...?" He snorts. "I take it you're getting at that business with the mine on the river? I'd be happy to throw the de Roelefs under the boat since they're the ones that stand to lose the most from the canals, but truth of the matter is I haven't a clue. All I know is that if anyone had come to me with an idea like that, I'd have buried them myself and saved you the trouble. Things like this, the big problem is that you aren't limited to the few who might actually benefit, there's also all the people who are stupid enough to think they might benefit." --- "The Cult of Verena does not have the rigid hierarchy of, say, the Cult of Shallya, or even that of your own Orders," says the small man with large, round glasses and a sword on his waist that almost scrapes the ground. "We of the Order of Mysteries are one of the few formal organizations within the Cult, organized as we are under the High Priest of Altdorf, and there are also the Templars of the Order of the Everlasting Light and the Order of the Sword and Scale. In contrast, the other 'Orders' within the Cult are better thought of as schools or philosophies. Each courthouse and library is subject only to law, truth, and Verena, and I'm sure you can imagine how opinions may differ in what these all have to say. It is with regret that I say that short of divine intervention, you have no option but to approach each library as its own entity." "Can you give me any advice for doing so? He considers that. "There are two distinct groups of people within the Cult of Verena who seek dominion over libraries: the Lorekeepers who see knowledge as sacrament and wish to spread it, and the Scrollbearers who see knowledge as power and wish to hoard it. Identify which you are dealing with as soon as possible, as you will need two entirely separate kinds of bait to ensnare each. The Lorekeepers would value an institution who can guarantee the safety and spread of knowledge entrusted to it, and if you wish to present yourself as positively as possible to such people, a chapter of the Knights of the Scroll to guard your library would be the most effective way of doing so. The Scrollbearers, however, do not have a better nature that can be enticed thusly, and so you must resort to a quid pro quo approach if you find yourself in need of what only they can offer." --- "My Lord," you say to the teenager who stands a foot taller than you already and doesn't seem done with growing. "Lady Magister," says Baron Heinrich, illegitimate son to Grand Duke Boris Todbringer of Middenheim. "I had expected that we would meet before long, but thought it would be closer to home. I forgot that you have a foot in both worlds of the Elder Races, how do you manage it?" "It's easier than you might think. Even for those as long-lived as they, their enmity is ancient history, and the world has no shortage of foes that have given them fresher scars." "An interesting perspective. Many of those I've spoken to about Dwarves seem to characterize them in terms of opposition to the Elves." "I suspect they would be most familiar with Imperial Dwarves, whose ancestors built kingdoms in the Reik Basin and lost them during the War. But it is the Elves I wished to speak to you of today, My Lord, and how Middenland's partnership with them is progressing." "Damned slow it seems to me, but at what I'm told is a breakneck pace for Elves. One of their Houses has taken responsibility for the Ulrican faith among the Eonir and is building a temple to Him in their city, and the Graf couldn't be happier. This whole matter was an unexpected windfall after an already advantageous beginning - the Beastlord who he was pursuing into that swamp is one that he had faced before and taken the eye of, and ever since it seemed determined to avenge itself upon the citizens of Middenland. The timely intervention of the Eonir helped bring the matter to a close, where otherwise it would have just been one more bloody chapter in an already too-long saga." "So no problems at all, then?" "Oh, Nordland is still furious, and they keep nudging the Nordlander Ulricans into mumbling something condemning about it all, but honestly they got their hands caught in the cookie jar and they need to take their lumps and be thankful they're not getting what Drakwald got. The only real problem is where to go from here. They want to start trading and so do we, but they refuse to build a road through their swamp - can't blame them, considering how useful it was against the Beastmen - and the only other alternatives will piss off Nordland or Marienburg or both. So perhaps we just have to be patient and let things simmer down before we escalate things even further." "Glad to hear it. Give my best regards to the Graf." "And mine to the Queen." --- "Gustav," you say as you approach the former Outrider and current Marshal of Stirland, clasping his arm in yours. The two of you didn't work together for long enough to quite call each other close friends in comparison to the relationships you'd built with Wilhelmina and Markus, but the two of you did fight alongside each other against the horrors of Sylvania. "How fares Stirland?" "Well enough that I'm getting nervous," he replies. "One of the remaining Vampires now decorates the Grand Countess' mantlepiece, and the other has fled into the swamp and is being pursued by what seems like half the Battle Wizards in the Empire. Sylvania is once more ruled by Stirland in truth rather than just on paper." "That is welcome news. What's to become of the administration thereof?" "There's talk of establishing a Markgraf, but no firm details yet. Rumour has it that Baron Anton was offered it and was sensible enough to turn it down. It looks like the Black Guard are going to get the County of Tempelhof and Kasmir has been talking a lot about a local religious coalition getting control of the Barony of Mikalsdorf, but Waldenhof and Nachthafen are still untaken. The problem with Sylvania is anyone competent enough to stand a chance has much better offers from literally everywhere else. But we have to fill those seats or the Vampires'll do it for us." You nod and commiserate with him for a while before moving on. --- You have to have Okri Drakkisson of Clan Bronzebeard pointed out to you, though once he is you're easily able to identify him due to some sort of multi-lensed loupe strapped to his forehead. "Loremaster Okri?" "Aye?" he says as he turns. "Ah, you must be my predecessor. I hear you've left mighty large shoes to fill." "More of a clear slate to build on what you wish." "Aye, and build I will. That Gotri does his best but his heart is in the sky, he's more familiar with a swashplate than an inclined plane. The way of the future is in Dwarf-portable weaponry, and Zhufbar's Drakegun is just the start. I had a few ideas to start with, but having seen some of the reading material you managed to nab from the former inhabitants of here, I've got much more than a few now. Been working with the manling engineers here, including that Zharrzhufokri of yours, and have been exchanging letters with the Gorlzhufokral to hammer out a few ideas. We refound Karak Eight Peaks Ironbreakers, give 'em something that holds real punch but can still be carried around, and pile 'em into those flying machines of Gotri's, and we'll be able to deliver a proper kicking to anywhere that needs it on a moment's notice." You allow him to talk your ear half off about said ideas, including an entirely mechanical equivalent of the Ratling Gun, an explosive charge launcher based on Adela's design but not reliant on being carried by a Bright Wizard, and refinements to be made to the current Drakegun designs to extend their range and increase the damage inflicted upon those caught on the wrong end of them, before you thank him for his time and escape. He's clearly ambitious and seems to know what he's talking about, but you can't help but feel he might be biting off more than he can chew. You're intimately familiar with the inside of a Ratling Gun and the many insane yet inspired ways it exploits the nature of warpstone to function. Is there really any chance of a machine so portable as to be carried to be able to replicate its functioning? Surely not. --- "Oh, Gunnars," you say as you find the Cleric of Gazul once more. "Yes?" "Did anything come of those introductions I made between you and the Light Order?" "We sent some notes over about some tricky buggers they're dealing with, and they sent some notes over about tricky buggers we're dealing with, and we established an agreement to do it some more if we encounter more tricky buggers." "That's it?" He shrugs. "If they wanted to come up to the mountains and chase demons we wouldn't say no, and if we wanted to go down to the lowlands to chase demons they wouldn't say no either. But we both have our own problems, and we're going to prioritizing dealing with our own problems before we even think about going to chase someone else's problems." You suppose that makes sense, though you'd hoped for something a bit more ambitious to come from the introduction you made. --- After the announcement is made that Clan Grimbrow has decided that Prince Kazrik's gift is the most worthy and that he is to wed Princess Edda, the room shakes with cheers and quickly becomes awash with freshly-broached barrels. After thousands of years of isolation the brewers of Karak Azul are finally able to explore the full range of their ancestral recipes once more, and the first batches have been deemed too amateurish to be worth ageing but just good enough to be drunk and have been donated to this celebration to be disposed of, a task the crowd gets to with vigour. The opportunities to have meaningful and informative conversations quickly evaporate after that point, and you let yourself become part of the atmosphere of general camaraderie rather than trying to pursue any final scraps of dialogue, and the rest of the day becomes something of a blur. To Dwarves, once the decision is made and agreed upon, the union becomes an accepted fact and the Harazdeg ceremony itself is merely a formality. It's also only open to the family of the spouses, you suspect because the ceremony includes taking both spouses aside and having them confirm in private that they're entering into the union of their own free will, and if the Priestesses of Valaya have to announce the wedding is off and then beat any objectors with hammers until they stop objecting, that's a lot easier without bystanders around to complicate matters. But that doesn't stop a number of people who attended yesterday's celebrations from loitering in the halls near the Temple of Valaya, some of them with leftover barrels to keep them company in their loitering, forming an entirely unofficial celebration almost as lively as yesterday's, though significantly more difficult to navigate. If the happy couple emerges as anything but, the crowd will quickly dissipate and pretend to have never been a crowd in the first place. But when it's Kazrik and Edda that emerge smiling and hand-in-hand, they find themselves having to make their way through a cheering gauntlet of back-slapping and ribald advice to progress towards the Grimbrow Clan Hall, where quarters suitable for royalty have been prepared for them. You know for a fact they've had quite a head-start on their nuptial duties already, but that's no reason for them not to hone their respective edges even further, and you clap them on their backs as they pass and yell something to that effect. The next morning you go through your incoming correspondence and find reports from the EIC confirming what you heard during the Barazdeg celebrations: the long siege of the remaining holdouts has concluded with one Vampire killed and its remains under guard and the other currently being pursued through the countryside, and with extremely light casualties sustained by the Army of Stirland. Some are grumbling that this proves the sieges were unnecessary, but most agree that it's a result of the sieges serving their exact purpose. Exactly whose problem Eastern Stirland will be is still up in the air, but with it no longer an active warzone there's hope that some semblance of peace might settle upon Stirland. Wilhelmina has taken the opportunity to enter into agreements with the Black Guard of Morr and something calling itself the 'Council of Manhorak' to handle trade into and out of the new provinces, and presumably the second anyone accepts rule over the remaining areas they'll find Wilhelmina looming behind them with a contract and a quill. At this point there's no disputing that the EIC has complete dominance over trade and transportation within Stirland. Library Purchases: [ ] [LIBRARY] Colleges of Magic Name four magical, non-divine topics to acquire all available Empire books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Barak Varr booksellers Name three public topics to acquire all available Empire and Dwarven books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Library of Mournings Name two non-magical topics to hire Cityborn scribes to copy all available Laurelorn books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Back-fill. Instead of seeking books on specific topics, fill in some of the sections of your existing library where you have some of the available books from the Empire and the Dwarves on a subject, but not all. Will acquire more books total than other options, but cannot be directed. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a two hour moratorium.

Turn 38 - 2488.5 - Built Upon a Shadow

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [LIBRARY] Back-fill. [*] [PURCHASE] The Lady: Extensive Bretonnian, Shallya: Extensive Bretonnian, The Kingdom Of Bretonnia: Extensive Bretonnian, Trade: Extensive Eonir, A dwarven axe for Baba Brzeginias/Gerdouen (30gc) [*] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [*] [DWARF] No purchase. Tally Spoiler: Backfill results Anatomy - +3 D Chemistry - +2 I / +1 D Geography - +3 I Toxins +3 D Arthropods +3 D Dragons +1 D Rodents and Mustelids +1 I The Dark Lands +2 D Dragon Isles +1 D The Old World +2 I / +2 D Empire +3 D Kislev +1 D Ulthuan +2 I Greenskins +3 D Ogre Kingdoms +2 I Undead +2 D Agriculture +2 I Architecture +2 I Grungni +2 D Valaya +2 D Grimnir +2 D Before you return to Laurelorn, you commission the making of a Dwarven axe to human dimensions, and arrange for it to be delivered upon completion to Baba Brzeginias of the village of Gerdouen. Her aid was a great help in dealing with the Gryphon Wood issue and bringing Kislev in to the Waystone Project, and though she likely did it in order to rid her forest of a dangerous interloper, that is no reason for ingratitude, especially if there is a possibility of needing to call on the knowledge and capabilities of the Hedgewise again in the future. While your Gyrocarriage is refuelling at Barak Varr, you drop in on your bookseller contacts there and, on top of giving them a bag of Kislevite gold and telling them to turn it into Bretonnian books, you give them a list of the topics you have a less than exhaustive coverage of in your library and the titles you currently have in them and tell them that Karak Eight Peaks will pick up the bill for every new addition to that section, and will require only a modest discount for volume. From the thoughtful look in their eyes you're fairly sure they realize that this will represent quite an opportunity to clear out accumulated unsold inventory at almost full price, and you've no doubt that there'll be junior members of their Clan delving through every inch of their warehouses before long for materials they can offload into your growing library. While this may not be the most directed means of filling out your library, the sheer volume it should result in will be something to behold. Turning your mind to the future as you board the Gyrocarriage once more, you're very aware that it has been two years since you began pursuing the Waystone Project, and though you're quite proud of having managed to bring in quite a diverse group of contributors, on paper you have nothing to show for it. And that begins to matter now that you have brought in four human contributors who do not have centuries of lifespan to wait, and who have responsibilities and ambitions of their own tugging at them. It will be very difficult to justify any further delays to the beginning of the Waystone Project, as any further recruitment you might make could very easily be countered by others withdrawing after years of no visible progress being made. You have five action points (AP) you can apply without engaging in overwork. For every two AP spent across all members of WEB-MAT, including recruiting new members, you can spend one 'free' additional AP with any member of WEB-MAT. WEB-MAT actions are performed by Mathilde alongside that person when possible, such as studying something alongside that person, cowriting a paper together, one teaching the other, both of them learning something new, et cetera. Current overwork status: [ ] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. WEB-MAT: Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which two papers or one book will be written. WEB-MAT: Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Lord Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, Light Wizard [ ] EGRIMM: Attempt a Windherder enchantment with Egrimm (specify what) [ ] EGRIMM: Learning: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] EGRIMM: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Other [ ] WEB-MAT: Hunt an apparition with a member of WEB-MAT (specify who and which) (NEW) [ ] WEB-MAT: Attempt to recruit someone to WEB-MAT (specify who) [ ] WEB-MAT: Hire someone as a full-time Gyrocopter pilot (optional: specify who) The Waystone Project, Recruitment [ ] Attempt to bring an Order into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a non-Order magical tradition into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a human Cult into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (specify which) The Waystone Project, Research [ ] Lay the foundations: work with the current members of WEB-MAT and the Waystone Project to build a single unified framework for understanding the Waystones. In theory, the more members there currently are, the more complete this framework will be. Will unlock further investigations. Can be repeated if desired, but will not unlock anything new after the first time, it will just make a new framework incorporating any new recruits. Lovely Laurelorn [ ] Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Explore one of the Wards of Laurelorn (specify which: Storm, Rain, Frost) Self-Improvement: [ ] Receive training: specify who and what. (acquaintances may train you for free, or you can hire someone with money or favours) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Attempt to gain control of one of your Arcane Marks (specify which) [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. Aethyric Vitae (18 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item: specify what and how (current skill level allows for Fiendishly Complex spells and lower; you may use Windherder to attempt to enchant something with spells from different Winds) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to codify Rite of Way so that others can learn it. [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff (specify for whom) (optional: specify from what) Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in current affairs: specify what and how. Current examples: Eastern Stirland pacification, Marienburg affair, Black Waters project Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting or ingratiating yourself with someone else: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 200 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Eastern Stirland EIC Handler: The Hochlander The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in your fief. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Improve and expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (optional: specify how) [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. [ ] EIC: Investigate what trade goods the Eonir might be willing to import from the Empire. Kron-Azril-Ungol Status: Built, unstaffed, not yet open to the general public. The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] Decide who your library staff will consist of, and go about recruiting them. (NEW) [ ] Go about recruiting an army of scribes so you can start copying entire libraries of material. (NEW) [ ] The many legends about the amount of books contained within and under Castle Drakenhof still haunt you. Organize an expedition to mine the ruins for books. (NEW) [ ] Seek the publishing contacts to start acquiring large amounts of books from a nearby realm (specify which: Bretonnia, Kislev, Tilea/Estalia, Araby) Gives wide and easy access within a language, but is subject to local restrictions and is a less efficient use of the Library's acquisition budget than other methods. [ ] Seek an exchange arrangement with another Library or a Karak's archives to be able to make copies of their corpus (specify which, eg: Great Library of Marienburg, Great Library of Altdorf, Ancient Library of Carroburg, Karaz-a-Karak Archives, Karak Vlag Archives) Difficulty will depend on the size, prestige, and disposition of the library in question, and the relative impressiveness of Kron-Azril-Ungol. [ ] Seek an agreement with a Cult to have access to their libraries (specify which, eg: Verenans, Myrmidians, Sigmarites) Difficulty will vary heavily depending on the Cult in question, but can allow access to rare tomes and esoteric subjects. [ ] Set up a no-questions-asked bounty system for books within the Cult of Ranald Results will be unreliable and depending on what is sought may result in blowback, but this may allow you to acquire books that would otherwise be entirely inaccessible. Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. [ ] The Father Ranald's daughters, and Their followers, will recognize you as being worthy of trust and faith. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Books and rubbings from an Asur explorer of Lustria and the Southlands Ghyran Nut Kurgan Shrine to Mannsleib Kurgan enchanted weapons Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Observations on the Windfall north of the Dark Lands (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghur (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Hysh (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ulgu (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Aqshy(FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Ghyran (FADED) Windsoak Mushrooms - Azyr (FADED) Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (FADED) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. Windsoak Mushrooms (missing: Chamon, Shyish) The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a eighteen hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - I've got a feeling I said 'remind me of X if I forget it' a lot more than I've added things. If so and you remember what X was, please speak up. - This is about as loud a hint you're going to get that if you delay the Waystone Project any further, there may be consequences.

Turn 38 Results - 2488.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan Disregard WEBMAT, Acquire AP -[*] One Overwork Action -[*] COIN: The Father -[*] WEB-MAT: Hire someone as a full-time Gyrocopter pilot (Adela) -[*] Lay the foundations: work with the current members of WEB-MAT and the Waystone Project to build a single unified framework for understanding the Waystones. -[*] Attempt to bring a non-Order magical tradition into the Waystone Project (Nordlander Haléthan Hedgewise) -[*] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (Tindomiel) -[*] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. -[*] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. -[*] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. -[*] KAU: Decide who your library staff will consist of, and go about recruiting them. -[*] SERENITY: Write a book: Windsoak Mushrooms (1/2) Tally From a certain way of looking at it, there are two broad ways to be a Wizard in society. The first, as practiced by most of the Colleges in Altdorf, is to try to filter and dampen oneself so as to broadcast a palatable and unthreatening image in the hopes that the people around you will become comfortable with your presence among them. And then there is the example set by the likes of the Dark Lady of Nuln, Magister Matriarch Elspeth von Draken, who lets their true nature shine through in open challenge to the masses, and if they don't like it they see if they can work up the courage to do something about it. House Tindomiel, it seems, believes in the latter approach. The entrance hall to House Tindomiel is shrouded in shadows, its only source of light being the burning eyes of the enormous statue that dominates the hall. In Her six arms is the traditional accoutrement of the Goddess of Conjurations - heart, scorpion, arrow, staff, dagger, and phial. At Her feet is a golden bowl filled with coins in what you presume to be tribute to the Hydra Queen. And though Her six arms and burning eyes do draw attention, Her proudly unclothed state makes it difficult to entirely miss that She has a form that is twin to that of the Goddess of Seduction. To most eyes the hall would be filled with darkness interspersed with flickering, bewildering shadows, but between your Magesight and your attunement to Ulgu a room so thick with shadows and heavy with magic is as clear as if it was open to the midday sun. This makes it easy to notice that in contrast to the crowds of House Miriel and the attendants to receive them, the only response to your arrival is a ripple of energies as one of the many spirits lurking in the murk of the room disappears deeper into the building. A watcher, you surmise, and you consider the statue of Hekarti as you wait. Her traditional armaments are rather overdone in a lot of the literature - a phial of orphan's tears? really? - but the books on Her you had copied from the Library of Mournings provide another explanation for them, saying that they are a set of basic shapes that got elaborated on over time. The infamous phial began as as the rune of Azyr turned upright, the serrated dagger the rune of Ulgu given a few extra points, the scorpion's tail comes from the flourish at the end of the rune of Shyish, and so on. This leaves two Winds unrepresented, and the statue before you uses one of the two usual solutions for this: burning eyes for Aqshy and an obvious lack of Chamon that a supplicant is invited to correct with the contents of their purse. The other common fix for statues has a brazier at Her feet and a crown upon her brow. You're not entirely sure you're convinced by this, but it's better than nothing. A flicker of energies draws your attention to one of the room's many entrances, as a door swings open and in floats a figure atop a platform floating on a cloud of Azyr - an older-looking Elf with a lined face sitting cross-legged on a bed of pillows, steering himself with small hand gestures as he approaches. You wonder to yourself whether the vehicle is an affectation or a requirement - such devices are not unknown in the Empire to grant mobility to those without the use of their legs, though even the most elaborate of those are entirely mechanical contraptions powered by hand cranks. "Lady Magister Weber," he says in a carefully neutral voice. "I am Councillor Isthien of Tindomiel. What brings you to our domain?" "The same goal that brought me to Tor Lithanel in the first place, Councillor. I wish to bring together experts from every corner of the Old World to examine the workings of the Waystones, in order to better protect, maintain, and hopefully even grow the network that keeps Chaos at bay. It is my hope that House Tindomiel will assist with this endeavour." "And why would House Tindomiel wish to do so?" "It was my understanding that House Tindomiel was in favour of better relations with the Empire." "It is, and it is also aware of how most citizens of the Empire feel about wielders of magic. That is a relationship that will be best cultivated by the likes of Kadoh and House Ellemakil." You consider that, and nod. "Status, then," you say, changing tacks. "You'd be an equal among the Project, on the same level as the Grey Lords and the Ward of Frost. And you'd be the only Major House to which this offer was extended." "Thus far." "Thus far," you concede. "But even if others are brought in later, you'd be the only one in from the start." "If we are to contribute, it will be on our terms. Should this endeavour succeed in the creation of new Waystones, it will be House Tindomiel that erects them, to a design of our choosing." "What sort of design?" "One that honours our patroness." Your mind goes over the range of possible responses of Waystones going up honouring the Hydra Queen. "If we have as much success as I hope, then such an agreement could significantly bottleneck the entire project." He nods, conceding the point. "Right of first refusal, then. If we aren't able to supply the required expertise, then you can turn to whoever else may be available." "And if the Project does not manage to ever reach the point of constructing entirely new Waystones?" He shrugs. "If that is the case, I will consider the Project to have failed, and will not lower my House by fighting for scraps." You give that some thought. Depending on the exact design, new Waystones cropping up with the form of the Goddess of Conjurations might cause trouble in the future. But that would be a problem in some hypothetical future, in exchange for assistance in the very tangible here and now. You gather your thoughts to hash out the exact details of what exact promises the Project might be making to House Tindomiel. Do you reach an agreement with House Tindomiel and bring them into the Waystone Project? [ ] [HOUSE] Yes [ ] [HOUSE] No If Yes wins the above vote, what form will the agreement take? This vote will be in plan format, and the numbers in parenthesis must add up to zero or greater to be a valid vote. Multiple representatives can be a part of a single plan if desired, but only one each from Scope and Form can be. Scope - House Tindomiel will have right of first refusal for providing the Wind-based aspects of constructing Waystones within: [ ] [SCOPE] Laurelorn (0) [ ] [SCOPE] Northern Provinces (+1) Nordland, Middenland, Ostland, and the Wasteland. [ ] [SCOPE] The Empire (+2) [ ] [SCOPE] Empire, Bretonnia, and Kislev (+3) [ ] [SCOPE] The Old World (+4) Representative - the member of House Tindomiel that will join the Waystone Project as a contributor: [ ] [REP] Head (-3) Councillor Isthien, Head of House Tindomiel, will join the Waystone Project himself. [ ] [REP] Enchanter (-2) House Tindomiel's foremost enchanter will join the Waystone Project. [ ] [REP] Magical Theorist (-2) House Tindomiel's foremost expert on Wind-based magical theory will join the Waystone Project. [ ] [REP] Priest (-1) A well-versed Priestess of Hekarti will join the Waystone Project. [ ] [REP] Heir (-1) Councillor Isthien's heir, who is well-educated and respected but unspecialized and comparatively young, will join the Waystone Project. Waystone Form - whether House Tindomiel will dedicate the Waystones they built to Hekarti: [ ] [FORM] Shrines (+1) Tindomiel-built Waystones will double as shrines to Hekarti, and will be easily recognizable as such. [ ] [FORM] Dedication (0) Tindomiel-built Waystones will have carvings that can only be recognized as dedications to Hekarti by someone well-versed in Elven Gods. [ ] [FORM] Discreet (-1) Tindomiel-built Waystones will have dedication to an accepted and legal God of the Old World Pantheon. [ ] [FORM] Secular (-2) Tindomiel-built Waystones will have no dedication to Hekarti whatsoever. --- Though technically controlled by the Grand Baron of Nordland, the Barony of Hüven is almost entirely neglected and he may not even remember that he owns it. In years past his predecessors parcelled out the villages of Varrel and Seuchenshof to the Cults of Ulric and Shallya respectively and most of the attached land with it, leaving only a single rump village isolated deep within the Forest of Shadows and near the theoretical border with Ostland. If you had nothing to go off but a map and the gazetteer it would likely be the first place you'd start looking for the Nordlander Hedgewise, so you take it with some satisfaction when the Provost points you in that direction. You normally try to avoid flying in via Gyrocarriage to an unsuspecting corner of the Empire, but in this case it might, counterintuitively, be the least disruptive way to visit Hüven. Nordland is currently rather sensitive to anything Laurelorn-related and Varrel is small enough that you passing through it could be the biggest news they have all year. The villagers proved to be alert enough to spot the Gyrocarriage approaching in enough time to muster a band that could have seen off most airborne predators, but the armed band that was summoned by a lookout seem more curious than wary as you land as far from the buildings as you can and give them plenty of time to see that it's a human clambering out of a Dwarven contraption. One only slightly awkward conversation with the villagers later they point you towards their carpenter, who you guess to be Kurtis Krammovitch's contact here, and has apparently spread word to expect you. The man himself proves to be an older, wiry man with greying blond hair cropped short and a pattern of scars that resemble tree roots encircling his right forearm. He introduces himself as Aksel and brings you in to his cottage, the main room of which is dominated by a workbench and a row of pegs on the wall from which hang a dizzying array of woodworking tools. "It's good times for my lot," he says to you as you settle down. "Most of the Ostland Blessed are dead, which is unfortunate, but it means that their families are coming out of the east for protection, joining with us. Old families with a lot of old secrets and a lot of proven wisdom. And the business in the west has people a lot more willing to face the dangers of the Forest, and having a lot more respect for those that protect them from those dangers. Word is you've a part in that." You consider how to answer that for a moment. "I wasn't involved with the founding of the relationship between Laurelorn and Middenland, but I am trying to build that into a relationship between Laurelorn and the Empire as a whole." "Mm. Shame what happened to those on the wrong side of the river, but we've enough problems without borrowing some from the westerners, and I can respect the Elves for doing what they must for their forest. So what is it you want our help for?" "What do you know of Waystones?" He shrugs. "Only from myths and legends. When Sigmar slew Morath of Mourkain, he charged the local Hedgewise with watching over the nexuses that the necromancer had fed upon, and granted us a fortress in the Middle Mountains for our own. But after he was declared a God, his Cult declared a crusade to claw back all authority he had ever given in life so they could keep it for themselves. When the Everchosen Cormac Bloodaxe attacked Ostland and left us weakened in his wake, the Cult of Sigmar assaulted the bastion that Sigmar had granted us and took it for themselves, and it's been changing hands ever since. At various times Ostland, Hochland, and Reikland have all claimed it, and all have in turn lost it. Similarly the nexuses within the Forest itself have been lost to us, and are now known only as the Tower of Melkhior and the Blood Fane. If the Kislevites hadn't cut off the flow of energy from Norvard when they rebuilt it into Erengrad, the Forest would have been lost to Chaos generations ago." That's rather more information than you expected, and you have to fight the impulse to start tugging on a half-dozen intriguing threads at once. "If you regained control of one of those tomorrow, could you restore it?" He takes a moment to think that over. "I could try, and pray that our recollections of what we once knew have remained true." You nod. "That's exactly why I want your help. The Empire is dotted with groups that have fragments of information about the Waystones and the Nexuses. Individually we're just doing our best to hold back the tide, and every time someone falters it's a loss that we don't know how to recover from. I'm hoping that we can at the very least better learn how to repair and maintain the Waystones we have, and perhaps even begin to replace the ones that have been lost." He's quiet for quite a time. "I've heard said," he eventually says, "that many thought it was the beginning of the end when the Magisters were formed. But it seems to me that me and mine have seen more good than bad out of you and yours. And I've heard of you, and the Kupfers and Krammovitches have vouched for you. If there is a chance that you can find success, then we are bound by ancient oaths to assist you in this." As you begin to talk to Aksel of the specifics, you think to yourself that if the Nordland Hedgewise were always this trusting, they likely would have been wiped out some time in the past two thousand years. Between that and the relatively unbothered reception you received when you arrived, you suspect you might have answered half the mystery that Ranald presented you with when you were gifted the fifth face of your Coin. Will Aksel of Hüven join the Waystone Project, and if so, in what manner will he do so? [ ] [HEDGEWISE] Openly Aksel of Hüven will join the Waystone Project as a representative from the Schattenwald Hedgewise. [ ] [HEDGEWISE] Discreetly Aksel will join the Waystone Project as a representative from the Cult of Halétha. [ ] [HEDGEWISE] Secretly Aksel will join the Waystone Project in the guise of a Grey Order Perpetual who will claim expertise in the inherited lore of the Grey Order. [ ] [HEDGEWISE] No Decide against the Hedgewise joining the Waystone Project. - There will be a six hour moratorium. - This update took longer than I'd like to come out. The past couple of weeks have been hectic. - The Tindomiel agreement will be in plan format, but the Hedgewise vote is separate. You can vote 'no' on Tindomiels and still vote for the form an agreement will take if 'yes' wins. - Example of a valid vote: [ ] [HOUSE] Yes/No [ ] Plan Example -[*] [SCOPE] Option (~) -[*] [REP] Option (~) -[*] [FORM] Option (~) [ ] [HEDGEWISE] Option

Turn 38 Results - 2488.5 - Part 2 - Day One of the Waystone Project

Spoiler: Voting results [*][HOUSE] Yes [*] Plan how many people can actually read elf anyways? -[*] [SCOPE] The Empire (+2) -[*] [REP] Magical Theorist (-2) -[*] [FORM] Dedication (0) [*] [HEDGEWISE] Discreetly Tally The deal you strike with House Tindomiel is straightforward: they will have first refusal on the construction of new Waystones throughout the Empire, upon which they will be allowed to carve dedications to their patron Goddess, and in exchange they will contribute their foremost magical theorist to the Waystone Project. This may cause you trouble in the future, but you welcome a future where a problem you're dealing with is aesthetic criticism of the new Waystones being built throughout the Empire, and House Tindomiel will help you reach that future. The magical theorist in question proves to be Senior Lecturer Emeritus Sarvoi of the Library of Mournings, who you've heard the name of a time or two before as his talks are quite popular among the artists who romanticize the Forestborn. From what you've heard, he speaks of magic as a lover to be wooed rather than an impersonal force to be studied, and the mental image you've constructed of him clashes rather harshly with the reality you're introduced to, which proves to be a short (for an Elf) and bookish man of indeterminate but advanced age, whose pristine white silks trimmed with gold can't hide the general impression you get: that at any given time there's a dozen stamped from the same mold as him in the halls of the University of Altdorf, the type that would give a lecture to a half dozen with the same enthusiasm as he would a thousand if they seemed like they were paying attention. Aksel, meanwhile, has rather cheekily adopted the title of Lector of the Cult of Halétha, which would be the Cult of Sigmar's equivalent rank to his approximate position within the Hedgewise. He says he'll be able to make his own way to the edge of Laurelorn, and you have a word to Cadaeth for her to keep an eye out for him, and with the other Wizards of the project to give them the impression that the Cult of Halétha is to the Grey Order as the Druids are to the Jades. It might even be true. With that sorted, the biggest potential problems you foresee at the table are, perhaps predictably, its two oldest members: Hatalath and Thorek. While the Eonir have been largely broken of the arrogance of Ulthuan by centuries of having to treat individual provinces of the Empire as their geopolitical equals, the Grey Lords predate that reality and have been insulated from it by the security of their liminal realm, and you expect you'll have to do some work to shake Hatalath into doing more than smiling indulgently down at you all and throwing out the occasional cryptic comment. Thorek, on the other hand, seems more willing to engage, but very severely restricted in how he can do so. The Cult of Thungni has very strong opinions on the importance of keeping their secrets, and it will take a fair bit of tact and sensitivity to extract much of use from him. --- At the head of a table of seven humans, three Elves and a Dwarf, you take a deep breath. "Caledor Dragontamer created the Great Vortex," you say, "and his successors built the network of Waystones across the world to drain away the magic that threatened to drown the world." There are nods of familiarity at that, and you move down to the next entry of your notes. "When the High King met with the Elgi led by Prince Malekith, he recognized both the virtues and vices of their kind. When they began to cobble together crude energy networks from the discarded refuse of the Old Ones, he instructed those that had learned from his brother Thungni to teach them a better way, and the Waystones erected in that partnership made possible that which the Elgi alone could only have dreamed." Thorek smiles at that. "When the Daemons walked and the Children of the Cradle were encircled, the Green Man first came to the Earth Mother and told Her of what was to come. In Her wisdom did She see what must be done, and in Her mercy did She make us, the Belthani, the instruments of correction. We built the Ogham Circles that halted the devastation, and we will guard them for Her." Magister Tocther nods firmly, ignoring thoughtful looks from Egrimm and Elrisse. "Tahoth Trisheros is a master architect who based reality on sacred geometry. The perfection of this geometry is found in the Great Pyramids, where the formless winds are given noble purpose." Elrisse is giving you a suspicious look now, probably because of how badly you had to mangle the translation of that scrap to fit the message you're going for. "In the time when those who brought the One had fallen and the birth-blood of the Green of Two first rained upon the world, the Four shackled the Eight and unleashed their endless armies upon the world to tear down those across the blue plains. We despaired that our Gods had turned from us. The Khans gathered together with their Shamans to set right the balance of the world. The first of the kurgans was built there, to be forever guarded by the Khans buried beneath it. Now once more do the Eight fly free and the Four ply us with tribute to see their will done." This one was a lot of pictographic guesswork, but neither Niedzwenka or Zlata seem upset with your creativity with the words of their ancestors. "Are we noticing a pattern? No matter where we look, everyone's stories paint them as the protagonists of the Waystone saga. And while this is historiographically predictable, it's given considerable weight by the fact that I can point on a map to something very much like a Waystone made by each of these peoples. The Waystone Network as it exists today was the result of Elves and Dwarves and men all working, if not together, then at least towards the same end - making sure that the world we live in remains one we can live in. But that knowledge has been scattered by time and war - the War of the Ancients shattered the accords between Asur and Dawi, the Sundering destroyed the Library of Caledor, the Time of Woes many ancient Karaks, the Belthani were driven into the deepest forests by the arrival of the ancestors of Sigmar, the Nehekharans were made into what they are now by the machinations of Nagash, and the Scythians split into the Kurgans and Gospodar. "Some might see this as reason to despair, because the gulf between our modern capabilities and the wonders of the distant past is very well-documented. But we're not talking about a holy artefact crafted by a God, or a one-off masterwork of a long-dead genius, or a unique confluence of unlikely circumstances. These things were mass-produced and erected across four continents. However inspired the development of them must have been, the result was something that was implemented, managed, and maintained by the ordinary. "The best of today may not be the equal of the best of the Golden Age, but I damn well think we can measure up to their Max Mustermanns and Chuj Gowies, their Okri Okrissons and Thananludwigs." You'll never admit if part of you was hoping for a standing ovation, but the firm nods from all present is enough to go forward with, so you press on. The first matter is a rather dull one of terminology, as there are speakers of four native tongues present at this table: Reikspiel, Khazalid, Eltharin, and Gospodarinyi. But though the roots of these languages are spread across three continents, you find very little variation in the magical terminology. In almost all languages Ulgu is Ulgu, which is theorized either linguistically as all known magical languages sharing descent from either Anoqeyån or Dark Tongue, or more prosaically as those being the syllables that resonate most effectively with the Wind itself. Even Khazalid has not proven entirely immune to this, the oft-used participle Gor is suspiciously close in sound and meaning to Ghur, and you know from previous work with Runesmiths that the other names are known to them. From there you move on to basic fundamentals of the nature of the Winds, and here too there is general agreement, save for a brief detour into a debate about the relationship between stone and Hysh. It does make a certain amount of sense, you reflect, that there's general agreement so far. The only people here who touch the Winds themselves are those who descend from the traditions of Ulthuan, everyone else knows them only at arm's length. Perhaps if you had brought in a Kurgan Shaman or a Cathayan Alchemist, someone who dealt directly with a Wind from an entirely foreign magical tradition, you'd have more trouble. But for now, you take the win and call a break for lunch. --- "This," you say as you use Ulgu to draw in the air a wireframe representation of your object of study at Fort Brachsenbrücke, "is what I believe to be a typical representation of the most common form of Waystone in the lowlands of the Old World, erected by the combined efforts of Ulthuan and the Karaz Ankor. A square frustrum topped by a square pyramid at about the height of a tall man or an average Elf. On each face of the frustrum is a Rune used in Eltharin to mean Waystone, though I find it notable that this Rune does not fit the style of any form of Eltharin I've ever seen. It almost seems as though it would be a better fit for the clean angles of Klinkarhun." You turn a questioning look towards the Elves at the table. "The Rune has entered Eltharin unchanged from Anoqeyån," Lecturer Sarvoi says. "Its purpose, and its presence on every Waystone, has rendered it immune to stylistic drift." "It is older than Anoqeyån," Hatalath says with a smile. "It is part of the script of the Old Ones." "The cunning beings in silver ships," you observe. Hatalath's smile fades and he gives you a long, thoughtful look. "Yes. Them." "The same Rune can be found in High Nehekharan to mean 'obelisk'," Lady Magister Elrisse notes. "It is the rune 'ogham' in Belthani script, usually translated as something like 'standing stone'," Magister Tochter follows. You turn a questioning look to Zlata and Baba Niedzwenka, who remain silent, and then to Thorek. "It is known to Runesmiths," he concedes, "from before the time of Bel Shanaar and Snorri Whitebeard." You nod. "It is said in some writings that the first Waystones, the first 'generation', if you will, were great stones that dotted Ulthuan since before the time of the Elves, which were rearranged in service of the Great Vortex. Would Elven lore agree with this?" Nods from Hatalath and Sarvoi. "And would the same Runes be found on those stones?" "Some," Hatalath says. "So we have an even older component in a very old work," you say, sketching the Rune onto the floating image of the Waystone. "But is it a loanword, a mere label, or is it an active mechanism in the workings of the Waystone? It is on each face of the Waystone, on the part of it that absorbs the ambient Winds. As we all know, stone is an excellent insulator of magic, but here it acts as a conduit for it." You glance towards Thorek, who looks pensive. "It is a known aspect of enchantment that the metaphysical material properties of a substance can be altered with the application of certain metaphysically resonant Runes, though this is, of course, entirely different to the art of Runesmithing and its entirely separate alphabet." "Part of the Dwarven contribution to the Waystones," Thorek finally chimes in, "was the application of certain techniques of Runesmithing while carving those Runes, which enhanced the effect it had upon the stone." He offers no more than that, and for now you make no attempt to extract more. "The capstone, too, is likely of interest here, as it seems to be made of the same material the Runes are inlaid in. Historically there's been a fair bit of study into this by human scholars, but most of that study was into attempts to extract gold from it." You exchange a rueful smile with Cadaeth. "The only known source of it is, of course, to extract it from a Waystone, so possession of it has been a capital offence since the time of Sigmar." You give a glance to Aksel, who nods. "Apart from the common epithet of 'Waystone Gold', it is also known by a great many names in different places and languages, including Hepatizon in the Empire, Aurichalcum in Tilea, Kavzarian Bronze in Estalia, Shakudo in Nippon, Panchaloha in Ind, and Hesmenkem in Nehekhara." You give a look to Elrisse at that last one. "It is theorized that the pyramidions of Nehekhara may be made of the same substance, though that would be a carefully-kept secret of the Mortuary Cult and, of course, rather fraught to investigate further," she says. "Definitely something to investigate further, and hopefully we can do so without having to sacrifice a Waystone. I'll secure dispensation for handling it from the Supreme Patriarch before pursuing the matter in detail. Are there similar laws against its possession in Laurelorn?" "Yes," say Cadaeth and Sarvoi, while Hatalath shrugs. "I'll speak to the Queen as well, then. Next," you start to draw the base of the Waystone, "is the foundation, usually partially or entirely buried, which is in the familiar shape known as the Wheel of Magic or the Star of Chaos, depending who you ask. I've read it's called the 'Gate of Cosmic Order' in Ind, and the 'Elemental Compass' in Cathay. That last one is of particular interest, as like a compass, the points of the Waystone's foundations are aligned with the cardinal and ordinal directions. I've also noticed that some links between Waystone Nexuses are in exact east-west or north-south lines." "Energy flows along the cardinal directions are easiest to maintain," Cadaeth says. "And ordinal ones, to a lesser extent." You nod, then frown as you leaf through your notes. Of course you didn't think to bring a map of Laurelorn, but you suspect... "The Tower of Se-Athil," you say, and Cadaeth nods, while most of the others exchange confused looks. Tor Lithanel is directly southeast of the Tower of Se-Athil, you're now sure of it. And you're pretty sure it's directly west of Salzenmund, but you don't say that out loud. You try to recall the other directions... Fort Solace in Westerland? But that was only recently built, wasn't it? "In any case, where the pillar of the Waystone absorbs magic, the foundation stores it. Eight points, eight Winds." "You suspect," Hatalath half-says, half-asks. "No, I don't. It's quite clear for those with the senses to see." And with a week to spend focusing on it. Hatalath is giving you another thoughtful look now, which you take as a good sign. "When the points have at least two Winds in them, they drop them into the leyline running below them and they make their merry way along it to a nexus, and from there, eventually, to Ulthuan. I'm not entirely sure why it needs two-" "Why not?" asks Sarvoi. "Ah. This is a human thing, isn't it? I mean, I suppose it makes sense why it wouldn't occur to you." He gestures to you. "The shadow and the smoke rather suit you, but I suppose the equivalents for Dhar would be rather disastrous for humans, wouldn't they? So you'd never even touch it." "What do you mean?" you ask patiently. "Why push or pull when there's something at hand that will do it for you? Dhar wants to return from whence it came, and it pulls on the other Winds. If you add one other Wind it'll just get sucked into the Dhar which is counterproductive if you want to make use of that Wind elsewhere, but if you have at least two you can set them up in a stable diametric orbit, as they repel each other exactly as much as the Dhar attracts them." "Ah. I see what you mean, thank you." He smiles and nods, and thankfully stops talking there before he goes on to what you already suspect to be the next part: if there isn't ambient Dhar to absorb and use, the Waystones could easily make some. Which would make the entire Waystone network that keeps the continent alive a sorcery that utilises the wicked powers of Dark Magic, and the study of it an Abominable Act. And from there the Articles are all heretic, traitor, sword and fire immediately. You put the finishing touches on the wireframe drawing of the Waystone as you make a mental note to have a meeting with the other Wizards later. "And finally, we have the leyline itself, a network from nexus to nexus. I haven't fully mapped it, but from my experience the main trunk in the Empire is Marienburg to Altdorf, from Altdorf to Talabheim and Nuln, and from Talabheim to Gross Selon. Which used to connect to Mordheim," winces from the Imperials present, "and to Kislev City." You turn a questioning eye to Baba Niedzwenka and Zlata. "On my last visit to Kislev, I did notice that the flow from Kislev City goes north to Praag." "It is Ice Witch business," Zlata says apologetically. "They took the leylines of the Elves and turned it into their own vortex," Niedzwenka says with a snort. "Around and around, Erengrad to Kislev City to Praag to Castle Alexandronov and back to Erengrad again, spinning it from Winds to Ice for the Widow's Witches to use against Kislev's enemies. Didn't the Elves howl and screech when they finally returned to Norvard and found their precious stones serving human masters!" Zlata looks aghast, and everyone else looks somewhere between shocked and impressed. "I... see," you say faintly, trying to keep your thoughts from being entirely consumed by wild plans to do something similar within the Empire. "That answers one question I had." And raises a great many more. "On the other end, from Marienburg it flows, I presume, to Couronne-" "Via Fort Solace," Cadaeth says. "It is difficult for leylines to be made to flow under mountains." "Difficult for Elves," Thorek mutters. You'd thought so. "Isn't Fort Solace relatively new?" "It used to be via a lighthouse on the other side of that sea," Sarvoi says, "but it was destroyed in the Great War." "Ulthuan helped build a replacement that had an Old One monolith as its spine," Cadaeth says, "built exactly north of Marienburg and exactly west of Tor Lithanel." "They can't have too many of those monoliths left," Hatalath observes. "But if Almshaven was the single point of failure for the entirety of the Empire and Kislev, it would have needed replacing. Why didn't the Empire ever hear of this? Marienburg wasn't independent then, not yet." "But they would have been planning it," Egrimm observes. "And building stronger ties with their patron." "Their patron whose Wizards fought against the Empire at Grootscher Marsh," Elrisse notes grimly. "I really don't like the idea of Marienburg being able to hold half the continent hostage," you say faintly. "Are there any other links to the west?" "Athel Yenlui," Hatalath says. "Where's that?" He thinks for a while. "Reikland somewhere, I think." "If leylines don't like to go under mountains, it would have to be going via Helmgart or Ubersreik. Something to investigate further, I think. Anywhere else?" "Karak Norn," Thorek says reluctantly. "Via Nuln?" you ask. "No," he says shortly. You consider further, recalling ancient maps of the pre-War of Vengeance Old World. "Kazad Thar?" Thorek's beard twitches as his lips thin. For him to be so touchy about it, this can't be ancient business. What would Dwarves be touchy about in southern Wissenland? Oh. Bugman's Brewery. No wonder they made such good beer. "On the other side," you say, "it would have to go through Athel Loren. Who are... not particularly cooperative these days, so let's put that as a last resort. Okay, from Couronne it would go to L'Anguille, and from there-" "Straight west," Hatalath says. "Seas are like mountains, if you're going to cross them you make it as easy as possible." "I see... wait, no I don't. Straight west of L'Anguille is nothing but ocean until Naggaroth." Hatalath blinks. "I must be thinking of somewhere else, then," he says, and rather evasively, it seems to you. You give him a long look. "If not from L'Anguille, then from where to Ulthuan?" "Los Cabos," Baba Niedzwenka says firmly. "Only a few places you can get Elven goods in the Old World, and one of them is Los Cabos. Bilbali and Magritta make sense, but the only thing significant about Los Cabos is it's right on the southwestern tip of Estalia." "And from there, straight west," Hatalath says. "To Cothique. That's what I was thinking of." You give Hatalath another long look, and he pretends not to notice. "How do you get from L'Anguille to Estalia? Surely not via Mousillon." Tochter closes her eyes. "To Gisoreux? Then to... Parravon, and under Athel Loren to Quenelles, then to Brionne?" "I'm really not liking how many times I'm hearing that the survival of the Old World might go through Athel bloody Loren." You don't see any disagreement from those present. "Something to investigate later. For now, let's talk about tributaries. Each nexus is connected to a spiderweb of tens or hundreds of Waystones, and each Waystone is in turn fed by tributaries, which are only sometimes smaller versions of the same design. There are oghams," you nod to Tochter, "there are lornalim," to Cadaeth, "there are kurgans, and there are probably all sorts of other things. What makes being a tributary so easy that a tree can do it?" You consider your phrasing. "A regular tree, that is, not one that's walking around and talking and trying to kidnap Boyars." Egrimm gestures, and a white line appears alongside your wireframe. "What makes this spell able to be converted into all the Winds? Smaller amounts of magic are easier to tame." Cadaeth nods in agreement. "So because small enough amounts of Winds have the same nature, their job is eight times easier than that of the main Waystones? Okay, that makes sense. But that also means they should be eight times easier for us to replicate." You nod to Cadaeth. "Or that is, to replicate in a way that doesn't require us to put a node of precious metal under each one. And finally, and Thorek, stop me if I'm overstepping here, but it's time to talk about other networks." Thorek looks pained, but stays quiet. "The Karaz Ankor has one. Laurelorn has one. Kislev, we just learned, has one. Athel Loren, I deeply suspect, has one. We won't ask anyone to give up the secrets of what they're doing or how they're doing it, but they do need to be considered and anyone feeling like sharing those secrets would be very welcome to do so. Are there any others we should be considering?" "Nehekhara," Elrisse says, "made of obelisks and pyramids, and the Mortis River itself. Walled off by border forts from Ka-Sabar to Zandri, across the southern border of the Badlands, and from Lahmia to Lybaras to Rasetra." You nod as you take notes. "Presumably Araby has one too," you say, "though I don't know whether I'd call that a separate network - it would connect to Ulthuan and work the same way as that of the Old World." You blink as something occurs to you. "Probably via the Sorcerer's Islands, I know someone who'd be able to confirm whether that's the case. So that makes five different polities, aside from Ulthuan, that are using the Waystone Network for their own betterment." Glances are exchanged around the table, as the unspoken thought hangs in the air that there's no reason there couldn't be a sixth. You consider the notes you've been taking. "The Rune, the capstone's metal, the foundational wheel, the leylines, the tributaries, and the other networks. Six different avenues of investigation for us to discuss further. It seems to me that this is a solid day's work, and a good point to leave off. Let's reconvene tomorrow to start planning how we'll investigate each of them." --- You consider your options as you round up Elrisse, Egrimm, and Tochter for an emergency meeting of Wizards of the Empire. What you've learned about the operation of the Waystone foundations makes the study of Waystones, and arguably their continued existence, a breach of the Articles of Imperial Magic. Naturally this strict reading of the Articles probably wouldn't last if it was brought to the attention of the proper authorities, as the Waystones are what's making life in the Old World possible, and Dragomas is favourably inclined towards the project. And you've already seen one Article 7 dispensation given out to Johann for his investigation of Skaven technology. But the process of going through proper channels could be one that would draw a lot of unwanted attention - you'd have to go via Algard, and since their Wizards would be involved, Alric, Paranoth, and Feldmann would need to be notified. Or you could bypass the proper channels and go over Dragomas' head to the Emperor via his charming wife, though it might rub Dragomas the wrong way. Or might not, he doesn't seem like one overly concerned with proper procedure. Or you could build an understanding among those present that doesn't need to go beyond the room. You could just all agree that while in Laurelorn, Article 7 might be set aside for the good of the Empire, and nobody needs to know. Or you could build a kind of justification that might not be able to stand up to proper scrutiny, but might allow everyone here to sleep at night - that you're operating as members of your respective ancestral Cults, of Halétha and Tahoth Trisheros and the Earth Mother, and so you need not concern yourself with Article 7. Alternately, you could leave the other Wizards out of the matter entirely. So far you have six different aspects of the matter to investigate further. It would be very easy to divide things up so that the other Wizards are all occupied with one of the other components, leaving the entire matter and its crimes to be dealt with by you and by those not bound by the Empire's laws. It's possible they might already have spotted the central problem and could be persuaded to pretend that they haven't, or it could be that it wouldn't have occurred to them yet. You spotted it immediately, but you're more familiar with Dhar than any Wizard should be, from your experience with Sylvania and Skaven and the Chaos Wastes - and, of course, from the Liber Mortis. What is immediately obvious to you probably wouldn't be to any other Wizard. Or you could just... accede to the law. Article 7 isn't really all that ambiguous, is it? You could just accept that you've hit an impermeable legal roadblock. It was set down by Magnus and Teclis, after all. Do you really think you know better than they do? [ ] College Dispensation Seek dispensation from Article 7 through proper channels from the Supreme Patriarch for the study of the Waystones. [ ] Imperial Dispensation Seek dispensation from Article 7 directly from the Emperor for the study of the Waystones. [ ] Cult Dispensation Cults are not under the authority of the Articles. Build a rickety framework of justification that this Project is under the authority of the Cults of Halétha, Tahoth Trisheros, and the Earth Mother, rather than the Colleges, and then have them grant you permission to study the Waystones. [ ] Conspiracy When there's no Witch Hunters around, anything's legal. Attempt to enter into an understanding with your fellow Wizards that what happens in Laurelorn, stays in Laurelorn. [ ] Ignorance The other Wizards don't need to know. Let them know that you'll take care of the study of the Waystone foundations, and they should restrict their attention to the rest of the mechanisms. [ ] Accede The law's the law. Wind down the Waystone Project, pack up, and go back home. - There will be a two hour moratorium.

Turn 38 Results - 2488.5 - Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] College Dispensation Tally "So," you say to the trio of your fellow Wizards. "I take it you all picked up on what Lecturer Sarvoi mentioned?" "Do you mean the part where the mechanisms keeping the world out of the grasp of Chaos is a sorcery that utilizes the wicked powers of Dark Magic?" Egrimm says, to winces from Tochter and Elrisse. "Yes, that. While that is rather startling news, I hope I'm not the only one here that thinks there's room for a more measured response than trying to put all the Waystones to sword and fire immediately?" "It can't have been the intention of the Articles that we'd start destroying the Waystones once we realized how they worked. The laws were set down by Teclis, after all," Elrisse says. "It might have been the intention that they would forbid us from studying them," you note. Tochter nods. "When he was forming our Order, he spent quite some time trying to convince us to stop using the ancient methods we had of drawing power from the Waystones, and only when we stood firm did he teach us the Elven method of pooling and drawing Ghyran from a Waystone - and only Ghyran, not the other Winds. The Elves believe that we should leave the Waystones be." "Baba Niedzwenka did say they reacted rather stroppily to Kislev having suborned theirs. Personally, I'm inclined to disregard Ulthuan's claim to the Waystones they abandoned four thousand years ago. Just as they have to acknowledge Laurelorn's independence, so too must they acknowledge that the Waystones that we've been killing and dying to protect ever since are now ours to do with what we will." "Uti possidetis," Elrisse agrees. "To that end, I'm inclined to seek a dispensation to continue our study into the Waystones - I need to get one for the Waystone Gold anyway, so I might as well get both at once and save myself a trip. I think it's a very straightforward argument that even if the Waystones are producing Dhar, they're not actually performing a sorcery with it, it's just allowing Dhar to flow towards the Great Vortex in the same way that water runs downhill. We don't accuse plumbers of having studied under the Elementalists in Nuln, do we?" You receive a round of agreeing nods in response. --- When you travelled to Altdorf Zoo and said to Dragomas that you wanted a word in private, you'd expected him to take you into a meeting room or perhaps a supply closet of some sort. Being taken through a series of heavily-secured doors that led into the chambers of the Imperial Dragon was not quite what you had in mind. "Does it mind?" you ask as the Dragon opens up a sliver of an eye and snorts a greeting towards Dragomas. "He's used to comings and goings. As long as you don't go near his treasure he isn't bothered." 'His' treasure. You wonder if the Dragon is aware that the Empire still considers it to belong to the state, and that there are promissory notes circulating using the hoard he rests upon as security. Normally there's a lot of resistance to any sort of currency that isn't made of precious metals, but gold being guarded by a Dragon is considered by many to be less likely to disappear overnight than gold secured in a more traditional vault. "Is he cleared for this discussion?" He smiles at you. "Dragons develop bestial cunning first, and true intelligence only after they've grown larger than this fellow currently is. Right now he's about at the level of a crow or a dog - clever, but not really the sort to eavesdrop." "Very well." You take a moment to get your thoughts back in order. "The Waystone Project has properly begun, but our partnership with the Eonir has uncovered something potentially tricky under the Articles. The mechanism the Waystones use to send magic towards the Great Vortex is based on the attractant properties of Dhar." He considers that. "That's the only transmission mechanism?" "There may be something about the leylines themselves that help facilitate it, but in the Waystones themselves, yes. Two or more Winds are put into diametric orbits around a core of Dhar and the whole package is dropped into the leyline, where the Dhar is attracted to the Great Vortex - the Eonir say this is because Dhar is naturally drawn towards the Aethyr." "And then they strip the Winds back out along the way. What if there's no Dhar around to be used?" "I suspect that the Waystones create some." "Ah." He considers that for a while. "I'll give you a dispensation to continue the study. If it turns out that there's no way around that mechanism it might be trouble for any hopes of creating entirely new ones, but no point wrestling with that here and now when we don't have all the facts. Who do you have from the Orders with you?" "Elrisse and Egrimm van Horstmann of the Lights, and Tochter Grunfeld of the Jades." "Didn't you have those Gold fellows?" "They're employees of the branch college, rather than formal members of the Project." "Then it's up to you whether to bring them under your dispensation, with the usual cautions about it falling on your head if they misuse it. I'll get ones made up for the other three." He purses his lips in thought. "And maybe have the letters informing their Magisters Patriarch left on their respective desks, rather than sent directly to wherever they are right now. Anything else?" "I'd also hoped for a dispensation for the study of Waystone Gold." "Right, that's not a problem. Same people?" You nod. "I'll send the paperwork through the usual channels. The Golds have a stockpile of the stuff from having absorbed all the pre-Teclisean alchemists, one of yours should be able to requisition some." "Thank you, Supreme Patriarch. That will be a great deal easier than having to find one we could afford to sacrifice." He nods. "Anything interesting come up so far?" You smile, and begin to tell him about what you learned about Kislev's Waystones. --- On your way to meeting with Adela, you'd reflected on the fact that none of the the three Journeymen who'd arrived in Karak Eight Peaks eight years ago had reached higher rank, but each had instead found a place for themselves in the organizations outside of the Empire. That train of thought is rather derailed when you find Adela wearing the robes of a Magister instead of those of a Journeyman. "Adela!" you say happily, giving the younger woman a hug in greeting. "When did you make Magister?" "I haven't technically, but the Bright Order brevets you according to your association with military units, and the powers that be decided that the Karag Nar Gunnery School counts. After the Chancellor and my aunt got married-" "The Chancellor of the Gunnery School? You mean Oswald?" She nods. "Is your family completely subsuming that institution?" She nods, completely unabashed. "Better them than a bunch of strangers, I figure. A lot of Nuln engineers will burn every bridge in the world to nab a secret of Dwarven engineering, they need someone breathing down their necks to keep them in line. My aunt's good at that, she's the one that got me to stop starting fires when I was a kid, back when we thought it was just a personal quirk instead of unrealized metaphysical attunement." You consider that for a while, then shrug it off. Francesco, Soizic, and Oswald are all sensible folk, so if they're not ringing alarm bells then things are probably fine, and you don't have enough hours in the day to make the inner workings of every organization your problem. "Anyway, after the marriage, I became a mostly official go-between for Dwarven and Empire and Undumgi engineers, with an attached rank and salary. So the Bright Order breveted me." You nod. "How's the masterpiece coming along?" She shrugs. "The launcher is sound and there's a lot of options for the payload, but it's the sort of thing that's useful to me specifically, rather than something with wider applications. I need to either simplify the steam half of it so that the average Bright Journeyman can use it, or minimize the magical component so that it can be used by non-magical engineers. Either way, I need a better grasp of steam and its workings." Now that's an opening. "About that. You know I've had a Gyrocarriage built for me?" "Aye, big news. First entirely non-military aircraft the Dwarves have built since the air barges of the Golden Age. Opinion's divided on whether that's a sign of hope or hubris." "Problem is, I can't find a full-time pilot for it, and having to organize my schedule in advance around whoever here needs training hours defeats the purpose of having the thing. I need someone skilled, trustworthy, reliable, and able to handle themselves in a fight, all of which are easy enough to find among the Dwarves, but the sticking point is I need someone who won't spiral into despair if their flying career doesn't involve dropping a single bomb on a single Orc. The Pilot Clans tend to be rather intense about that sort of thing." "To put it lightly. And you think I'm a good fit for the job?" "You get on with the engineers, you already have a solid grasp of steam, you can handle yourself in a fight, and I already know you. You being a Wizard makes clearance and chain of command a lot simpler. You'd be employed and paid through my branch college at standard rates, and though you'd have to swear oaths of secrecy for a lot of what you'd need to learn to take it on, I'm sure a lot of what you'd learn could be applicable to your inventions. The job will have a lot of downtime that you'll be able to put towards them, but you won't have a lot of control over where that downtime will be - a fair bit of it would be here, but otherwise will be wherever the job takes me. For now a lot of it would likely be at Tor Lithanel, other times it's in major cities like Altdorf or Talabheim or Bechafen, others it's tiny places in the middle of nowhere, like Fort Brachsenbrücke in Reikland or Resvynhaf in southern Kislev." She considers that for a while. "So I'd get paid to learn a lot about steam that the Dwarves otherwise would never tell me, and to hop around the continent to wherever you think is the most interesting?" You consider the current open questions of kurgans and obelisks, and the mystery of what's west of L'Anguille. "Possibly outside the continent as well." "Sounds like you've got yourself a pilot." --- After carefully negotiating the web of Guilds and oaths involved in getting a human taught as a Gyrocopter pilot, with some relief you shut yourself away from all of that. You've sectioned off a neat chunk of time with which you can get to the nice, relaxing activity of poking at the fundamental forces of magic to see if you can make them do anything unexpected. To that end you have a measure of Aethyric Vitae and a power stone. Your expectation is that it will just cause the Vitae to detonate, but it does not seem too unlikely that it will do so in a particularly reliable or novel way that might have some utility. By now, the procedures of setting up a proper testing apparatus in your Room of Calamity within the White Tower are straightforward, and before long you have a mechanism set up to introduce the fragment of Crystal Mist to a very small measure of the Vitae, and without further ado you provide the prod that causes the two forces to collide. In an instant the Vitae detonates, and you fruitlessly try to blink away from your Magesight the bright afterimages of exploding energy. You run an eye over the scraps of energies already beginning to flow out of the room, and frown to yourself. You gather a slightly larger sample of Vitae and repeat the experiment, this time with a slab of stone between you and the detonation to shield your Magesight, and once again you survey the energies present. Again, all are present except the Ulgu. You turn your eye to the Crystal Mist, and find it looking much as it always does: a coiled strand of Ulgu compressed into a ball, with not a scrap of unexpected energy to be found. You frown at it and pick it up, weighing it in your hand. Then you fetch some callipers. One more detonation later, you have confirmation: the power stone has grown slightly larger. That is, as far as you're aware, impossible. A length of a strand of a Wind is a constant, which is why all power stones are of the same size. But the counterpoint to that is obvious: the Orbs of Sorcery that Teclis gifted to the nascent Colleges, each an orb of pure magic the size of a man's head, much larger than any conventional power stone. A single one of them can allow for magical phenomena that would normally take an entire array of conventional power stones and be a lot easier to build around as well, and a socket for them can be found at the heart of the most potent and rarely-used Battle Altars of the Colleges. He never shared the secret of how they were made, and the most commonly-shared legend is that each contained a sliver of Teclis' own magical power within them. It seems you may have stumbled across another possibility: that the properties of the Winds, including that of the length of an individual strand, are more malleable at their moment of creation, and that when Vitae is detonated in immediate contact with a power stone, the primordial Ulgu adds itself on to the coiled strand within the power stone, rather than creating new strands of its own. You walk down to your library, stare in befuddlement at the bare shelves, then sigh as you recall that most of your books are now housed within Kvinn-Wyr. --- Quite a bit of careful study within your primordial library later, you confirm that an actual study of primordial Winds has not been undertaken by Wizards of the Empire for the simple reason that the only places that primordial Winds exist is at the poles, when a rift has been carved between reality and the Aethyr, and during the disintegration of a slain Daemon, none of which are particularly conducive to careful research. And, as you've become aware, the moment of the creation of Winds is one that is rather blinding to mystical senses. How do you derive useful insight from an event that is over in a fraction of a second, is invisible to conventional senses, and is blinding to unconventional ones? That aside, you do find mentions in Dwarven texts that Karag Dum Runesmiths have put forward arguments that there's a difference in the nature of the Winds closer to the pole than further south, though you can't find more than those tantalizing hints, and it's not like you can send them a letter to ask for their research on the matter. You return to your laboratory and repeat the experiment with the Crystal Mist a few more times until you're sure your calliper measurements are accurate, and then you sigh and return all the way back to the library - would it be wasteful to have Adela on hand to fly you back and forth from your home to the library? - to look up the diameter of the Orbs of Sorcery. By your calculations, it would take about eight gallons of Vitae detonated in this way to grow a power stone to the size of an Orb of Sorcery, but that would be wasting the other seven Winds contained within. You sketch out a device with which you could hold eight power stones equidistant from a central point, and on that point careful measures of Vitae could be dropped and detonated and allowed to congeal on the power stones before the next measure is introduced. Then you work on a device to automatically deliver and detonate those measures, because that seems like a long and tedious process to do manually, and then measure the viscosity of the Vitae so you're able to sketch out a set of tubes dripping Vitae into a Cup of Verena that should allow the entire process to be automated. Over a number of days, eight power stones plus eight gallons of Vitae should result in something the Colleges thought impossible: the creation of entirely new Orbs of Sorcery. Though that's quite a pleasing result, you find your mind continually drifting back to the question of primordial Winds, and the frustration that you can make it occur on demand but you're unable to observe it in any useful way. Something to pursue another day, because the time you set aside has already been significantly eaten into and you really should pay your library some attention while you're here. --- Right now, your library is large, echoing chambers filled with shelves and empty of people. And while on a certain level that does appeal to you, you have resolved that more people than just yourself will benefit from this library, and for that to happen you need staff. And for that, you have a decision to make: who will those staff be? The simplest route, you suppose, would be to simply copy what already works. The Colleges have tried and true mechanisms for setting up and maintaining libraries. A core of Perpetual Assistants and the careful vetting processes of the Colleges could skim the most promising and trustworthy of human candidates from across the Empire and build them into a staff able to construct a library of magic that is perfectly able to assist the studies of Wizards and ensure that the Library slots into the larger Collegiate ecosystem. Or you could turn to the Cult of Verena, to the scriveners of Clio and the calligraphers of Scripsisti. Nowhere will you be able to find a more dedicated and enthusiastic staff of aficionados of the written word, and they will work tirelessly to ensure that the knowledge within is as accessible as possible to those who visit it. And then there's the Dwarven equivalent: the Runescribes Guild. A staff drawn from them would be one where the proper organization and maintenance of the books within are guaranteed, as you've seen for yourself that a properly maintained Dwarven library can withstand the ravages of any amount of time. Or you can have a staff trained up from scratch. The easiest way to integrate the Library into the wider Karak is to recruit its staff directly from it, bringing in whoever is willing and able and training them as librarians. While this might not give you any distinct advantages, it does mean that the Library will be more properly part of the Karak rather than merely located within it, to the benefit of both. Or you could recruit from the Halflings for your librarians, the same way and for the same reason Belegar did for the Karak's farmers. Halflings are overlooked by many and resented by some, but the reasons for that are the same reasons they might make good librarians - they're quiet, insular, hardworking, and usually of modest ambitions. Or you could take a page from the book of the Light Order and start scouring the orphanages of the Old World, except looking for those suited to the book rather than the spell. As you know, a child without hope that is unexpectedly granted some is a deep and reliable well of gratitude, and by doing so you would be granting good educations and employment to those that might otherwise have little hope of it. Then there's the more exotic options. The We have been doing well enough for long enough that they're beginning to consider 'splitting', where a few Egglayers are birthed, given a coterie of Webweavers and an honour guard of Hunters, and go off into the world to find a new home for themself. At first the new We will be almost identical to the original, but over time they will diverge into entirely different individuals. While the current plans would be to establish then somewhere under Karagril so they can be conveniently close to the greenskins that are their prey, they could instead establish themselves in your library and dedicate themselves to the care and cultivation of your library. It will be a long and difficult process to teach them all that they'd need to know, but at the end of that path is a staff of librarians that are able to easily move in three dimensions, instantly communicate with each other, increase their numbers to whatever amount is needed, and be absolutely terrifying to anyone inclined to misbehave and might normally expect nothing more than a smack with a ruler and a stern look from a more conventional librarian. And then there's Cython. There's been a great many times when you've reflected that Cython's deep well of knowledge and experience might be of use, but there's precious little that you can offer it that it cannot already secure simply because its goodwill is greatly desired by the Karak it lives within. But there's one thing that might be able to lure it down from its peak for more than the occasional raid on your shelves, and that is if you offer it a large and ever-growing hoard of knowledge it will be able to call its own. There's sure to be difficulties in acclimating Cython to having intruders wandering around its hoard and its sure to consider itself a full partner in the library rather than a mere employee, and the task of recruiting the rest of the librarians will have to be granted to it so that it can hire a team it feels comfortable allowing full access to its hoard. But the full cooperation of an Emperor Dragon is something that you're fairly sure no other library can boast. From where will Mathilde recruit a staff of librarians for the Library of Kron-Azril-Ungol? [ ] Collegiate Will be a boon to any magical research, and will allow the Library become a seamless part of the larger Collegiate ecosystem. [ ] Cult of Verena Will ensure the goodwill of the wider Cult, and will make a Library dedicated to sharing truth and knowledge. [ ] Runescribes Guild Guarantees the proper organization and maintenance of the Library. [ ] Locals Will more fully integrate the Library with the wider Karak, to the benefit of both. [ ] Halflings Will be reliable, trustworthy, hardworking, and relatively incorruptible. [ ] Orphans Will ensure staff that is fanatically loyal to you. [ ] The We Spider Librarians. [ ] Cython Dragon Librarian. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Tragically you can only pick one, though some of these options will be available with minor modifications if/when you recruit a team of scribes for the Library. - If you have ideas for other possible sources for librarians, feel free to suggest them. - A note on libraries: The possessiveness of some potential recruits is not as much of a concern as you might think. in this era, most libraries only ever lend out books if they have multiple copies or to exceptionally trusted individuals. They don't work the same way as modern libraries, where almost everything is expected to go out the door on a regular basis.

Turn 38 Results - 2488.5 - Part 4

Spoiler: Voting results [*] The We Tally While you spend some time considering building greater ties to the local population of Karak Eight Peaks or trying to rope in Cython, in the end the We win out in your mind. Your long-term ambitions with the library depend on building up an institutional memory among those that will be taking care of its day-to-day operations while you're not here and eventually when you're gone, and if you can bring the We in, that instantly goes from a significant challenge to a given. And while they currently lack a great deal of even the basic knowledge they'll require for the task, all of that can be taught to them, but you can't really teach a librarian of any other species to be in constant communication and perfect harmony with the rest of the library staff at all times. You go over your pitch as you make your way to the We's nest beneath the Citadel, though you're quite certain they'll accept for rather complicated reasons. Though a We could be effectively immortal, their memories were not. Anything stored in one of the minds of a We would last only as long as the individual Hunter or Webweaver or Egglayer that contained that memory. For information to outlive its container required it to be repeated back and forth in the constant stream of communication that a We maintained, giving name to the concept of 'Echo'. But this requires some measure of conscious effort to do, is limited to the number of living minds within a We, and the turnover of those minds could be quite high when suffering from Warpstone poisoning, attacks by Skaven, and a lack of food. The We might have a much better chance at immortality than any given human, but though this frees them of anxiety at the inevitability of death, it's replaced with the angst at the inevitability of forgetting. The amount of memories a We accumulates will always increase, but the amount of memories they're able to contain is always limited by their food supply. The memories of the We you know could theoretically go back all the way to the genesis of the consciousness of the very first We, but instead they only become unbroken and reliable upon their arrival at Karak Eight Peaks. The concept of writing, of the ability to record information that can last indefinitely without requiring a constant caloric upkeep, has the potential to change the way of life of the We as thoroughly, though hopefully more positively, as necromancy did to the Nehekharans. "I hear that you're considering splitting," you say to the spokesspider inside what you take to be a meeting room within its nest, as the floor is free of webbing and they have acquired a few battered chairs from somewhere. "Sufficient food, very good many-food. Black-Crag-green-four-legs hunting is four-eighths sufficient, small-food is one-eighths sufficient, gold-food is three-eighths sufficient. Gauntlet-We will be closer to Black-Crag-green-four-legs, can hunt deeper into their tunnels. Could also hunt in old tunnels of the smaller-not-green-four-legs, or in the above. Different nest in different place, will learn different hunts. Gold-food means can spend much time learning without no-food." "That's actually what I wanted to speak to you about. Would a split-We be able to live on only gold-food?" There's a moment as the Webweaver considers that, its pedipalps wavering uncertainly. "If Karak-We has enough gold-food," they conclude. "But for what purpose?" "I am building a great book-nest, with books from the Karaz-We and the Empire-We and all the other biggest-Wes. Normally not-green-four-legs would act as Webweavers to keep it clean and organized, and as Hunters to protect it. But not-We are only ever one, so this would need many not-We, and each not-We would need to learn how to tend and protect the book-nest. But a split-We would only need to learn once, and would then only get better at tending and protecting." "Book-nest for you?" "For all not-food of the Karak-We's many-foods." "You would let other-We take your books?" they asks, pedipalps drooping in befuddlement. "No. They may read the books and take it into their Echo, or pay not-food-gold to have copies made. But the books will remain, and be added to, and only ever grow larger. If anyone seeks to take books that are not copies, they must be defended against." It chitters in agreement at that. "Where is book-nest?" "The mountain known as Kvinn-Wyr." You think for a moment, and then point. "That direction, at about this depth." "Near larger-not-green-four-legs above-tunnel?" The human gate, so the Eastern Gate. You nod. "There are old tunnels of smaller-not-green-four-legs near there. Split-We will be able to hunt them." "They would." You suppose it makes sense that a being so used to getting sustenance through hunting would be hesitant to give it up entirely, and the We hunting in the old mines would make it easier for when the Karak gets around to reclaiming them. Or, you belatedly realize, they might be worried about food security, as they're yet to fully grasp how deep the Karak's pockets are, and how much deeper the We's silk might make them. "And the split-We could still exchange silk for gold." "Karak-We has hunger for silk enough for two We?" they ask. "Karaz-We and Empire-We has hunger for silk. Enough hunger for many more We." The room goes silent as the constant background noise of the hive's activity goes silent, as the entire attentions of the We are focused upon this decision. "Split-We will try book-nest," it eventually declares. "If many-food continues, split-We will build We-nest in book-nest. Otherwise must no-food to Black-Crag-tunnel." You smile at the warning. "That is acceptable." "We will lay eggs for split-We. Will be ready for split in..." It takes a while to think. Above-ground timekeeping has not come naturally to the We. "Six-eights above-fire." Six weeks, then. Thankfully, the base-eight thinking of the We translates easy to an eight-day week. "I will have the masons ready to build a chamber or chambers for their nest to their specifications, and I will organize trainers to teach them how to maintain a book-nest." That last bit is easier said than done, but the reputation of a Dwarven King is a useful thing. You smile to yourself as you picture the announcement soon to be distributed to scholarly guilds and learning institutions throughout the Old World. 'King Belegar of Karak Eight Peaks seeks Loremasters and Scholars to train a colony of large and non-hostile spiders in librarianship...' --- When you received Branulhune, you had thought that the sheer force its Runes allowed it to strike with meant that any defence against it would be fruitless. But the Expedition to Karag Dum taught you that there are beings fast enough to catch Branulhune mid-swing, and there are beings with the favour of Gods that are quite capable of overruling even Kragg's Runes. The paradox of an irresistible force and an immovable object might make for an interesting thought experiment, but the middle of combat is no place to be testing it. The Rune of the Unknown might allow you to bypass even the swiftest or most durable of defences, letting Branulhune disappear just as it was to impact a parry or block and reappear on the other side to continue on to strike the opponent. In a way, the idea of the guard bypass is similar to that of the momentum dump, but where the momentum dump takes advantage of the fact that Branulhune is motionless when it is summoned, the guard bypass is at war with it. When you swing a greatsword at an enemy you're putting a lot of energy into that strike, and Branulhune disappearing and reappearing might bypass defences, but it appears without the speed it had an instant ago. Imperial greatswording techniques have no answer to this problem, but this is where the influence of the Order of Guardians begins to shine. Like all Dwarven martial styles, they take it for granted that they might need to fight in confined spaces, so they have a series of drills and techniques to increase swinging power without needing a full wind-up. [Branarhune training: Martial, 9+23+7(Library: Greatswords)=39.] It takes some trial and error to adapt the ones that Gunnars taught you into something that can be applied mid-swing, and then a lot of practice to be able to trigger it at what would have been the moment of impact and then to resummon the blade in time. Due to safety measures built into the Rune itself, Branulhune refuses to be summoned when there is something in the way, which Kragg only gives a few dire hints about before disappearing back into his workshop, but you glean enough for it to be clear that it's for similar reasons to the dangers of Substance of Shadow. Reality is built on the assumption that all matter has its own space, and using magic to break that rule tends to have unpredictable and dangerous consequences. Wizards are cautioned not to, but Runesmiths just don't let you. So you don't just need to flicker it away and back again, you need to be able to identify and swing in an arc where there is space to resummon Branulhune inside the opponent's guard. It would be a vast understatement to say that this presents significant logistical challenges. While it is possible to deactivate the Runes on Branulhune so it can be maintained and sparred with safely, it is not possible to deactivate individual Runes, so you cannot safely practice with the Rune of the Unknown against any living person without making it extremely likely that person will end up extremely dead. You take up a training blade the size and weight of Branulhune and spend some time within the training halls of the Undumgi anyway, having those that wish to hone their defensive skills block and parry your swings while you study the way they do so and do your best to identify where the guard bypass might be used. Then you have the carpenters of Karag Nar build you a series of training dummies in the shape of where those opportunities exist. The dummies prove absurdly fragile, of course, but the silver lining to this is that it gives you more incentive to get it right, as obliterating a training dummy with a mistimed strike to the guard that blows right through it is immensely frustrating when you only have a few dummies a day to work with. At the end of a few weeks of this, it would be a vast overstatement to call yourself happy with the results, especially compared with the results of developing the quick-draw. But short of seeking out some novel means of practicing it or honing it in live combat, it's about as advanced as it's going to get. You do your best to convince yourself that you're content with that, and turn your attention elsewhere. [Branarhune aspect developed: guard bypass. Remaining aspect: hand switching.] [Branarhune stretch goal identified: double tap. Strike at an enemy's guard, let the impact damage or destroy what they parry or block with, dismiss and resummon Branulhune to rid yourself of the rebound energy, then swing again using the Order of Guardian's techniques.] --- "I believe it to have belonged to a cultist of Stromfels," you say to the Hochlander as you lead him down the alley. "And then they came off second-best in some kind of cosmic turf war with Manhorak, a local god of floodings and wetlands, leading it to sink into the ground and then be built over. This alley is currently only accessible by the street, which only I have the key to, and by the tavern, the owner of which I have an understanding with." He frowns at the unassuming shack that the trapdoor is built into. "More comings and goings means that this might not be sufficient. The other doors might be boarded up, but there's more windows than I like overseeing the alley." You nod. "If you acquire the tavern outright you could build the entrance into it. Or you could use the sewers for comings and goings like the local criminal element do." "No other inhabitants down there?" "None that I encountered during my own comings and goings. It could be that the War Below hasn't spread this far yet." You climb down the ladder, taking up a lantern that you kept by the entrance, and run an eye over the room. That there's a thin layer of dust instead of a layer of mud over the furniture you left behind proves that the foundations are solid, at least. "Any remnant of Stromfels?" the Hochlander asks as he climbs down after you. "No, I exorcised Him in favour of someone more cooperative. I'd recommend either maintaining the shrine for those of your employees who might share the same faith, or sealing it up and using another room if you wish to set up a shrine to someone else. Either way, you'll probably start getting cats coming in and out again once there's people here to annoy. Putting out food for them will keep the vermin out." You walk him through the excavated rooms, and he nods as he runs a critical eye over the bookshelves that once contained your very nascent library. "Surprisingly dry," he concludes. "I'd thought that might be a problem if there was paperwork coming in and out, but it looks like this should be fine. I'll map out the local tunnels, figure out the comings and goings and see if it'll be possible to connect directly to the EIC building. What are the possibilities for expansion?" "I never did map out the full extent of the building, and the digging paid for itself with what I was able to salvage from under the mud. Once you hit that limit, it's up to you whether you think it will be easier to build downwards or buy upwards." "This should do nicely." You nod, and can't fully keep a nostalgic smile off your face as you take another look around. "It was a lucky find," you say, "and I'm glad it'll see more use." --- The Windsoak mushrooms have been hovering in the back of your mind for a while now, as you vacillated on whether to treat your inability to create Chamon and Shyish variants as the project being incomplete or as an immutable fact of the inherent properties of those Winds that you need to accept. But in the end you decide to publish what you have and let the rest of the academic landscape wrestle with the problem instead. You are a Grey Wizard, after all, and if you could be said to specialize in anything, that thing is not mycology. If the field of thaumomycology is to be developed, and then those of of necrothaumomycology and alchemothaumomycology invented, it will be by others. Perhaps in a greenhouse of the Gold Order or in a Garden of Morr somewhere there exists the crossover of skills that can achieve this, and the entire point of academia is that you don't have to spend your limited time and energy seeking those people out. You can simply publish and let those with interest and expertise in the subject take the next step. [Writing the book on Windsoak Mushrooms, Learning: 12+29+7(Library: Sevir)+2(Library: Dwarven Agriculture)=50.] It proves to be something of an uphill battle, and for quite a while the only progress you make is getting your notes properly organized and hammering out the proper vocabulary for describing the processes. While you are rather familiar with the Winds, you're less so with fungi, and if it weren't for your books on Dwarven agriculture to work from you might have hit a rather significant roadblock. You can't quite recall when and why you acquired those, but you're glad you did. By the time you take a break from it, you've described what you know of the origins of the mushrooms and carefully detailed the procedures for creating each of the mono-Wind varieties. Reading back through it is something of a challenge, but while it might not be the most gripping work you've ever produced, you suppose a book on mushrooms was never going to be a page-turner. [Book on the Windsoak Mushrooms: 1/2 actions completed.] --- Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The five with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Laurelorn [ ] Max The entire time you've known Maximilian, he has been pursuing his own goal of true transmutation via magically-enhanced blacksmithing. Check in to see how he's going with that. [ ] Thorek See what inroads Thorek has made with the Major Houses of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Magister Tochter Grunfeld Get to know Tochter Grunfeld, ritualist, traditionalist, and veteran of the Sylvanian Campaign. [ ] Zlata Get to know the young woman who is the Ice Witch contribution to the Waystone Project. [ ] Lector Aksel Learn more of the Hedgewise who venerate Halétha, Goddess of the Forest of Shadows. [ ] Lecturer Sarvoi Learn more of the Hekartian understanding of and relationship with the Winds. Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Gretel She's apparently getting involved in the Karaz Ankor's ambitions in the Border Princes. [ ] Okri The new Loremaster of Karak Eight Peaks is Okri Drakkisson of Clan Bronzebeard, formerly of Karak Norn. Meet your replacement and gauge what kind of person he is. Foreign Relations [ ] Stirland See for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. [ ] Middenland See how the Ulricans are going with their new Eonir coreligionists. [ ] Karaz-a-Karak To investigate their preparations for the Mount Silverspear campaign. [ ] The Black Water Canal Pay another visit to the canal project, and see if there's any further signs of sabotage. Friends Abroad [ ] Roswita Get a sense for who will control Sylvania after you turned down the position. [ ] Kasmir See how his partnership with Sylvania's native faith has been going. Following Up [ ] Brief the Emperor Though the Waystone Project is in very early days, the sheer amount of disparate traditions you've brought under the one roof could be seen as reason enough to boast to the highest authority. [ ] Amber College Check in on the salamanders. [ ] Gold College See what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Organ Vat Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Skull River Ambush Look into the investigation of the mining of the Skull River, and any consequences of it. [ ] The Weber Estate Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. - There will be a two hour moratorium.

Turn 38 Social - 2488.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) [*] Zlata [*] Lector Aksel [*] Lecturer Sarvoi [*] The Weber Estate [*] Organ Vat Tally "So," Senior Lecturer Emeritus Sarvoi says to you in an open-air tavern built into the side of the Library of Mournings. "Tell me about this," he says, gesturing to your shadow as it inspects a jar of olives inset into the bar. You give him a scrutinizing look. "You don't know what it is?" "I know nothing of your understanding of what it is." You accept that with a nod. "We call it an 'Arcane Mark'. It is theorized to be the visible effect of a partial transmutation of the soul into a Wind, or something partway between Wind and soul-stuff. It comes from exposure to large amounts of insufficiently-controlled Wind, usually from miscasting. It is considered inevitable, even desirable, among the Orders." He nods slowly. "It would make you incapable of wielding any other Wind, but that is the way of your Orders anyway, isn't it?" "It is possible for someone to change Orders, but not after they have developed their first Mark." "Immutably bound to a single Wind, and unable to touch any of the others without flooding themselves with Dhar." He looks at you with something like pity. "To an Elven perspective, perhaps. How long does an Elven Mage study for?" He nods thoughtfully. "To think that you are not yet forty and already half-spent. I can see how that would alter your perspective. If you don't have the years to master them all, then what value is there in retaining the potential to?" "It's more than that. Here, catch this." You lightly toss an olive in his direction, and he catches it obligingly. "How long have you practiced catching olives?" "Not at all, of course. I take your meaning, but for that to be true..." He frowns, and looks back to your shadow. "Well, it clearly is true, isn't it? It is literally a part of you, now. Instead of learning it in the abstract, you have made it a part of your being, and you control and understand it as such. You don't have to learn fundamental Sevirrics in the same way a child with a ball doesn't need to learn ballistics. This is an underpinning of your Orders?" "Not just ours. It's also the method of the Dragons that schismed from the Caledorians and bound themselves to individual Winds." "Oh?" he says, curiosity growing. "Is this conjecture?" "An Ice Dragon resides in Karak Eight Peaks," you say with a smile. "Not quite as a citizen, but as a neighbour, and I have found that I share some interests with it. Its embrace of Hysh has advanced to the point where it is light and magic where once it was flesh and blood, and it has said that my Marks are a step down the very same road. A road that I do not believe exists for Qhaysh." He looks at you for a while longer, then begins to titter. "Oh, very elegantly framed," he says with glee and sincerity. "To not just say that embracing a singular Wind is a handicap or a shortcut, but an outright rival to the holistic approach. Is this your own theory, or something your Orders have been working on collectively?" "A bit of both. Teclis made no secret of how Sapherian doctrine would feel about the way our Orders learn magic, and nor have the guest speakers at Tempelwijk. It is something we have been grappling with for our entire existence, and we have developed several schools of thought over whether our inherent mutability is a handicap or an advantage." "And what do you think?" "I think I like being what I am." He smiles. "Who could ask for more?" --- "There's something I've been wondering about," you ask him a while later, after several more cups of wine. "When I spoke to Councillor Isthien to bring him in to the Project, he only attached conditions if the Project got to the state of constructing new Waystones. I'm wondering why that is. Does he see the job ahead of us as particularly easy?" He gives you a smile. "I would not claim to know the mind of the Councillor, but I doubt he thinks so." "Then why? He considers that. "The Waystone Project is perceived by many as a way to build bridges to the Empire," he says, slipping into the tone of someone used to explaining things to an audience. "Its continued existence is a continued success for Laurelorn's foreign policy. Even if nothing comes of it, working alongside major figures from the Empire and Kislev and the Karaz Ankor reassures those among us that think that Laurelorn might be condescended to, or that Nordland's troops might spill over into the Ward of Frost at any moment. The involvement of the Grey Lords or the Ward of Frost doesn't change that perception. But bringing in a Major House very easily can, as if an isolationist House becomes part of the Project, then that gets a lot murkier. And if you're looking for a Major House to contribute magical theory, the choice is between four Houses - Tindomiel and Vaire of the Hekartian school, and Echthelion and Thyriolan of the Hoethian school. Of those, all but Tindomiel are isolationist." "So if he named a price I balked at and I went to one of the other three Houses, House Tindomiel would be to blame for robbing the cooperative clique of a victory." "There are those that could make that argument." You mull that over some more. "Just by walking in that door, I'd cornered him." Sarvoi smiles, but says nothing. "He couldn't let me walk out of there without making a deal. If he'd let on, I could have pushed for concessions from him. But not only did he avoid that, he also set his house up nicely for if the Waystone Project turns into a huge success." "What's the difference between a Mage and a politician?" You give him a questioning look. "One tries to wrestle poorly-understood forces into submission for personal gain despite the fact that it could all blow up in his face and ruin the lives of everyone around him, and the other casts spells." You can't help but join him in laughter. --- Zlata stares forlornly out over a park full of Elven athletes. "They had me swear a vow of chastity," she bemoans, "and sent me to the land of beautiful men." "We are all called on to sacrifice for our peoples," you commiserate. "Hopefully our business here ends on good terms," she says with a heartfelt sigh, "so I can return after I am promoted." You give her a moment to wallow in her yearning before you broach the subject you have in mind. "There was something of a confrontation between you and Baba Niedzwenka earlier." She shrugs, seemingly unconcerned. "This was expected. Baba Niedzwenka is always trouble. Has been since before Kislev was Kislev." You consider that. "Is it an inherited title?" "Nie. Just her. Ice Witches eventually rejoin the winter, but Hag Witches get old quick and some stay old forever. She used to be worse, but still likes to interfere with Ice Witch business." She sighs. "Maybe that's why I was sent. If it was an older Witch, they wouldn't be able to help themselves, would keep trying to out-Witch her." She shrugs. "The leylines in Kislev are Ice Witch business, but anyone with Witchsight can see it and anyone with common sense can guess the rest. Ulthuan knows, Za knows, the Fire Spire knew." You frown as you consider that. "What happens when one of the four falls?" Praag did during the Great War Against Chaos, and both Erengrad and Kislev City came close. "That is why Castle Alexandronov was built. There used to be only three, the old cities of Norvard and Dorogo and Srebrograd, but if you have three and lose one it collapses. If you have four, you can lose one and fall back to the others and retake and rebuild later." You consider fishing for more information on that subject, but decide against it. The Ice Witches have already agreed to contribute, and will do so in their own time. "Why is it, do you think, you were selected for this?" "Beyond having nothing more important to be doing? Because I can read and I can speak Reikspiel." "Is that unusual for Ice Witches?" "The reading more than the Reikspiel. Most Ice Witches are from peasant families. Some say because they are closer to winter and the land, others say it's just a matter of most Kislevites being peasants. So most are only really taught the secrets of Ice Magic and the doctrines of the Ancient Widow. I've heard things were different before Kattarin, back when we had a proper Ice Court and the Ice Witches shaped the bloodlines of the Boyars, but for now the only Ice Witches that can read are the ones that were taught to as children. My parents were traders in Kislev City, so I was one of them." You nod. "I take it being an Ice Witch wasn't a career path you would have expected as a child." She gives a short laugh. "No. And I did sometimes resent it, because I grew up expecting to see the world, like in tato's stories. But now look at me." She smiles at a particularly shirtless group of Elves jogging past, their muscles gleaming. You talk with Zlata a while longer, and the overall impression you get is that what you see is what you get - she's fairly competent, fairly scholarly, and fairly out of her depth. And while you might have preferred an Ice Witch of greater age and experience like Ljiljana or Věnceslava, there's something to be said for someone who's too intimidated to play games, and won't do anything but her best. --- The high and gleaming walls of Tor Lithanel are its last line of defence, but its battlements are patrolled only by those who wish to admire the view over the trees. This is the norm for the capital of Laurelorn, and yet has only recently been restored, as when humans encroached as nearby as Schlaghügel the city had felt vulnerable enough for a full-time watch to be needed. It is up here you find Aksel, staring moodily out over the ocean of canopies. "What do you think of the Loren Lauroi?" you ask him as you approach. "Compared to what I know, it's like the difference between a dog and a wolf. Is this what the Forest of Shadows could become?" You look out at the trees as you consider that. "I suppose it's possible," you eventually conclude. "Though likely no time soon. The Elves have cultivated this forest for thrice the age of the Empire, and I doubt it was so welcoming when they first arrived." He sighs. "I suppose so. I don't know whether to be jealous or pitying of them and their tamed trees." "If you wish to do the same, or something like it, you may have an advantage over them. The Eonir venerate Isha above all, but Her domain is all things that grow, and this forest and those within it are just a sliver of it. Halétha is a much more local Goddess, so much more of Her attention would be reserved for your struggle. If we can restore and expand the Waystone network, it should be possible to change the nature of the Forest with Her help, whether that be simply to be less welcoming to Chaos or whether that be to shape it as dramatically as the Elves have theirs." He nods, though he doesn't seem convinced. "I suppose we've got the same goal as everyone else, make our homes a little less Chaos-y. That's the sort of goal that can bring just about anyone together. Worked for Sigmar, worked for Magnus." "Lofty company to be in." "Lofty goals." "So everyone keeps saying, but I'm not so sure. Back when Chaos was flooding the world, everyone was doing it. I think the reason everyone forgot wasn't that literally everyone has fallen from some mythical global golden age, I think it was just too expensive to bother with when the problem was solved. Now it's not quite so solved, so we just have to dust off what we used to know and get to work." "Is that how you'll put it if you succeed?" "Gods no. If we pull it off I'm definitely painting us all as the equal of Caledor Dragontamer." He chuckles and nods at that. "So, bit of a strange question, but does Halétha have any siblings?" He gives you a considering look. "We're not the Ostermarkers, but that doesn't mean our faith is a completely open book," he says, his tone neutral. "If there's nothing you can tell me, that's fine. I've just encountered the name Haleth a time or two." He seems to relax. "Oh, that. Yes, some of our people in larger towns disguise some aspects of their worship, and those half-truths have grown into almost separate faiths as outsiders see their success and attribute it to what they know of their God. Lady of the Hunt in the west, Patroness of Childbirth in the south, God of Journeys in the east. It rubs some of the hidebound the wrong way, but nobody can deny how useful it can be to have allies outside the Forest." You ponder that. "Do you think they worship truly out of ignorance, or do you just worship different facets of the same being?" "Oh, don't get me wrong, I don't see their worship as lesser. If I was speaking to one of them I'd put it more diplomatically." He gives you a worried look. "Erm. I'm not, am I?" You weigh for a moment how much truth to give, and eventually say simply, "I worship Ranald." He nods in understanding. "Like our brothers in Middenland. No wonder you think in aspects. But no, I don't think I know the full truth of Halétha. Nobody knows every face of any being. I do think I worship Her most important facet, but I'd guess the others do too. And if I found myself lost in the Western Oblast or seeking to father a child in Middenland, I would gladly accept any help or teachings they'd be willing to share." --- On your way to your next meeting in Altdorf, you make a detour to the Great Library of Altdorf to leaf through their texts on Kislevite faith, and a few hours of effort finds you a few scant paragraphs on Kalita, called by some the God of Journeys. At first glance He seems to be a poor fit for Halétha and most Imperial writers would seem to agree, describing him as a rival or aspect of Handrich, but one of the books contains the God's sigil: a singular point with roads branching downwards from it, a more angular mirror of the tree-root scars ringing Aksel's arm. It's not very difficult to see how such a thing might have come about if a little imagination is applied: a trader of Kislev on the dangerous roads of Ostland hearing a partial description of a God that might protect them from its dangers, and they find enough success to adopt that faith for their own and with a sightly garbled name. Gods do have a tendency to sprawl when they have the opportunity, don't they? And Ranald is attempting to make inroads into the sphere of commerce as Ranald the Dealer, perhaps His daughter is following in His footsteps. You tear yourself away before you get too mired in crafting theories out of nothing and make your way to the Grey College for a meeting with the Dean, the person ultimately responsible for all recruitment and education efforts of the Order. Not the same Dean you occasionally encountered as a student, as time marches on and he retired a few years back. His replacement is Magister Tomaso Mugnaio, known to most of Altdorf as Tomas Muller, a man earning a good name in the Guild of Stevedores for the prison sentence he's supposedly serving in Mundsen Keep for a crime committed by their Guildmaster. Actually serving that sentence would be a waste of a perfectly good Wizard, so he's also serving as Dean in between occasional appearances looking suitably miserable yet stoic as part of the prison's work gangs. "Lady Magister Weber," he says to you as you enter his office, his accent impeccably dockyard Altdorfer and rather out of place in an academic setting. "Thank you for coming." "Of course, Dean Tomaso. What can I do for you?" "Apprentice Eike Hochschild," he says, taking a folder from a pile. "I understand you have a stake in her education." You nod. "I work with her grandmother in a trade concern in Stirland, and Eike's to inherit her grandmother's stake in it." "The EIC, yes. I've encountered them a time or two in my other job, they're a nightmare to suborn. Was Eike named after the company?" You blink. "I never noticed that, actually. I don't believe so, she was named by her mother, who wasn't involved with the EIC back then." "Glad to hear it. By all accounts the girl has taken to the mysteries and habits of Ulgu like a duck to water, her teachers describe her as bright and inquisitive, and she spends a fair bit of her spare time in the library. The only potential problem of note is that she's rather open and expressive about what she thinks, which is nice to have in a student but could develop into a weakness for a Grey Wizard. She's also on track to graduate out of Junior Apprentice in the first half of next year, which means it's time to start talking about who her Master is going to be. Starke and the Bursar have both expressed an interest, but you're the one that brought her in and you're probably going to be inextricably tied up in her future, so unless Algard decides he wants her as his Apprentice it's going to be up to you." You nod thoughtfully. It's a matter you've given no small amount of thought to yourself in the past few years. An Apprentice is a big commitment and would require some work on your part, but the point of Junior Apprenticeship is to get the student to the point where they'd be at least as much help as they are a hindrance to their future Master, so she shouldn't be an outright encumbrance. After all, you spent most of your time with Regimand assisting him with research and translations, tagging along on the occasional adventure within Altdorf, and performing projects he pointed you at and left you with. Your role as her Master wouldn't be to tutor her one-on-one for months at a time, but to allow her the opportunity of learning from her experiences as she assists you in your endeavours. If you decide against taking her on, then your word will carry a lot of weight in where she'd end up. Wilhelmine's interest is to be expected, considering the woman's pet project of making sure the economy of the Empire serves the Empire, but you're not as sure what Starke's angle would be - perhaps he thinks her faith and forthrightness makes her a good match for his responsibilities. If you don't like either, then Regimand is also a possibility. He's pretending to be retired for longer and longer stretches these days which suggests his actual retirement might not be that far off, but plenty of Wizards spend their twilight years training successors, and you're fairly sure you'd be able to convince him to do for Eike what he did for you. Who will Eike's Master be? [ ] You Eike will become the Apprentice of Lady Magister Mathilde Weber. [ ] Wilhelmine Eike will become the Apprentice of Lady Magister Wilhelmine von Bucht, Bursar of the Grey Order. [ ] Starke Eike will become the Apprentice of Lord Magister Reiner Starke, Porter of the Grey Order. [ ] Regimand Eike will become the Apprentice of Magister Regimand Speiseschrank. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - I hope it is unnecessary to remind thread participants to keep the coming debate civil. - If you decide to take Eike on as your Apprentice, then she will begin at the start of Turn 40, so you will still have the coming turn before she enters your care. - Eike's affinities were rolled for here.

Turn 38 Social - 2488.5 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] You Tally You hadn't been entirely decided, but hearing about Eike's development into what seems a lot like your younger self settles the matter. "I'll take her on," you say. "I move around a lot, but I've got Ulgu-only rooms that will allow her to continue her education in both Karak Eight Peaks and Tor Lithanel." He nods. "Ah yes, your World's Edge Branch." He makes a few notes. "Very well, I'll have word sent to you when her graduation tests are scheduled, which will likely be in the summer. If you can make it yourself that does tend to make an impression on the Apprentice. At your rank it's generally assumed that the only one who is qualified to teach your understanding of Ulgu is you, but we do have a course that is tailored for Magisters taking on their first Apprentice if you feel like you would benefit from it." You nod. "Is there some sort of ritual or ceremony for taking on an Apprentice?" You'd asked Regimand that about a month after he'd officially taken you on, and he'd told you that it had already been done. You never managed to get a straight answer out of him as to whether he meant that some part of your esoteric early lessons had incorporated that, or whether your presence hadn't been required for it. "If you believe your Apprentice would benefit from one, we have templates available of many themes and styles, and agreements with the Ambers and the local Cults to use their facilities for such. If you want to get really elaborate, just wave a bag of silver within earshot of the Breughel." Of course that wouldn't have a yes-or-no answer. You thank the Dean for his time and the information. --- Anatomy is a rather fraught science in the Empire, as the demand for legal corpses so that physicians and anatomists can learn their trade greatly outstrips supply, leading to a black market price of ten crowns or more for a fresh or well-preserved corpse. Rising to this opportunity are the criminal enterprises known as Resurrection Men, who at best consist of grave robbers and crooked embalmers and grave wardens, and at worst consist of those who turn to more direct methods to ensure a supply of fresh corpses. This would be reason enough to earn the attention of the Amethyst Order, but that this illicit industry provide necromancers with cover to acquire raw materials for their twisted art makes it one more front in their eternal war against those that misuse Shyish. Grim business, but one fortunate side-effect of this is that the Amethyst Order always has a few Wizards who circulate in those circles and as such require a working knowledge of anatomy to blend in. One such Wizard is Magister Margarete Schluchtbuck, a short-haired and pretty young woman as skilled with a scalpel or pistol as she is with the Wind of Death. She cheerfully receives your visit and guides you through the dusty hall of the Morrite cathedral that the Amethyst College is somehow within, and despite looking for it, you're unable to spot the point where one gives way to the other and are quite surprised when you reach the office marked with her nameplate. "Let's see," she says, rummaging through shelves filled with preserved creatures and organs. "Ah, yes. I haven't had the privilege of having a Rattus sapiens upon my table, but in this case it was no obstacle to identifying the organ once I got one out of that goop. Do you recognize it?" In the clearer liquid you can make out enough to see that it's spongy-looking and vaguely triangular, but that doesn't really narrow things down for you. "Can't say I do." "Glandulae renibus incumbents, though significantly larger than what I usually see. We each have two of the very same organ within us, perched atop our kidneys like a jaunty hat, and it's actually the centre of something of a controversy within anatomist circles, over whether it should be properly labelled ad-renal or supra-renal. Humoralists call them capsulae atrabiliarae, believing it to be an instrument for the creation or storage of black bile. The rest of us, being burdened with the obligation to actually investigate and test instead of being able to make it up as we go along, were a little more in the dark, and in truth few had given them too much attention. One more weird wobbly bit in a body full of 'em. But if our downstairs neighbours are going to the trouble of collecting and preserving them in a warzone, it stands to reason that there must be some significance to them. So I rounded up some physiology students and pointed them towards the slaughterhouses, and before long they were able to reliably extract the fluid within. Unfortunately for you and me, but fortunately for the advancement of knowledge, one of them blabbed to the Physicians Guild, and now those buggers are running around giving it to everyone for everything. I can't get them to stop - might be there's not a power in the world that could get them to stop selling the latest nostrums - but I can bully them into telling me what they've found, and I have." She opens a drawer and pulls out a notebook and flips through it until she finds what she's looking for, and continues on. "Drinking it does nothing but make the physician richer, as expected, but things get interesting when you're a bit more creative with it. Applied as a vapour has proven very effective as a tonic against croup and anhelitus, but when injected it causes the subject to feel anxious and jittery, of all things." You consider that. "That sounds like a perfectly reasonable reaction to being stabbed by a physician, regardless of the substance involved." "I tried it myself. The heart beats faster, the body sweats, the hands shake, fatigue is banished. Rather similar to the feeling one gets during a confrontation." "Might this be related to the phenomenon of 'Black Hunger' among the Skaven?" "I suspect so, in which case replacing or supplementing an oversized version of the same gland would drive them to even higher heights and lower lows, which seems like just the sort of thing they'd be liable to dabble in. I don't know if there's any use to that facet of the discovery, but personally I'm delighted that their experiments have inadvertently advanced our grasp of anatomy and medicine. There's a pair of papers making their way through the Colleges, one from me and one from the Physicians Guild, and though they beat me to the punch I did badger them into giving us some credit." You skim a copy of her paper, and nod. A pity that part of the credit had been poached, but before you entered this office you had no idea that there were results worth poaching, so there's a limit on how upset you can rightfully be. And this paper, competently-written and kicking apart a pet theory of the Humoralists as it does, is something you're happy to have your name attached to. "Thank you for your work on this." "No, thank you, Lady Magister. This has given me a significant amount of credit within the circles I work in, and that's going to do a lot of good for the causes of the Amethyst Order within them." [A Novel Treatment for Croup and Anhelitus, 2488. Subject: Common, -1. Insight: Revolutionary, +2. Delivery: Dull, -1. Contributor, -3. Useful, +1. Total: +1 (minimum).] [The Function of Glandulae Renibus Incumbents, 2488. Subject: Common, -1. Insight: Shattering, +3. Delivery: Competent, +0. Secondary Author, -2. Thorough, +1. Varied, +1. Popular, +1. Total: +3.] --- It's been seven years since you last paid a visit to your fief. Part of you frets at this, but the reason this land was chosen for you is that it can take care of itself while you're taking care of the rest of the Empire. Besides, it's not like you've abandoned them entirely, as you left them with instructions to contact you via the EIC if anything was amiss and left the EIC instructions to keep you informed of any significant dangers in the area. As neither has done so, you're reasonably certain that there's nothing to worry about, though despite this you're still at least a little relieved when everything looks intact from the sky as your Gyrocarriage approaches. It's not the first time you've visited here by air and the locals are interested but unworried, save for a dog that stands between the Gyrocarriage and the crowd as it lands, barking at the strange, roaring metal beast that has intruded on its domain. You learn that the headsman you knew is still given the respect due to a headsman, but over the years the unofficial authority has unofficially migrated to his son, Rolf, your Steward for these lands. You find him older, more confident, and now with a flock of his own and several children, one of whom is named Mathilde. He leaps straight to business, showing you a trio of rams kept in a fenced-in area of pasture just outside the keep. "Estalian mayor sheep, m'lady," Rolf says. "Imported from Averland, who imported them from Tilea, who stole them from Estalia. You did tell me that if I saw an opportunity to invest I should take it, and I had your EIC check the seller to make sure they were reputable." He pauses as if waiting for you to react, and continues on once he's sure you're not going to do so. "It has a reputation for very fine wool, but more important, they're smarter than the average sheep. Problem we're having up here is the ragwort, it springs up all over the place if other plants die off and leave room for it, like during drought or if you overgraze. So in bad times there's more ragwort than anything else, and it's poison if a beast eats enough of it, and sheep ain't got the sense to avoid it. The mayor sheep is smart enough not to eat too much of it, and almost as tough as the local breed, so we're breeding them in to the local flocks." You give a thoughtful nod, as though you're at all qualified to pass judgement on animal husbandry. "I see. That seems a sensible idea." "I'd also like to bring in some East Westerlander rams to try to improve milk production in our ewes. You said I could make improvements without asking, but problem with these is that they're a lowland sheep. I could let the mayor sheep out with the other flocks tomorrow and they'd be mostly fine, but lowland sheep don't do well up here, and it could take generations of crossbreeding them until we get something that does. Until then I'd need to bring in provender from Tarshof, that'd come to a shilling per head per month, more during the winter, so maybe as much as a crown per head per year. To maintain a breeding population until there's enough of the local blood in them to survive up here, without breeding out the extra milk..." He inhales through his teeth. "Could get as high as a hundred crowns, and no guarantee that it'd prove worth it in the end." "I'll give it some thought. Any concerns in the area?" "Nothing out of the ordinary, m'lady. The Elector Countess' men have been coming through the towns checking taxes, but I've kept ours paid up proper. Widened what could be paid in kind, too, and there's more roadwardens around lately, so nobody's grumbling too much." He thinks for a moment. "Top Walter lost an eye to a hawk that tried to take one of his sheep and got tangled in the wool, but he sold the feathers for enough that he says he got the better of the deal. The Wagners, silly buggers, kept drinking from a stream from which they shouldn't've, almost lost their youngest before they saw sense. The Senns are feuding with the Ankenbauers again, but that keeps happening and it never goes beyond shouting and insulting each others' cheeses. Rumour has it they might be building a new road round here, but nobody can agree whether it'd be Tarshof to Pürgg, or Sonningwiese to Pürgg, or Sonningwiese to Ohlsdorf, or Tarshof to Biberhof. Was a time when a few'd be talking about joining the work to make some coin on the side, but digging up flint is closer to home and pays better." He scratches his chin. "Think that's about it, m'lady." You let the wave of bucolic mundanities wash over you with a faint smile. Worlds away from your concerns of Waystones and interprovincial rivalries, the people of this fief need worry about nothing more than the weather and the wildlife. You're not sure if you would have found the same sort of peace if you'd remained in this sort of life, or if you would have been driven mad with boredom, or if you would have ended up clawing your way into a position not unlike Rolf's out of sheer need to meddle in the world around you. And speaking of which, the decision is now yours whether to okay his ambitious plan for animal husbandry. Judging from the rattle in the chest that Rolf digs out of his vegetable garden, you've got more than enough funds to do so. 836 crowns have accumulated at your fief. [ ] [FIEF] Approve Will cost between 20 and 100 crowns over the coming years. [ ] [FIEF] Approve plus Jade Wizard Put word out that there's good, easy work here for a Jade Journeyman. Will cost between 70 and 150 crowns over the coming years. [ ] [FIEF] (Write in) Alter this plan in some other way, or suggest some completely different plan to improve the fief. [ ] [FIEF] Deny Make it clear that the mayor sheep was a good investment that you're happy with, but this one is too uncertain and expensive to be the same. [ ] [CASH] Take all [ ] [CASH] Take half [ ] [CASH] Leave it [ ] [CASH] Other amount (write in) Library Purchases: [ ] [LIBRARY] Colleges of Magic Name four magical, non-divine topics to acquire all available Empire books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Barak Varr booksellers Name three public topics to acquire all available Empire and Dwarven books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Library of Mournings Name two non-magical topics to hire Cityborn scribes to copy all available Laurelorn books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Back-fill. Instead of seeking books on specific topics, give a very broad direction and have your bookselling contacts grab everything on it that you don't already have, with special attention to existing but incomplete topics. Possible categories: Dwarven religion, human religion, geography, war and combat, social science, natural science, applied science. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - How much of the credit you'd get for the organ vat results and how much was poached was rolled for here. - Even if Mathilde cleans out the coffers, she'll make it clear that the fief is allowed to use future accumulated taxes to make improvements. - The current state of the fief can be found in the Organizations threadmark. - The mechanics of the back-fill option for the library have tweaked.

Turn 39 - 2489 - The Waystone Project

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [FIEF] Approve plus Jade Wizard [*] [CASH] Take half [*] [LIBRARY] Colleges of Magic: Apparitions, Powerstones, Aethyr, Wild Magic [*] [DWARF] Greatsword with Rune of the Unknown, for training (1 gallon AV) [*] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [*] [PURCHASE] Books on Greatswords (Extensive Dwarven) Tally After some thought you give Rolf's breeding project your go-ahead, and make a mental note to send word to the Jade Order that the services of a Journeyman would be welcome here. The lure of guaranteed safe work and welcoming locals means that your fief won't go long at all before one of them adds your fief to their rounds and lends magical assistance to the tupping and the lambing. To that end you take half the funds stashed in the chest and leave the other half to pay for the project and any future expenses. Other recent expenditures include an influx of books from the Colleges on some esoteric topics, a few volumes from the Order of Guardians on their greatswording techniques, and from Kragg - indirectly, as he'd sent the job off to a Runesmith whose great-great-great grandfather had learned the Rune from Kragg and threatened a dire haranguing if the knowledge has been lost in a mere five generations - you have a training blade for practicing the techniques of your nascent combat style, Branarhune. Though it is, of course, very well-made, it is still a training blade, as its composition was made to mimic the weight of Gromril rather than for hardiness in battle, and it was made with blunt and tough edges, rather than ones that could easily be ground or hammered into sharpness. Kragg has called the blade 'Branithune', and though as a verb it could be interpreted straightforwardly as 'practicing Branulhune', as a noun it is very easy to interpret it along the lines of 'precocious beardling who's up past their bedtime'. You suppose that's what you get for coming to Kragg with a job he feels unworthy of his skills, and there's not many on the continent who'd get off so lightly if they did so. --- With the Waystone Project finally begun, your options for pursuing it have branched significantly. On top of the four significant components of the standard Elven Waystone - capstone, runes, foundation, and leyline - you'd need to reverse-engineer to be able to build one of your own, you've also uncovered several other interesting facets that could be worth investigating. There's the other forms of Waystone built by the Belthani, the Scythians, and grown by the Eonir, there's the entirely separate networks scattered throughout the continent used by various peoples for various purposes, and there's all kinds of nexuses, both functional and lost, that could stand further scrutiny. There's also the question of fully mapping out the network, because from the sound of it the nexus network has a worrying amount of bottlenecks that could block the flow of half the continent if something happened to them. If the fall of one or two foreign cities would doom the entire Empire, that's something you think that the Empire should be aware of. You have five action points (AP) you can apply without engaging in overwork. For every two AP spent across all members of WEB-MAT, including recruiting new members, you can spend one 'free' additional AP with any member of WEB-MAT. WEB-MAT actions are performed by Mathilde alongside that person when possible, such as studying something alongside that person, cowriting a paper together, one teaching the other, both of them learning something new, et cetera. Current overwork status: [+] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. WEB-MAT: Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which two papers or one book will be written. WEB-MAT: Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Lord Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, Light Wizard [ ] EGRIMM: Attempt a Windherder enchantment with Egrimm (specify what) [ ] EGRIMM: Learning: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] EGRIMM: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Other [ ] WEB-MAT: Hunt an apparition with a member of WEB-MAT (specify who and which) [ ] WEB-MAT: Attempt to recruit someone to WEB-MAT (specify who) [ ] WEB-MAT: Enchant or otherwise modify your Gyrocarriage (specify how) (NEW) The Waystone Project, Recruitment [ ] Attempt to bring an Order into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a non-Order magical tradition into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a human Cult into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (specify which) The Waystone Project, Research (NEW) [ ] Waystone: Capstone [ ] Waystone: Runes [ ] Waystone: Foundation [ ] Waystone: Leylines [-] Waystone: Build an Elven Waystone Requires Capstone, Runes, Foundation, and Leylines to be fully and successfully completed. [ ] Waystone: Nexuses Specify which: Marienburg (Almshoven and Fort Solace), Forest of Shadows (Brass Keep, Blood Fane, Tower of Melkhior), Reikland (Axe Bite Pass and Grey Lady Pass), Mordheim, Los Cabos, Bugman's Brewery. [ ] Waystone: Tributaries Specify which type: Belthani, Scythian, Lornalim. [ ] Waystone: Mapping Specify two of: Empire, Bretonnia, Tilea, Estalia, Border Princes, Araby, Badlands. [ ] Waystone: Other Networks Specify which: Karaz Ankor, Kislev, Laurelorn, Athel Loren, Nehekhara. For the above options, as well as any option-specific specifications, also state who you will be researching this with. You can specify as many or as few members of the Project as you please, as well as bringing in people from outside the Project if you pay for their services or convince them in some other way. If the only ones involved are members of WEB-MAT the action can count as a WEB-MAT action. In general the fastest progress will be made by involving only those with the most applicable knowledge, but also keep in mind how each individual might feel about being included or excluded in a particular investigation. Lovely Laurelorn [ ] Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Explore one of the Wards of Laurelorn (specify which: Storm, Rain, Frost) Self-Improvement: [ ] Receive training: specify who and what. (acquaintances may train you for free, or you can hire someone with money or favours) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Attempt to gain control of one of your Arcane Marks (specify which) [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. Aethyric Vitae (18 gallons): [-] Create Orbs of Sorcery solo (requires one of each Power Stone) (insufficient CF) Mathilde will have full control over what happens with the resultant Orbs, including the option of presenting the full collection as a shockingly impressive fait accompli. Any Power Stones Mathilde does not have will be acquired for 5 CF each. [ ] Create Orbs of Sorcery with College buy-in (no cost) Mathilde will not have to source her own materials, but will have to negotiate in advance what happens with the resultant Orbs. [-] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. Can only be taken alongside an action to learn how to create power stones. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item: specify what and how (current skill level allows for Fiendishly Complex spells and lower; you may use Windherder to attempt to enchant something with spells from different Winds) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to codify Rite of Way so that others can learn it. [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff (specify for whom) (optional: specify from what) Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in current affairs: specify what and how. Current examples: Eastern Stirland pacification, Marienburg affair, Black Waters project [ ] [ ] [ ] Travel to Nagarythe at the invitation of Ambassador Daroir, and join their eternal war against Naggarothi invaders for three months. Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting or ingratiating yourself with someone else: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 200 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Eastern Stirland EIC Handler: The Hochlander The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Improve and expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (optional: specify how) [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. [ ] EIC: Investigate what trade goods the Eonir might be willing to import from the Empire. Kron-Azril-Ungol Status: Being colonized by a new We, not yet open to the general public. The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] Go about recruiting an army of scribes so you can start copying entire libraries of material. [ ] The many legends about the amount of books contained within and under Castle Drakenhof still haunt you. Organize an expedition to mine the ruins for books. [ ] Seek the publishing contacts to start acquiring large amounts of books from a nearby realm (specify which: Bretonnia, Kislev, Tilea/Estalia, Araby) Gives wide and easy access within a language, but is subject to local restrictions and is a less efficient use of the Library's acquisition budget than other methods. [ ] Seek an exchange arrangement with another Library or a Karak's archives to be able to make copies of their corpus (specify which, eg: Great Library of Marienburg, Great Library of Altdorf, Ancient Library of Carroburg, Karaz-a-Karak Archives, Karak Vlag Archives) Difficulty will depend on the size, prestige, and disposition of the library in question, and the relative impressiveness of Kron-Azril-Ungol. [ ] Seek an agreement with a Cult to have access to their libraries (specify which, eg: Verenans, Myrmidians, Sigmarites) Difficulty will vary heavily depending on the Cult in question, but can allow access to rare tomes and esoteric subjects. [ ] Set up a no-questions-asked bounty system for books within the Cult of Ranald Results will be unreliable and depending on what is sought may result in blowback, but this may allow you to acquire books that would otherwise be entirely inaccessible. Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. [ ] The Father Ranald's daughters, and Their followers, will recognize you as being worthy of trust and faith. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Books and rubbings from an Asur explorer of Lustria and the Southlands Ghyran Nut Kurgan Shrine to Mannsleib Kurgan enchanted weapons Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Observations on the Windfall north of the Dark Lands (FADED) Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (FADED) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. Windsoak Mushrooms (missing: Chamon, Shyish) (1/2 completed) The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a eight twenty hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - The option 'Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments' has been removed, as Mathilde is now familiar enough with the substance and its reactions to be confident that there's no useful applications or new information to be found by pursuing it. - A map of the Old World's Waystone nexuses based on Mathilde's current knowledge and speculations can be found here, courtesy of @ScarabShell

Turn 39 Results - 2489 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan: Ordnance Survey -[*] Waystone: Tributaries (Belthani) (Tochter, Cadaeth, Aksel, Niedzwenka, Zlata) -[*] Waystone: Mapping (Empire, Border Princes) (Egrimm, Johann, Max, Aksel) -[*] Waystone: Leylines (Sarvoi, Hatalath, Zlata, Elrisse, Thorek) -[*] Receive training: On the Education of Apprentices (100gc) -[*] Receive training: Powerstone creation methods (100gc) -[*] EIC: Investigate what trade goods the Eonir might be willing to import from the Empire. -[*] KAU: The many legends about the amount of books contained within and under Castle Drakenhof still haunt you. Organize an expedition to mine the ruins for books. --[*] The Gambler: KAU: Drakenhof -[*] SERENITY: Write a book: Windsoak Mushrooms (2/2) Tally After two years of preparations, the Waystone Project has finally, actually begun. You refuse to let the enormity of the task ahead of you get to you, and you've decided to start chipping away at the problem from three directions. First, a basic fact-finding survey of the network of nexuses in the Empire and Border Princes so you can finally know for sure how many points of failure there are between the Empire and the western half of the continent. Second, an examination of what seems like the lowest-hanging fruit: the Belthani tributary waystones. And third, a first inroad into studying the Elven Waystones themselves by examining the leylines they feed the magic into. You've split up the contributors to the project amongst them so that everyone has a part to play, but without separating most of the potential trouble points - the High Luminary with the Hekartian, the Ice Witch with the Hag Witch, the Runelord with the Grey Lord, the Druidess with the Haléthan. If there are going to be problems, better to meet them head on and deal with them early than to try to forestall them and have them finally erupt when you're hip deep in disassembled metaphysics. --- It seems likely to you that there will not be any such thing as an unclaimed nexus. In your experiences so far this has meant Jades and Taalites, but as you go further afield it stands to reason that the forces that may have laid claim to local nexuses would be not quite as intertwined with Imperial society. Aksel, of course, represents one such example of an unintertwined party, and after working with them for over a decade you're confident Max and Johann will follow your lead. But Egrimm, the fifth member of the cartographical coterie you have in mind, might be more of a sticking point. So before you gather your party and venture forth, you take Egrimm aside to feel him out on the matter. "So far," you say to him, "we know of two extremes: nexuses controlled by the Empire's institutions, such as the Waystone at the heart of the Jade College, the Horn of Taal, and the Runestones of Gross Selon, and nexuses controlled by our deadly enemies, such as those in the Forest of Shadows. But as we start poking into the dimmer corners of the Empire, and especially as we venture into the Border Princes, it becomes likely that we'll encounter those in the hands of more ambiguous parties - the Article 13 sort, rather than the Article 15 sort. It would be best if we're all in agreement on how to handle that before we actually encounter it." Egrimm smiles. It can be hard to tell with him, but he seems amused. "And you're worried I'd be particularly hidebound on the matter?" "I thought it best to be sure. I know being taken for granted is a sore spot with you." His smile fades a bit, but he nods. "Put like that, I see where you're coming from. Don't worry, my conscience can accept turning a blind eye to a lesser evil." "It might be more than that. If it comes to it, I've got clearance from the highest levels to directly work with any equivalents to the Hag Witches that might exist on our side of the border." He gives you a long, searching look. "I may have oversold the Cult of Tahoth Trisheros to you, if you think they're still enough of a power to control nexuses." You frown at him. "What?" "Isn't that what you're getting at?" "No, I'm just trying to find out if you'd expect us to go right to the Witch Hunters if we find a bunch of Hedge Wizards worshipping a nexus in Hintertupfingen or whatever." "Oh, I thought-" He shakes his head. "No, I'm really not going to lose any sleep about letting a few bumpkin Magickers go free. It'd take us a decade to get across a province if we stopped to chase down every herbalist and talismonger." That will do. "Glad we're on the same page, then." --- With mutual understanding finally achieved, you bring everyone together to start consulting a map. "Right," you say, pointing at Marienburg. "Start at the 'mouth' of the river. Marienburg itself has a nexus within it, which connects to Fort Solace, which connects to Couronne. This is the only confirmed route we know of out of the Empire. Fort Solace is a new construction, built to replace Almshoven after the Great War Against Chaos, and that the Asur went to the trouble of erecting it makes me worried that it might be a single point of failure for the eastern half of the continent. Our first job will be to confirm that, and to see if we can narrow down where in Marienburg their nexus might be." Despite recent tensions, Marienburg is a cosmopolitan trade city whose gates are open to all, so you have no trouble moving in and out of the city as you perform your mystical survey. Though it's hard to spot against the blinding torrents of energy flowing from Altdorf and on to Fort Solace, you're greatly relieved to find a trickle of outbound energy heading west-southwest, which must be heading towards the Gisoreux Gap and presumably onwards to Gisoreux itself. That still leaves Marienburg as a possible single point of failure, but it does mean that Fort Solace is not. These three leylines also allow you triangulate the position of Marienburg's nexus to the fortress of Rijker's Isle, once the seat of the Elector Count of Westerland and, as the Directorate does not trust any one of their number to control such a symbolically and strategically important location, now a heavily-garrisoned prison. --- "Upstream, Reikland. Marienburg connects to Altdorf, whose nexus is the heart of the Jade College. It connects to Talabheim and Nuln, and once connected to a place called 'Athel Yenlui' that previously offered another path through the mountains. We'll do a lap to be sure, but I'm almost certain that it is no longer connected to anywhere else." After Marienburg you keep your eyes peeled for even a thin trickle of outbound energy which you presume to indicate a currently-unused 'backup' leyline, but you find nothing but the bright streams coming in from Talabheim and Nuln. Aksel tries to get in touch with his counterparts in Reikland, but with the Reikland Hedgewise engaged in some sort of theological conflict with the Sigmarites and therefore being especially hunted by the Templars, he's unable to do so. --- "Next, east to Talabecland. I believe the Horn of Taal to be Talabheim's nexus, and I know it connects to Gross Selon in Ostermark, and we'll be checking it for any other incoming connections. From pre-War of Vengeance maps I've seen, the Elves used to have a string of colonies along the Wolf's Run, so I suspect a nexus in Hochland somewhere." You're able to confirm that the stream from Altdorf disappears into the Taalgrunhaar forest that the Horn of Taal is somewhere within, and you leave it at that instead of investigating further and finding out for yourself how stringently modern Taalites follow the old tradition that any outsiders looking upon the Horn of Taal would have their eyes put out. You do a great lap of the Taalbaston and sure enough find a stream of energy coming in from the north, which you follow up the Wolf's Run to Hergig. Your first suspicion is the Hochland College of Sorcery, but you follow it instead all the way up to the ancient fortress of Hochergig at the heart of the city. The Hochlanders claim that in the time of Sigmar it withstood the assault of Nagash just as well as Taalaheim, Fauschlag, and Marburg did, and that the largest beastherd the continent has ever seen shattered upon its walls. In other provinces these are laughed off as the petty boasting of the Empire's smallest province, but standing at the foot of the ancient fortress you find it rather easier to believe. Onwards from Hergig you cross the border and find yourself led to the unassuming barony of Kienbaum, whose single population centre is a town of the same name, centred by a modest castle. The guards on the keep find themselves rather alarmed to be presented with a bevy of Magisters, and you have no trouble talking your way into the central courtyard, which rather incongruously has a small, locked shed in its centre. Inside that - as the castle's steward has appeared and proves rather easy to browbeat into opening it - and covered by a sheet is a familiar shade of gold, the tip of a waystone that must have its foundations deep in the subbasements of the castle. Actually intruding on the castle itself would be more trouble than its worth, so you thank the locals for their time and move on. The third and, it seems, final stop on this unexpected relay is Castle Lenkster, the fortification guarding both the border with Hochland and one of the larger valleys leading into the Middle Mountains. Local legend has it that this is where the Dwarves of Karaz Ghumzul left the Middle Mountains for the last time, and on the way through they laid a curse upon the mountains. This comes as something of a surprise to you, as you know for a fact that Karaz Ghumzul was abandoned four thousand years ago, and these curse-laying Dwarves must have been leaving just as the ancestors of the Empire were first arriving in these lands. The garrison of Castle Lenkster are state troops reporting directly to the Elector Count of Ostland so you refrain from trying to browbeat your way in, but you do a lap of the walls to confirm that this is the end of the line. Perhaps the fall of wherever was next in this chain of nexuses is either caused by or contributed to the abandonment of Karaz Ghumzul, and the 'curse' the locals remember was a severe uptick in nastiness crawling out of the Middle Mountains now that the ambient magic was no longer being drained away. You return to Talabheim and reunite with Aksel, who has been making contact with his fellows in Talabecland. These, he tells you, are even more insular than most Hedgewise, and apparently practice a variation of the Old Faith that brings them into conflict with the Taalites. Though he doesn't get much out of them, he does learn that their legends tell of what had once been their own fortress nexus to guard, similar to the Brass Keep of the Forest of Shadows Hedgewise, but with even more tragic a fate. You find yourself overcome with an eerie sense of repetition as you hear of the Marcher Fortress being drawn into the realm of the Lord of Excess, its guardians doomed to be corrupted at the leisure of the resident Daemons. --- "Ostermark I've already investigated and I don't fancy a trip into Mordheim without a lot more preparation, so next would be Wissenland. We find the nexus in Nuln - bets on the tower of the Dark Lady of Nuln? - and then we check for any other connections. I'm hoping that there's a way through the mountains, even if it means it goes through Athel bloody Loren." Huh. Not the tower of Magister Matriarch Elspeth von Draken, but the Iron Isle, the place that the Elector Count Konstantin von Liebwitz offered you when he was trying to recruit you as his Spymaster. Had he known that and assumed you did too, or is it a coincidence? In any case, you do a lap and not only find a stream coming in from a direction that does heavily suggest Bugman's Brewery, but also one from exactly east. Had there been a nexus in Stirland the entire time and you'd failed to notice it? You consult a mental map - Franzen? Vigaun? and then put the matter out of your mind for now. One nexus at a time. You will not, you decide, disturb the ruins of Bugman's Brewery if you don't have to. The tale is one you can't spend long amongst Dwarves without hearing. Clan Dragonback, the Royal Clan of Ekrund, helped found Karak Norn, and the Dragonback King-in-Exile became the consort of its ruler, the first Queen to rule a Hold of the Karaz Ankor. This should have permanently intertwined the Dragonback and Ironpick clans, but for reasons unsaid part of the Dragonbacks splintered off and came to the lowlands, adopting the name of Bugman and establishing a settlement. Or, to those who have seen the ancient maps of the Old World of the Golden Age, re-establishing the Hill Dwarf settlement of Kazad Thar. Then came the time of Dieter IV and the devastation of Waaagh Grom, and Bugman's Brewery was destroyed, its ale looted, its people killed or taken as slaves. When Josef Bugman returned home from delivering a shipment of ale to Dieter IV to find nothing but ruins and blood, he and his remaining companions went after the Goblins responsible in the hopes of rescuing their families. It is here that the tale trails off into dark murmurs and oaths of vengeance, and Josef Bugman and those that follow him still pursue vengeance to this day, seventy years later. As you circle the ruins of what was once the most renowned brewery in the known world and find a torrent of energy flowing in from the west-northwest, you begin to guess at the rest of the tale of Clan Dragonback. Why would part of their Royal Clan walk away from a place of honour in Karak Norn to build a brewery in the lowlands? For duty. Because atop Karak Norn, you now have no doubt, somewhere in that forested plateau upon which grows the finest wood of the Karaz Ankor, is a nexus. What would be the only nexus standing between the Empire and a slow slide into the realm of Chaos if the Rijker's Isle nexus was destroyed. --- It's with some relief for your younger self that you cross from Stirland into the Moot, glad that the nexus at least wasn't literally in your backyard, and you find your path taking you to the Halfling capital of Eicheschatten. You spend some time staring at the towering stone maypole at the centre of the public green - 'the largest maypole in the Empire!', you remember being told when you spent a night in a tavern here - and smile. There's a single other connection here, and you follow it just south of southwest into Averland, where, Aksel says, the Hedgewise claim direct descent from the Priest-Kings of the Brigundians. Your path leads you to the crossroads town of Heideck, somewhat famous for the extensive Dwarven catacombs it is built atop. Somewhere in it, is is said, are sealed chambers filled with riches. Usually the ones saying that are the ones selling 'authentic' maps to credulous visitors, but there's no denying the catacombs exist, as extensive research has been done by the sort of academic who would rather poke around an ancient ruin than go ask the Dwarves the questions they seek the answers to. Somewhere in there, you now have reason to believe, is a sealed chamber wherein one can find a nexus. It would, it seems, be the last nexus in the chain, a fact that you triple-check before you accept, as Heideck's location seems ideal for a leyline to pass straight down Black Fire Pass from the Border Princes. Perhaps somewhere in the mountains is a destroyed or deactivated or incomplete nexus that once would have bridged north and south. You part ways with Aksel here, and you, Egrimm, Johann, and Max make your way through Black Fire Pass and into the Border Princes. It is said to be a dangerous place to travel through, but the ones that say it are not Wizards. Any one of you could probably conquer just about any polity within the Border Princes, and the four of you together would probably be able to get a fair way through conquering the entire region before the Colleges notice and tell you to cut it out. It is an area poor in just about everything except for greenskins, who pour in from the Badlands at will. That it is populated at all relies on two things: that the population can retreat to the sheltered valleys in the shadow of Karak Izor to wait out any invader, and that there's a certain kind of person that will accept living in even the smallest pond as long as they can be the biggest fish in it. Your first stop, and the last bit of proper civilization you're likely to encounter in the coming journey, is Barak Varr. At first you begin to believe that it isn't a part of the Karaz Ankor network, but slightly east in its foothills, in a point your compass and map tells you is exactly southwest of Karaz-a-Karak, you find the deep, steady thrum of energy connecting Barak Varr to the rest of the Karaz Ankor. A long slog through inexplicably populated wasteland later, you find yourself at the city-port known variably as Matorca or Matorea, depending on which local faction one is a part of, which manages to find some semblance of wealth on the back of salt deposits and a sheltered cove at the mouth of the Tana Dante River, at the other end of which one can find a mountain path leading to Karak Hirn. It even has something resembling prestige, as it is here that the imprisoned Tilean philosopher Imaschiavelli Venedetto wrote his seminal work on statecraft. The Border Prince, filled with frank advice on assassination, treachery, slander, and war, had its printings sell out in Tilea and banned in the Empire. And somewhere in the crumbling palace that the philosopher was imprisoned within can also be found a nexus. You consider and eventually decide against forcing your way through what passes for guards here to seek unneeded confirmation and instead follow the energy southwest. You pass through Achaes, a town built on nothing in particular with its crude huts clustered around the base of the nexus like nervous chicks clinging to a mother hen, and onwards to Myrmidens, which is in something of a geopolitical grey area. Most maps agree that the line between Tilea and the Border Princes is the Wrecker's Run, but on the tip of the Black Peninsula one finds Myrmidens, a colony of Luccini and twin to Monte Castello on the other side of the Bay of Wrecks. Both were built on the ruins of ancient Elven citadels, and both, it seems, are home to a nexus. Looking at your map once more, you're once more struck by the absence of any link between the Empire and the Border Princes. If Karak Hirn had a nexus in the same way Karak Norn did, then it could link Matorca to Bugman's Brewery. Or if Barak Varr was, then it could bridge Matorca and a nexus on the southern end of Black Fire Pass. And then there'd be one more link between east and west, one step further from the Empire being cut off from the Great Vortex. The Border Princes is, you reflect, about as far as you can get from Ulthuan without leaving the continent entirely, both directly and by sea. Perhaps it's simply a matter of the network not being complete before the Sundering caused Ulthuan to withdraw from the Old World for centuries, or before the War of Vengeance ended the alliance between Ulthuan and the Karaz Ankor for good. Or perhaps the Karaz Ankor and the rest of the network weren't always so separate. All this time staring at maps has resulted in a fair few observations on your part. Praag, according to your map, is exactly west of Karak Vlag. The Gross Selon runestones, likewise, are exactly west of Karak Ungor. Mordheim is exactly west of Karak Kadrin. Eicheschatten is exactly northwest of Karak Varn. Matorca is exactly west of Barak Varr. Perhaps the Karaz Ankor network was not built entirely separately. Perhaps it was once connected. That the Eonir noticed Karak Eight Peaks reconnecting would suggest that at least a ghost of a connection between the two still lingers. Perhaps it was severed long ago, perhaps out of spite, perhaps out of caution, and perhaps the Dwarves found that once the rubble had been cleared and the bodies buried from the Time of Woes, they no longer knew how to reconnect it. You finish writing your encoded notes and share nothing of these suspicions with the others. - An updated map of the Old World's Waystone nexuses based on Mathilde's current knowledge and speculations can be found here, courtesy of @ScarabShell